<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>


<midrash>
    
    <verse>Of David. A psalm. The earth is the LORD’s and all that it holds, the world and its inhabitants.</verse>
    
    
    <midrashim>
        <source>
            <midtext>Midrash Ein Yaakov </midtext>
            <edition>Glick Edition</edition>
            <midpass>Rosh Hashanah 4:1</midpass>
        </source>
        <p>Fol. 31) We are taught in a Baraitha: R. Juda said, in the name of R. Akiba: <quote>"What [song] did [the Levites] chant on the first day of the week? <ref>(Ps. 24)</ref>
            The earth is the Lord's and the fulness thereof, because He [the Lord, in establishing the world] took possession and gave [His creatures] possession 
            (invested them with life), and [became] the Sovereign of the world. What did they sing on the second day? (Ib. 48) Great is the Lord and greatly to be praised, 
            because [on that day] He divided His works [the heavens from the earth] and reigned over them. On the third day they sang (Ib. 82) God standeth in the 
            congregation of the mighty, because [on that day] He, in His wisdom, caused the earth to be revealed and the world to be prepared for its occupants. 
            On the fourth day they sang (Ib. 94) O Lord, to whom retribution belongeth, because [on that day] He created the sun and moon, and in the future He will punish 
            those who would worship them. On the fifth day they sang (Ib. 81) Sing aloud unto God, our strength, because [on that day] He created the birds and the fishes 
            [which bring] praise to His name. On the sixth day they sang, (Ib. 93) The Lord reigneth. He is clothed in majesty, because [on that day] He finished His works and 
            became sovereign over them. On the seventh day they sang (Ib. 92) A psalm, a song, for the Sabbath day; i.e., for the day that is a perfect rest." </quote>
            R. Nechemia said : <quote>"What reason had R. Akiba to make distinctions among these sections, [for the last refers to a future event, while all the others refer to the past] ? 
            We must therefore say that they sang that psalm on the Sabbath day, because He rested."</quote> This is contrary to the opinion of R. K'tina, for R. K'tina said: 
            <quote>"The world will last six thousand years, and one thousand years it will be waste; as it is said <ref>(Is. 2, 11)</ref> And exalted shall be the Lord alone on that day"</quote> Abaye, 
            however, said: <quote>"Two thousand years it will waste; as it is said <ref>(Hos. 6, 2)</ref> He will revive us after two days."</quote></p>
    </midrashim>
    
    <midrashim>
        <source>
            <midtext>Midrash Ein Yaakov </midtext>
            <edition>Glick Edition</edition>
            <midpass>Berakhot 6:2</midpass>
        </source>
        <p>Our Rabbis taught: "It is prohibited to enjoy anything of this world without saving a benediction, and he who enjoys [the least thing] in this world without saving a benediction defrauds
            [the Lord]. What shall his remedy be? Let him go to a learned man." What can a learned man do for him when he already has transgressed the prohibition? "But," said Raba, "let him go unto a learned man first; 
            study the laws of benedictions that he may avoid sacrilege." R. Juda said in the name of Samuel : "He who enjoys [the least thing] in this world without having said a benediction is considered as if he had enjoyed
            something of the things dedicated to Heaven, for it is said (Ps. 24, 1.) Unto the Lord belongeth the earth and all that filleth it." R. Levi pointed out the following contradiction: "It is written (Ib. ib.) Unto 
            the Lord belongeth the earth and all that filleth it, and it is also written (Ib. 115, I6.) The Heavens are the Heavens of the Lord; but the earth hath He given to the children of man. It is not difficult to reconcile 
            [these two verses]. The former refers to the time before he pronounced the benediction [it still belongs to Heaven], (Ib. b.) and the latter refers to the time after he pronounced the benediction [then it belongs to man]."
            R. Chanina b. Papa said: "He who enjoys [anything] in this world without saying a benediction is considered as if he has robbed the Holy One, praised be He! and the Congregation of Israel, for it is said (Pr. 28, 24.) Whoso 
            robbeth his father or his mother and saith it is no transgression, he is the companion of a destroyer. His father, refers to the Holy One, praised be He! as it is said (Deu. 32, 6.) Is He not thy father who hath bought thee; Or his mother,
            refers to nothing else but the Congregation of Israel., as it is said (Pr. 1, 8.) Hear, my son, the instructions of your father and cast not aside the teaching of your mother." What is meant by He is a companion of a destroyer? R. Chanina b. 
            Papa said: "He is a companion of Jeroboam, the son of Nebat, who has corrupted Israel in their relation to their Heavenly Father."</p>
    </midrashim>
    
    


</midrash>
