<midrashim book="BereishitRabbah">
    <source>
        <midtext>Bereishit Rabbah</midtext>
        <midpass>45</midpass>
        <!-- unclear which verse numbers -->
    </source>
    <p>...2. "And <ref character="sarah sarai">Sarai</ref> said to <ref character="abraham"
        >Abram</ref>, <quotation cite="genesis16:2">Look, the Lord has kept me from
            bearing</quotation>
        <paren><ref bibverse="genesis16:2">Gen.16:2</ref></paren> as follows: <quote>Said
            she, I know the source of my affliction: It is not as people say <paren>of a
                barren woman</paren>, <quote>she needs a talisman, she needs a
                    charm</quote>, but Look, the <ref god="Lord">Lord</ref> has kept me from
            bearing.</quote></p>
    <p>" , ...<ref rabbi="Shimon_ben_Yohai">Rabbi Shimon ben Yohai</ref> said <quote
        speaker="Shimon_ben_Yohai"><ref character="hagar">Hagar</ref> was <ref
            character="pharaoh">Pharaoh's</ref> daughter. When he saw the deeds on
        behalf of <ref character="sarah">Sarah</ref> in his house, he took his daughter
        and gave her to him, saying, <speech speaker="pharaoh">better that my daughter
            by a maidservant in this house than a mistress in another house.</speech>
        This is what is written: <quotation cite="genesis16:1">She had an Egyptian
            handmaid whose name was <ref character="hagar"
                >Hagar</ref>.</quotation></quote>
        <paren>In other words:</paren>
        <hebrew>ha agrikh</hebrew>: <quote><translation heb="ha agrikh">This is your
            reward.</translation></quote></p>
    <p>And he went into <ref character="hagar">Hagar</ref> and she conceived <paren><ref
        bibverse="genesis16:4">Gen. 16:4</ref></paren>. <ref rabbi="Levi_bar_Hayta"
            >Rabbi Levi bar Hayta</ref> said: <quote speaker="Levi_bar_Hayta">She became
                pregnant at the first intimacy.</quote> Said <ref rabbi="Eleazar">Rabbi
                    Eleazar</ref>: <quote speaker="Eleazar">A woman never conceives by the first
                        intimacy.</quote> An objection is raised: surely it is written, So both of <ref
                            character="lot">Lot's</ref> daughters got pregnant by their father <paren><ref
                                bibverse="genesis19:36">Gen. 19:36</ref></paren>? Said <ref rabbi="Tanhuma"
                                    >R. Tanhuma</ref>: <quote speaker="Tanhuma">By an effort of will power they
                                        brought forth their virginity, and conceived at the second <quote>act of
                                            intercourse</quote>. The first act is what they did to themselves.</quote>
        Said <ref rabbi="Chanina_ben_Pazi">Rabbi Chanina ben Pazi</ref>: <quote
            speaker="Chanina_ben_Pazi">Thorns are neither weeded nor sown, but they grow and
            spring up on their own. But how much suffering and effort for wheat to grow! Why
            were the matriarchs barren?</quote>
        <ref rabbi="Levi">Rabbi Levi</ref> said in <ref rabbi="Shila">Rabbi Shila’s</ref>
        name and <ref rabbi="Chelbo">Rabbi Chelbo</ref> in <ref rabbi="Yochanan">R.
            Yochanan’s</ref> name: <quote speaker="Levi Chelbo">Because the <ref
                god="Holy_One_of_Blessing">Holy One of Blessing</ref> yearns for their
                prayers and supplications, as it is written <quotation cite="SongOfSongs2:14">O
                    my dove, you on the clefts of the rock let Me see your face, let Me hear
                    your voice</quotation></quote>
        <ref bibverse="SongOfSongs2:14">Song of Songs 2:14</ref>: Why did I make you barren?
        In order to <quotation cite="SongOfSongs2:14">see your face... hear your
            voice</quotation>. <ref rabbi="Azariah">Rabbi Azariah</ref> said in the name of
        <ref rabbi="Yochanan_bar_Papa">Rabbi Yochanan bar Papa</ref>: <quote
            speaker="Azariah">So that their husbands might cling to them in their
            beauty.</quote>
        <ref rabbi="Huna">Rabbi Huna</ref> in the name of <ref rabbi="Hiya bar Abba">Rabbi
            Hiya bar Abba</ref> said: <quote speaker="Huna">So that they might pass the
                greater part of their life without hard work.</quote>
        <ref rabbi="Huna">Rabbi Huna</ref> and <ref rabbi="Avun">R. Avun</ref> in the name
        of <ref rabbi="Meir">Rabbi Meir</ref>: <quote speaker="Huna Avun">So that their
            husbands might derive pleasure from them, for when a woman is with child she is
            disfigured and does not care for her appearance.</quote> The ninety years that
        <ref character="sarah">Sarah</ref> did not bear she was like a bride in her
        canopy. Ladies would come to ask how she was, and she would say to them, <speech
            speaker="sarah">Go and ask about the welfare of this wretched woman
            <paren>Hagar</paren><!-- elected not to consider this a character reference b/c Hagar is alluded to and only named in the translation -->!</speech>
        <ref character="hagar">Hagar</ref> would tell them: <speech speaker="hagar">My
            mistress <ref character="sarah sarai">Sarai</ref> is not inside what she is
            outside: she appears to be righteous but she is not righteous, had she been a
            righteous woman, see how many years have passed without her conceiving, whereas
            I conceived in one night!</speech> Said <ref character="sarah">Sarah</ref>:
        <speech speaker="sarah">Am I going to argue with this woman?! I should argue
            with her master!...</speech></p>
    <p>'And <ref character="abraham">Avram</ref> said to <ref character="sarah sarai"
        >Sarai</ref>: <speech speaker="abraham">do it her what is good in your
            eyes!</speech>
        <paren><ref bibverse="genesis19:6">Gen. 19:6</ref></paren> He said to her: <speech
            speaker="abraham">what do I care about her well being or her harm?
            <paren>But</paren> It is written: <quotation cite="deuteronomy21:14">You
                will not deal with her as a slave since you humbled her</quotation>
            <paren><ref bibverse="deuteronomy21:14">Deuteronomy 21:14</ref></paren>, and
            this one, after we made her suffer, we will enslave her? I don't care about her
            well being or her harm. <paren>But</paren> It is written <quotation
                cite="exodus21:8">he shall not have the right to sell her to foreigners,
                since he broke faith with her</quotation>
            <paren><ref bibverse="exodus21:8">Exodus 21:8</ref></paren> and this one, after
            we made her a master we will make her a slave? I don't care about her well being
            or her harm.</speech>
        <ref bibverse="genesis16:6">Then <ref character="sarah sarai">Sarai</ref> treated
            her harshly, and she ran away from her.</ref>
        <ref rabbi="Aba_bar_Kahana">Rabbi Aba bar Kahana</ref> said: <quote
            speaker="Aba_bar_Kahana">she forbade her from having sexual relations.</quote>
        <ref rabbi="Berachia">Rabbi Berachia</ref> said: <quote speaker="Berachia">she
            slapped her face with a slipper.</quote>
        <ref rabbi="Berachia">Rabbi Berachia</ref> in the name of <ref
            rabbi="Aba_Bar_Kahana">Rabbi Aba Bar Kahana</ref> said: <quote
                speaker="Berachia">She made her carry water buckets and bath towels to the
                baths.</quote> And she called the name of <ref god="Ad-nai">Ad-nai</ref> who
        talked to her <quotation cite="genesis16:13">You are <ref god="El-Roi"
            >El-Roi</ref></quotation>
        <paren><ref bibverse="genesis16:13">Gen. 16:13</ref></paren>
        <ref rabbi="Yehuda_bar_Simon">Rabbi Yehuda bar Simon</ref> and <ref rabbi="Yochanan"
            >Rabbi Yochanan</ref> said, in the name of <ref rabbi="Eleazar_Bar Shimeon"
                >Rabbi Eleazar Bar Shimeon</ref>: <quote speaker="Yochanan Yochanan">The <ref
                    god="Holy_One_of_Blessing">Holy One of Blessing</ref> did not grant speaking
                    with women, with the exception of that righteous one <paren>Sarah</paren>, and
                    even that had a particular reason.</quote>
        <ref rabbi="Aba">Rabbi Aba</ref> said, in the name of <ref rabbi="Beiri">Rabbi
            Beiri</ref>: <quote speaker="Aba">How many roundabouts He did in order to talk
                to her!</quote>
        <ref bibverse="genesis18:15">He said: 'no, you did laugh!'</ref>
        <paren><ref bibverse="genesis18:16">Gen. 18:16</ref></paren> But it is written:
        <quotation cite="genesis16:13">and she called the name of <ref god="Ad-nai"
            >Ad-nai</ref></quotation> who talked to her '<quotation cite="genesis16:13"
                >You are El-Roi</quotation>''! <ref rabbi="Yehoshua_Bar_Nechemiah">Rabbi
                    Yehoshua Bar Nechemiah</ref> said: <quote speaker="Yehoshua_Bar_Nechemiah">it
                        was through an angel.</quote> But it is written: <quotation cite="genesis25:23"
                            >And God said to her</quotation><paren><ref bibverse="genesis25:23">Gen.
                                25:23</ref></paren>! Said <ref rabbi="Levi">Rabbi Levi</ref>, in the name of
        <ref rabbi="Eleazar">Rabbi Eleazar</ref>, in the name of <ref
            rabbi="Yosi_ben_Zimra">Rabbi Yosi ben Zimra</ref>: <quote speaker="Levi">it was
                through a name.</quote> '<quotation cite="genesis16:13">You are El
                    Roi</quotation>' - said <ref rabbi="Aivu">Rabbi Aivu</ref>: <quote
                        speaker="Aivu">You are the one who sees the sufferings of the
                        persecuted.</quote> 'Since she said: also, here
        <paren><hebrew>halom</hebrew></paren>], <quotation cite="genesis16:13">I have
            seen after the One Who sees me.</quotation> She said: Not only I was granted a
        talk, but even royalty, as it is written: <quotation cite="IISamuel7:18">You that
            brought me this far</quotation>
        <paren><hebrew>halom</hebrew></paren>
        <paren><ref bibverse="IISamuel7:18">II Sam. 7:18</ref></paren>. <speech
            speaker="hagar">Not only I was granted to see with my mistress, but even if my
            mistress were with me right now she would not have seen.</speech> Another
        interpretation: <speech speaker="hagar">Not only I was granted to see with my
            mistress, but now even when I am alone!</speech>
        <ref rabbi="Shmuel_Bar_Nachman">Rabbi Shmuel Bar Nachman</ref> said: <quote
            speaker="Shmuel_Bar_Nachman">this is similar to a lady to whom the king said
            <quotation cite="genesis32:17">pass before me</quotation>.</quote> She
        passed before him but was relying on her slave, and hiding her face, and she did not
        see the king - but the slave did. </p>
</midrashim>