<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<?xml-model href="midrashim_schema.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<midrash>
    <verse>The stranger who resides with you shall be to you as one of your citizens; you shall love
        him as yourself, for you were strangers in the land of Egypt: I the LORD am your
        God.</verse>
    <midrashim>
        <source>
            <midtext>Midrash Tanchuma</midtext>
            <edition>Buber</edition>
            <midpass>Yitro 11:1</midpass>
        </source>
        <p><ref>Exod. 19:1</ref>: <quote>ON THE THIRD NEW MOON</quote>. What is written above on the matter? The parashah
            about Jethro, in which he taught Moses (in <ref>Exod. 18:21</ref>): <quote>YOU SHALL ALSO SEEK OUT [ABLE
            MEN] FROM AMONG ALL THE PEOPLE.</quote>32 And after that (in <ref>vs. 27</ref>): THEN MOSES SENT HIS
            (FATHER-IN-LAW ) AWAY. And after that (in Exod. 19:1): ON THE THIRD NEW MOON. Solomon
            said (in Prov. 14:10): THE HEART KNOWS ITS OWN BITTERNESS…, and therefore (according to
            the rest of the verse) NO OUTSIDER SHALL INTERVENE IN ITS JOY. The Holy One said: My
            children were enslaved with clay and bricks while Jethro was dwelling quietly within his
            house. So shall he come to behold the joy of the Torah along with my children? Then
            after that (in Exod. 19:1): ON THE THIRD NEW MOON. Why so? Moses interpreted (the matter
            on the principle of ) qal wahomer (i.e., a fortiori): If in the case of a single
            precept, when the Holy One was going to give the precept on Passover, Torah said (in
            Exod. 12:43): NO FOREIGNER SHALL EAT OF IT; in the case of six hundred and thirteen
            commandments which he wanted to give to Israel, should Jethro be there to behold them?
            Therefore (in Exod. 18:27): MOSES SENT HIS (FATHER-IN-LAW) AWAY; and after that (in
            Exod. 19:1): ON THE THIRD NEW MOON. Why ON THE THIRD NEW MOON, and not on the second new
            moon, or the seventh new moon, or on another new moon?33 Our masters have said: R.
            Osha'ya said: R. Hiyya the elder taught me: A female proselyte, a female captive, or an
            emancipated female slave may neither marry nor be betrothed for three new moons.34 So
            (it was with) Israel. They were called proselytes (gerim), as stated (in Lev. 19:34):
            FOR YOU WERE STRANGERS (gerim) IN THE LAND OF EGYPT. (They were called) captives, as
            stated (in Is. 14:2): THEY SHALL TAKE THEIR CAPTORS CAPTIVE. (They were called)
            emancipated slaves, as stated (in Lev. 26:13): I AM THE LORD YOUR GOD WHO BROUGHT YOU
            OUT OF THE LAND OF EGYPT TO BE THEIR SLAVES NO MORE…. The Holy One said: I will wait
            three new moons for them and after that I will give them the Torah.</p>
    </midrashim>
    <midrashim>
        <source>
            <midtext>Vayikra Rabbah</midtext>
            <midpass>35:3</midpass>
        </source>
        <p>Rabbi Elazar said: In the way the world functions, a king of flesh and blood decrees a
            decree; if he wants to fulfill it, then he fulfills it, if he doesn’t [want to],
            ultimately it will be fulfilled by others. But the Blessed One is not like this, rather,
            if God decrees a decree, God will fulfill it first, as it says in the verse: (Leviticus
            19:32) “You shall rise up before the hoary (greyish white) head, and honor the face of
            the old, and you shall fear your God: I am the LORD.” I fulfilled the commandment of
            standing up for the old first, “If you will walk in My statutes.”</p>
    </midrashim>
</midrash>
