<?xml-model href="midrashim_schema.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<midrash>
    <midrashim>
        <!-- This perhaps won't be a super viable one -->
        <source><midtext>Ein Yaakov</midtext> (<edition>Glick Edition</edition>), <midpass>Sanhedrin
                3:11</midpass>)</source>
        <p>(Fol. 31) Our Rabbis were taught: <quote>Whence do we know that one of the judges, when
                leaving court, must not say : 'I was in favor of the defendant, but my colleagues
                were against me, and I could not help it, for they were in the majority ?' The
                passage, therefore reads <ref>Lev. 19, 16</ref> Thou shalt not go up and down as a
                tale-bearer among thy people. And another passage says <ref>Prov. 11, 13</ref> He
                that walketh about as a tale-bearer revealeth secrets.</quote> There was a disciple
            concerning whom there was a rumor that after twenty-two years he disclosed a secret
            thing which was taught in the college. R. Ami drove him out of the college, and
            announced: <quote>This man is a revealer of secrets.</quote></p>
    </midrashim>

    <midrashim>
        <source>
            <midtext>Sifrei Devarim</midtext>
            <midpass>89:3</midpass>
        </source>
        <p>Because it is written <ref>Vayikra 19:16</ref>
            <quote>And you shall not abide the (spilling of the) blood of your neighbor,</quote> I
            might think that the same applied to this one, too; it is, therefore, written <quote>and
                your eye should not look mercifully upon him.</quote>
        </p>
    </midrashim>

    <midrashim>
        <source>
            <midtext>Midrash Tanchuma</midtext>
            <midpass>Kedoshim 3:1</midpass>
        </source>
        <p><ref>Lev. 19:2:</ref>
            <quote>Speak unto the whole congregation of the Children of Israel, and say unto them,
                ‘You shall be holy.’</quote> What reason did He have to speak this parashah in an
            assembly?5 Why did He not say, <quote>Speak unto the Children of Israel,</quote> as in
            the rest of the parashiot,6 rather than <quote>[Speak] unto the whole congregation of
                the Children of Israel?</quote> Because all of the [ten] commandments are included
            within it. How? In the commandments it is written (in <ref>Exod. 20:2</ref> = <ref>Deut.
                5:6</ref>), <quote>I [am] the Lord your God</quote>; and here (in <ref>Lev.
                19:2</ref>), <quote>I [am] the Lord your God.</quote> In the commandments it is
            written (in <ref>Exod. 20:3</ref> = <ref>Deut. 5:7</ref>), <quote>You shall have no
                [other gods beside Me]</quote>; and here (in <ref>Lev. 19:4</ref>), <quote>Do not
                turn unto idols.</quote> In the commandments it is written (in <ref>Exod. 20:7</ref>
            = <ref>Deut. 5:11</ref>), <quote>You shall not take [the name of the Lord your God in
                vain]</quote>; and here (in <ref>Lev. 19:12</ref>), <quote>You shall not swear
                falsely by My name.</quote> In the commandments it is written (<ref>Deut.
            5:12</ref>), <quote>Guard the Sabbath day</quote>; and here it is written (in <ref>Lev.
                19:3</ref>), <quote>You shall keep My Sabbaths.</quote> In the commandments it is
            written (in <ref>Exod. 20:12</ref> = <ref>Deut. 5:16</ref>), <quote>Honor your father
                and your mother</quote>; and here it is written (in <ref>Lev. 19:3</ref>, cont.),
                <quote>you each shall fear his mother and his father.</quote> In the commandments it
            is written (in <ref>Exod. 20:13</ref> = <ref>Deut. 5:17</ref>), <quote>You shall not
                murder</quote>; and here it is written (in <ref>Lev. 19:16</ref>), <quote>you shall
                not stand over the blood of your neighbor.</quote> in the commandments it is written
            (in <ref>Exod. 20:13</ref> = <ref>Deut. 5:17</ref>), <quote>you shall not commit
                adultery</quote>; and here it is written (in <ref>Lev. 19:2</ref>), <quote>You shall
                be holy.</quote> In the commandments it is written (in <ref>Exod. 20:13</ref> =
                <ref>Deut. 5:17</ref>), <quote>you shall not steal</quote>; and here it is written
            (in <ref>Lev. 19:11</ref>), <quote>You shall not steal.</quote> In the commandments it
            is written (in <ref>Exod. 20:13</ref> = <ref>Deut. 5:17</ref>), <quote>you shall not
                bear [false witness against your neighbor]</quote>; and here it is written (in
                <ref>Lev. 19:16</ref>), <quote>You shall not go around as a slanderer among your
                people.</quote> In the commandments it is written (in <ref>Exod. 20:14</ref> =
                <ref>Deut. 5:18</ref>), <quote>You shall not covet</quote>; and here it is written
            (in <ref>Lev. 19:13</ref>), <quote>You shall not oppress your neighbor, and you shall
                not rob him.</quote> Here all of the [ten] commandments are included within [it]. It
            is therefore stated (in <ref>Lev. 19:2</ref>), <quote>Speak unto the whole congregation
                [of the Children of Israel]</quote></p>
    </midrashim>

    <midrashim>
        <source>
            <midtext>Midrash Tanchuma</midtext>
            <midpass>Chukat 4:1</midpass>
        </source>
        <p>(Numb. 19:2:) “This is the statute of the Torah.” R. Tanhum bar Hanila'i opened [his
            discourse] (with Ps. 12:7), “The sayings of the Lord are pure sayings.”36 Are the
            sayings of the Lord [true] sayings, but the sayings of flesh and blood not [true]
            sayings? Now by universal custom, when a king of flesh and blood enters a province, the
            inhabitants of the province praise37 him; and their praise is pleasing to him. He says
            to them, “Tomorrow I am building bath houses38 for you, and I am building baths for you
            and I am bringing in a water carrier for you.” [Then] he goes to sleep and never gets
            up. Where is he [now], and where are his promises (literally, statements)? The Holy One,
            blessed be He, however, is not like this. Rather the statement of God is true, as (in
            Jer. 10:10), “He is a living God and an everlasting King.” R. Joshua ben Levi said, “We
            find that the Torah has twisted two or three words in the Torah, so as not to bring
            forth something unclean from His (i.e., the Holy One, blessed be He's) mouth.39 Thus it
            is stated (in Gen. 7:2), ‘From the clean beast and from the beast which is not clean.’
            So it is not written, ‘of the unclean beast.’" R. Judan said, “When He came to introduce
            the signs of an unclean beast, He only began with the signs of purity. It is not written
            here (in Lev. 11:4), ‘the camel, because it does not have a cloven hoof,’ but “[the
            camel] because it chews its cud [but does not have a cloven hoof].’ It is not written
            here (in Lev. 11:6), ‘The hare, because it does not have a hoof,’ but ‘[The hare],
            because it chews its cud [but does not have a cloven hoof].’ It is not written (in Lev.
            11:7), ‘The pig, because it does not chew its cud,’ but ‘[the pig], because it has a
            cloven hoof [and is cleft footed, but does not chew its cud].’” R. Joshua of Sikhnin
            said in the name of R. Levi, “The infants who lived in the days of David, [even] before
            they had a gotten a taste of sin, knew how to interpret the Torah with forty-nine
            reasons for declaring an object unclean and forty-nine reasons for declaring an object
            clean.40 So David prayed for them and said (in Ps. 12:8), ‘You, O Lord, will keep them;
            You will guard each [of them] from this generation unto eternity.’ (ibid.:) ‘You, O
            Lord, will keep them,’ [i.e.,] watch over their instruction in their hearts; (ibid.,
            cont.) ‘You will guard each [of them from this generation unto eternity],’ from the
            generation which is worthy of destruction. But after all this praise, they went out to
            war and fell, because there were slanderers41 among them. This is what David says (in
            Ps. 57:5), ‘My soul is in the midst of lions, I lie down among those who are aflame, men
            whose teeth are spears and darts, and whose tongues are a sharp sword.’ (ibid.:) ‘My
            soul is in the midst of lions,’ these are Abner and Amasa, who were lions with the
            Torah42; (ibid., cont.) ‘I lie down among those who are aflame,’ these are Doeg and
            Ahithophel, who were aflame to slander [David]43; (ibid., cont.) ‘men whose teeth are
            spears and darts,’ these are the people of Keilah, of whom it is stated (in I Sam.
            23:12), ‘Will the people of Keilah surrender me?’ (Ps. 57:5, cont.:) ‘And whose tongue
            is a sharp sword,’ these are the Ziphites, of whom it is stated (in Ps. 54:2), ‘When the
            Ziphites came and said to Saul, “Is not David hiding among us […]?”’ At that time David
            said (in Ps. 57:6), ‘”Be exalted, O God, above the heavens,” remove your Divine Presence
            from among them.’ The generation of Ahab, however, were all worshipers of idols; yet
            because there were no slanderers among them, they went out to war and won.44 That
            [freedom from informers] is what [enabled] Obadiah to say to Elijah (in I Kings 18:13),
            ‘Has it not been told to my lord what I did [when Jezebel slew the prophets, how I hid a
            hundred prophets of the Lord …, and provided them with bread and water?’ If bread [is
            mentioned], why [mention] water? Simply because it was more difficult to bring them the
            water than the bread.45 And yet Elijah made his proclamation46 on Mount Carmel and said
            (in vs. 22), ‘I am the only prophet of the Lord left,’ and [even though] all the people
            knew [about Obadiah’s prophets], they did not expose it to the king.” R. Samuel b. R.
            Nahman said, “They said to the serpent, ‘Why is it that you are found among the fences?’
            It said to them, ‘I made a breach in the fence of the world.’47 They said to it, ‘Why is
            it that you move along with your tongue slavering?’48 It said to them, ‘That [tongue]
            caused me [to make the breach].’ They said to it, ‘Why is it that, when all the [other]
            animals bite, they do not kill; but when you bite, you do kill?’ It said to them (in
            Eccl. 10:11), ‘”If a snake bites without being under a spell, the owner of the tongue
            (i.e., one able to charm the snake) has no advantage.” Is it possible for me to do
            anything without me being told from on High?’ ‘Then why is it that, when you bite one
            limb, all the limbs feel [the pain]?’ It said to them, ‘Are you asking me? Ask a
            slandering informer,49 the one who [remains] here and [yet] slays in Rome.’” Why is the
            slandering informer named a "third?”50 Because [such a slanderer] kills three people:
            the one who speaks it, the one who accepts it, and the one about whom it is spoken.51 In
            the days of Saul it killed four: Doeg, who spoke it52; Saul, who received it53;
            Ahimelech, about whom it was spoken54; and Abner ben Ner. Now why was Abner ben Ner
            slain? Joshua ben Levi said, “[He was slain] because he had his [own] name the name of
            David. This is what is written (in II Sam. 3:12), ‘Then Abner sent messengers unto David
            where he was, saying, “To whom does the land belong?”’ [In the message] he wrote, ‘From
            Abner to David.’”55 R. Simeon ben Laqish said, “[He was slain] because he made the blood
            of young men [a matter of] amusement (rt.: shq), as stated (in II Sam. 2:14), ‘Please
            let the young men arise and play (rt.: shq) before us.’” Our masters have said, “[He was
            slain] because he did [not] wait for Saul to be reconciled56 with David, where it is
            stated (in I Sam. 24:12, with David addressing Saul), ‘See, my father, see the corner of
            your cloak in my hand; for when I cut off the corner of your cloak, I did not kill
            you].’ [Saul] said to him, ‘Abner, what do you want [to understand] from the cloak? You
            said, “It was caught on a thorn.”’ When [David] came toward wagons around the camp, he
            said to him (in I Sam. 26:14), ‘“Abner, will you not answer?’ As for the corner of the
            cloak, you said was caught on a thorn. Were [the] spear and [the] water jar (of I Sam.
            26:11) caught on a thorn?’” There are also some who say, “[Abner was slain] because he
            had the power to protest about Nob, the city of priests, but did not protest."</p>
    </midrashim>
</midrash>
