<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="midrashim_schema.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<midrash>
    <verse>
        <versenum>Genesis 17:15</versenum>
        <versetext> And Elohim said to Avraham [As for] Sarai your wife, do not call her by the name
            Sarai, for Sarah is her name.</versetext>
        <versenum>Genesis 17:16</versenum>
        <versetext>I will bless her, and I will also give you a son through her. I will bless her,
            and she will be [a mother] of nations [assemblies], kings of peoples [who rule over
            nations] will descend from her.</versetext>
        <versenum>Genesis 17:17</versenum>
        <versetext>Avraham fell on his face and laughed [rejoiced]. He said in his heart: Can a
            hundred year old man have children? Shall Sarah, who is ninety years old give
            birth?</versetext>
        <versenum>Genesis 17:18</versenum>
        <versetext>And Avraham said to [before] Elohim: May it be granted that Yishmael live before
            You.</versetext>
        <versenum>Genesis 17:19</versenum>
        <versetext> Elohim said: Indeed, your wife Sarah will bear you a son, and you will name him
            Yitzchok. I will establish My covenant with him as an eternal covenant to his
            descendants after him.</versetext>
    </verse>
    <midrashim>
        <source>
            <midtext>Bereishit Rabbah</midtext>
            <midpass>39</midpass>
        </source>
        <p>“And the souls that they had made in Haran.” Said <ref rabbi="Elazar ben Zimra">Rabbi
                Elazar ben Zimra</ref>: <function definition="create">Even if every creature on
                earth conspired to create <paren>out of nothing</paren> even one mosquito, they
                could not give it a <ref item="soul">soul</ref>--and you say <quote>the souls that
                    they had made.</quote></function> Therefore <paren>they must be</paren> they
            must be those who lived with them and converted. And it it meant
                <quote>converted</quote> why did it say <quote>made?</quote>
            <function definition="create">In order to teach you that each one who brings an idol
                worshipper and converts him, it is as though he created him.</function> And
                <function definition="he they">why did it say that <quote>they made</quote> rather
                than <quote>that he made?</quote></function> Said <ref rabbi="Rav Hunna">Rav
                Huna</ref>: <ref character="abraham">Abraham</ref> would convert the men, and <ref
                character="sarah">Sarah</ref> would convert the women. </p>
        <!-- Rav Huna was a talmudist, not a rabbi; important distinction? -->
    </midrashim>
    <midrashim>
        <source>
            <midtext>Bereishit Rabbah</midtext>
            <midpass>45</midpass>
            <!-- unclear which verse numbers -->
        </source>
        <p>...2. "And <ref character="sarah sarai">Sarai</ref> said to <ref character="abraham"
                >Abram</ref>, <quotation>Look, the Lord has kept me from bearing</quotation>
            (Gen.16:2) as follows: <quote>Said she, I know the source of my affliction: It is not as
                people say [of a barren woman], 'she needs a talisman, she needs a charm', but Look,
                the Lord has kept me from bearing.</quote></p>
        <p>" , ...<ref rabbi="Shimon ben Yohai">Rabbi Shimon ben Yohai</ref> said <ref
                character="hagar">Hagar</ref> was <ref character="pharaoh">Pharaoh's</ref> daughter.
            When he saw the deeds on behalf of <ref character="sarah">Sarah</ref> in his house, he
            took his daughter and gave her to him, saying, 'better that my daughter by a maidservant
            in this house than a mistress in another house.' This is what is written: <quotation>She
                had an Egyptian handmaid whose name was Hagar.</quotation> [In other words:]
                <hebrew>ha agrikh</hebrew>: <quote><translation heb="ha agrikh">This is your
                    reward.</translation></quote></p>
        <p>And he went into <ref character="hagar">Hagar</ref> and she conceived <paren><ref
                    bibverse="genesis16:4">Gen. 16:4</ref></paren>. <ref rabbi="Levi bar Hayta"
                >Rabbi Levi bar Hayta</ref> said: She became pregnant at the first intimacy. Said
            Rabbi Eleazar: A woman never conceives by the first intimacy. An objection is raised:
            surely it is written, So both of Lot's daughters got pregnant by their father (Gen.
            19:36)? Said R. Tanhuma: By an effort of will power they brought forth their virginity,
            and conceived at the second “act of intercourse”. [The first act is what they did to
            themselves. Said Rabbi Chanina ben Pazi: Thorns are neither weeded nor sown, but they
            grow and spring up on their own. But how much suffering and effort for wheat to grow!
            Why were the matriarchs barren? Rabbi Levi said in Rabbi Shila’s name and Rabbi Chelbo
            in R. Yochanan’s name: Because the Holy One of Blessing yearns for their prayers and
            supplications, as it is written 'O my dove, you on the clefts of the rock let Me see
            your face, let Me hear your voice' (Song of Songs 2:14): Why did I make you barren? In
            order to 'see your face... hear your voice'. Rabbi Azariah said in the name of Rabbi
            Yochanan bar Papa: So that their husbands might cling to them in their beauty. Rabbi
            Huna in the name of Rabbi Hiya bar Abba said: So that they might pass the greater part
            of their life without hard work. Rabbi Huna and R. Avun in the name of Rabbi Meir: So
            that their husbands might derive pleasure from them, for when a woman is with child she
            is disfigured and does not care for her appearance. The ninety years that Sarah did not
            bear she was like a bride in her canopy. Ladies would come to ask how she was, and she
            would say to them, 'Go and ask about the welfare of this wretched woman [Hagar]!' Hagar
            would tell them: 'My mistress Sarai is not inside what she is outside: she appears to be
            righteous but she is not righteous, had she been a righteous woman, see how many years
            have passed without her conceiving, whereas I conceived in one night!' Said Sarah: 'Am I
            going to argue with this woman?! I should argue with her master!...</p>
        <p> 'And Avram said to Sarai: do it her what is good in your eyes!' (Gen. 19:6) He said to
            her: "what do I care about her well being or her harm? [But] It is written: 'You will
            not deal with her as a slave since you humbled her' (Deuteronomy 21:14), and this one,
            after we made her suffer, we will enslave her? I don't care about her well being or her
            harm. [But] It is written 'he shall not have the right to sell her to foreigners, since
            he broke faith with her' (Exodus 21:8) and this one, after we made her a master we will
            make her a slave? I don't care about her well being or her harm." 'Then Sarai treated
            her harshly, and she ran away from her.' Rabbi Aba bar Kahana said: she forbade her from
            having sexual relations. Rabbi Berachia said: she slapped her face with a slipper. Rabbi
            Berachia in the name of Rabbi Aba Bar Kahana said: She made her carry water buckets and
            bath towels to the baths. And she called the name of Ad-nai who talked to her 'You are
            El-Roi' (Gen. 16:13) Rabbi Yehuda bar Simon and Rabbi Yochanan said, in the name of
            Rabbi Eleazar Bar Shimeon: The Holy One of Blessing did not grant speaking with women,
            with the exception of that righteous one [Sarah], and even that had a particular reason.
            Rabbi Aba said, in the name of Rabbi Beiri: How many roundabouts He did in order to talk
            to her! 'He said: 'no, you did laugh!'' (Gen. 18:16) But it is written: 'and she called
            the name of Ad-nai who talked to her 'You are El-Roi''! Rabbi Yehoshua Bar Nechemiah
            said: it was through an angel. But it is written: 'And God said to her'(Gen. 25:23)!
            Said Rabbi Levi, in the name of Rabbi Eleazar, in the name of Rabbi Yosi ben Zimra: it
            was through a name. 'You are El Roi' - said Rabbi Aivu: You are the one who sees the
            sufferings of the persecuted. 'Since she said: also, here [halom], I have seen after the
            One Who sees me.' She said: Not only I was granted a talk, but even royalty, as it is
            written: 'You that brought me this far [halom] (II Sam. 7:18). Not only I was granted to
            see with my mistress, but even if my mistress were with me right now she would not have
            seen. Another interpretation: Not only I was granted to see with my mistress, but now
            even when I am alone! Rabbi Shmuel Bar Nachman said: this is similar to a lady to whom
            the king said 'pass before me'. She passed before him but was relying on her slave, and
            hiding her face, and she did not see the king - but the slave did. </p>
    </midrashim>
    <midrashim>
        <source>
            <!-- associated with gen 17:15 -->
            <midtext>Bereishit Rabbah</midtext>
            <midpass>47:1</midpass>
        </source>
        <p>"God said..., 'Sarai your wife...'" In Proverbs (12:4), it is written, "A woman of valor
            is a crown to her husband." Rabbi Aha said, "Her husband was crowned through her, but
            she was not crowned through her husband." Our rabbis taught that she ruled over her
            husband. In all places, the man gives orders, but here (Genesis 21:12), "In all that
            Sarah orders you, listen to her voice." Said Rabbi Yehoshua Ben Korcha: 'The Yud that
            the Holy One of Blessing took from Sarai was given half to Sarah, and half to Avraham.
            Said Rabbi Shime'on Bar Yochai: The Yud that the Holy One of Blessing took from Sarai
            flew and posted itself in front of the Throne of the Holy One, and said: 'Master of the
            Universe! Because I am the smallest letter You took me out of the name of Sarai the
            Righteous!! The Holy One said: In the past you were in the name of a woman, and in the
            end of the name! Now I will put you in the name of a man, and on the beginning of the
            name, as it is written 'And Moshe called Hosea Bin Nun Yehoshua' (Numbers 13:16). Said
            Rabbi Mana: Sarai was just [a princess] for herself, now she will be a princess for all
            the world.</p>
    </midrashim>
    <midrashim>
        <source>
            <midtext>Bereishit Rabbah</midtext>
            <midpass>53</midpass>
        </source>
        <p>AND SARAH SAID: GOD HAS MADE JOY FOR ME; EVERY ONE THAT HEARS WILL REJOICE WITH ME (Gen.
            21:6). R. Berekiah, R. Judah b. R. Simon, and R. Hanan in the name of R. Samuel b. R.
            Isaac said: If Reuben has cause to rejoice, what does it matter to Simeon? Similarly, if
            Sarah was remembered, what did it matter to others? But when the matriarch Sarah was
            remembered [gave birth], many other barren women were remembered with her; many deaf
            gained their hearing; many blind had their eyes opened, many insane became sane. For
            ‘making’ [HAS MADE] is mentioned here, and also elsewhere, viz. And he made a release to
            the provinces (Est. II, 18). As the making mentioned there means that a gift was granted
            to the world,l so the making mentioned here means that a gift was granted to the world.
            R. Levi said: She increased the light of the luminaries: ‘making’ is mentioned here,
            viz. GOD HAS MADE FOR ME, while elsewhere it says, And God made the two lights (Gen. I,
            16).</p>
        <p>AND SARAH SAW THE SON OF HAGAR THE EGYPTIAN etc - Rabbi Shimeon bar Yohai said: Rabbi
            Akiva used to interpret this to his [Ishmael’s] shame, Rabbi Akiba lectured: AND SARAH
            SAW [THE SON OF HAGAR THE EGYPTIAN, WHOM SHE HAD BORNE TO AVRAHAM, MAKING SPORT.] Now
            'making sport' refers to nothing else but sexual immorality, as in the verse, "The
            Hebrew servant, whom you have brought to us, came in to make sport of me. (Gen. 39:17).
            This teaches that Sarah saw Ishmael ravish maidens, seduced married women and dishonored
            them. R. Ishmael taught: This term 'making sport' refers to idolatry, as in the verse,
            "And the people sat to eat and drink and got up to make sport' (Exodus 32:6). This
            teaches that Sarah saw Ishmael build altars, catch locusts, and sacrifice them. R.
            Eleazar said: The term 'making sport' refers to bloodshed, as in the verse, "Let the
            young men, please, arise and make sport before us" (II Sam. 2:14) Rabbi Azariah said in
            Rabbi Levi’s name: Ishmael said to Isaac: 'Let us go and see our pieces in the field'
            and he would pick up the bow and shoot arrows, aiming in Itzchak's direction, while
            pretending to be playing (making sport), as it is written: "as a madman who casts
            fire-brands, arrows, and death; so is the man that deceives his neighbor, and said: 'I
            am just joking (making sport)'. And I [Rabbi Shimon bar Yochai] say that this is to be
            interpreted to the praise [of Ishmael]. This expression of making sport is only used as
            'inheritance'. In the moment that Itzchak our father was born all were happy. Ishmael
            said to them: are you dumb? I am the first-born, I am going to receive double portion
            [of the inheritance], that from the answer of Sarah our mother to Avraham 'because the
            son of this maidservant will not inherit with my son, with Itzchak' you learn that he
            would not inherit 'with my son' - even if he wasn't Itzchak - and 'with Itzchak' - even
            if he wasn't my son. All the more so [this is true] 'with my son, with Itzchak'.</p>
    </midrashim>
    <midrashim>
        <source>
            <midtext>Bereishit Rabbah</midtext>
            <midpass>58</midpass>
        </source>
        <p>..."The sun rises and goes down" (Ecclesiastics 1:5). Rabbi Aba bar Kahana said: Don't we
            know that the sun rises and goes down? Rather (this is what it means): When the Holy One
            of Blessing causes the sun of a righteous person to set, he causes the sun of his fellow
            to shine forth. The day that Rabbi Akiba died, our rabbi (Judah the Prince) was born and
            it was written about him "The sun rises and the sun goes down." On the day that our
            rabbi died Rabbi Ada Bar Ahava was born and it was written about him "The sun rises and
            the sun goes down." On the day that Rabbi Ada Bar Ahava died, Rabbi Avin was born and it
            was written about him "The sun rises and the sun goes down." On the day that Rabbi Avin
            died, his son Rabbi Avin was born. The day that Rabbi Avin died, Aba Hoshaya from Traya
            was born. The day that Aba Hoshaya died Rabbi Hoshaya was born and it was written about
            him "The sun rises and the sun goes down." Before the sun of Moses set the sun of Joshua
            shone forth as it is written, "God said to Moses, take Joshua Son of Nun" (Numbers
            27:18). Before the sun of Joshua set the sun of Itaniel son of Kenaz shone forth as it
            is said, "Itaniel son of Kenaz took it" (Judges 1:13). Before the sun of Eli the priest
            set, the sun of Samuel shone forth, "the lamp of God had not yet gone out and Samuel lay
            on the sanctuary of God" (1 Sam 3:3). Rabbi Yochanan said, "like a perfect calf." Before
            the God causes the sun of Sarah to set, he causes the sun of Rebecca to shine forth. For
            first it says "Behold Malkah also bore children" (Gen 22:20) and after "and the life
            Sarah was one hundred years..."</p>
        <p>Rabbi Akiva was once sitting and lecturing, and the community [his students] was falling
            asleep. To arouse them, he said: How could Esther rule over one hundred and twenty seven
            provinces? It should be that Esther, a descendant of Sarah who lived to one hundred and
            twenty seven, to rule over one hundred and twenty seven provinces.</p>
        <p>And Avraham came to eulogize Sarah-From where did he come? Rabbi levi said: He came to
            Sarah from the burial of Terach. Rabbi Yossi said to him: And did not the burial of
            Terach precede the burial of Sarah by two years?! Rather, from where did he come? From
            Mount Moriah.</p>
    </midrashim>

    <midrashim>
        <source>
            <midtext>Bereishit Rabbah</midtext>
            <midpass>60</midpass>
        </source>
        <p>"And Isaac brought her into the tent of Sarah, his mother-" All the days that Sarah was
            alive, a cloud was connected (lit. tied) to the entrance of her tent. When she died, the
            cloud stopped [resting at her tent.] And when Rebecca came, the cloud returned. All the
            days that Sarah was alive, the doors were open wide. When she died, the wideness
            stopped. And when Rebecca came, the wideness returned. And all the days that Sarah was
            alive, there was a blessing in her dough, and when Sarah died, that blessing ended. When
            Rebecca came, [the blessing] returned. All the days that Sarah was alive, there was a
            candle that would burn from Sabbath Eve to [the next] Sabbath Eve, and when she died,
            the candle stopped [burning for so long]. And when Rebecca came, [the week-long flame of
            the candle] returned. And as soon as [Isaac] saw her, that she did the deeds of his
            mother, separating her challah in purity and separating her dough in purity, he brought
            her into the tent. Rabbi Yudan said, "The Torah teaches you, that if a man has grown-up
            sons, he should marry them off first and then he should marry. Who do you learn [this
            teaching] from? From Abraham: first, "And Isaac brought her into the tent of Sarah his
            mother," and afterwards, "And Abraham took another wife, and her name was Keturah."</p>
    </midrashim>
</midrash>
