<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="midrashim_schema.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<midrash>
    <section user="sam">
        <verse>
            <versenum>Genesis 17:15</versenum>
            <versetext> And Elohim said to Avraham [As for] Sarai your wife, do not call her by the
                name Sarai, for Sarah is her name.</versetext>
            <versenum>Genesis 17:16</versenum>
            <versetext>I will bless her, and I will also give you a son through her. I will bless
                her, and she will be [a mother] of nations [assemblies], kings of peoples [who rule
                over nations] will descend from her.</versetext>
            <versenum>Genesis 17:17</versenum>
            <versetext>Avraham fell on his face and laughed [rejoiced]. He said in his heart: Can a
                hundred year old man have children? Shall Sarah, who is ninety years old give
                birth?</versetext>
            <versenum>Genesis 17:18</versenum>
            <versetext>And Avraham said to [before] Elohim: May it be granted that Yishmael live
                before You.</versetext>
            <versenum>Genesis 17:19</versenum>
            <versetext> Elohim said: Indeed, your wife Sarah will bear you a son, and you will name
                him Yitzchok. I will establish My covenant with him as an eternal covenant to his
                descendants after him.</versetext>
        </verse>
        <midrashim book="BereishitRabbah">
            <source>
                <midtext>Bereishit Rabbah</midtext>
                <midpass>39</midpass>
            </source>
            <p><quotation cite="genesis12:5">And the souls that they had made in Haran.</quotation>
                Said <ref rabbi="Elazar_ben_Zimra">Rabbi Elazar ben Zimra</ref>: <function
                    definition="create">Even if every creature on earth conspired to create
                        <paren>out of nothing</paren> even one mosquito, they could not give it a
                        <ref item="soul">soul</ref>--and you say <quote>the souls that they had
                        made.</quote></function> Therefore <paren>they must be</paren> they must be
                those who lived with them and converted. And it meant <quote>converted</quote> why
                did it say <quote>made?</quote>
                <function definition="create">In order to teach you that each one who brings an idol
                    worshipper and converts him, it is as though he created him.</function> And
                    <function definition="he they">why did it say that <quote>they made</quote>
                    rather than <quote>that he made?</quote></function> Said <ref rabbi="Rav_Hunna"
                    >Rav Huna</ref>: <ref character="abraham">Abraham</ref> would convert the men,
                and <ref character="sarah">Sarah</ref> would convert the women. </p>
            <!-- Rav Huna was a talmudist, not a rabbi; important distinction? -->
        </midrashim>
        <midrashim book="BereishitRabbah">
            <source>
                <midtext>Bereishit Rabbah</midtext>
                <midpass>45</midpass>
                <!-- unclear which verse numbers -->
            </source>
            <p>...2. "And <ref character="sarah sarai">Sarai</ref> said to <ref character="abraham"
                    >Abram</ref>, <quotation cite="genesis16:2">Look, the Lord has kept me from
                    bearing</quotation>
                <paren><ref bibverse="genesis16:2">Gen.16:2</ref></paren> as follows: <quote>Said
                    she, I know the source of my affliction: It is not as people say <paren>of a
                        barren woman</paren>, <quote>she needs a talisman, she needs a
                    charm</quote>, but Look, the <ref god="Lord">Lord</ref> has kept me from
                    bearing.</quote></p>
            <p>" , ...<ref rabbi="Shimon_ben_Yohai">Rabbi Shimon ben Yohai</ref> said <quote
                    speaker="Shimon_ben_Yohai"><ref character="hagar">Hagar</ref> was <ref
                        character="pharaoh">Pharaoh's</ref> daughter. When he saw the deeds on
                    behalf of <ref character="sarah">Sarah</ref> in his house, he took his daughter
                    and gave her to him, saying, <speech speaker="pharaoh">better that my daughter
                        by a maidservant in this house than a mistress in another house.</speech>
                    This is what is written: <quotation cite="genesis16:1">She had an Egyptian
                        handmaid whose name was <ref character="hagar"
                    >Hagar</ref>.</quotation></quote>
                <paren>In other words:</paren>
                <hebrew>ha agrikh</hebrew>: <quote><translation heb="ha agrikh">This is your
                        reward.</translation></quote></p>
            <p>And he went into <ref character="hagar">Hagar</ref> and she conceived <paren><ref
                        bibverse="genesis16:4">Gen. 16:4</ref></paren>. <ref rabbi="Levi_bar_Hayta"
                    >Rabbi Levi bar Hayta</ref> said: <quote speaker="Levi_bar_Hayta">She became
                    pregnant at the first intimacy.</quote> Said <ref rabbi="Eleazar">Rabbi
                    Eleazar</ref>: <quote speaker="Eleazar">A woman never conceives by the first
                    intimacy.</quote> An objection is raised: surely it is written, So both of <ref
                    character="lot">Lot's</ref> daughters got pregnant by their father <paren><ref
                        bibverse="genesis19:36">Gen. 19:36</ref></paren>? Said <ref rabbi="Tanhuma"
                    >R. Tanhuma</ref>: <quote speaker="Tanhuma">By an effort of will power they
                    brought forth their virginity, and conceived at the second <quote>act of
                        intercourse</quote>. The first act is what they did to themselves.</quote>
                Said <ref rabbi="Chanina_ben_Pazi">Rabbi Chanina ben Pazi</ref>: <quote
                    speaker="Chanina_ben_Pazi">Thorns are neither weeded nor sown, but they grow and
                    spring up on their own. But how much suffering and effort for wheat to grow! Why
                    were the matriarchs barren?</quote>
                <ref rabbi="Levi">Rabbi Levi</ref> said in <ref rabbi="Shila">Rabbi Shila’s</ref>
                name and <ref rabbi="Chelbo">Rabbi Chelbo</ref> in <ref rabbi="Yochanan">R.
                    Yochanan’s</ref> name: <quote speaker="Levi Chelbo">Because the <ref
                        god="Holy_One_of_Blessing">Holy One of Blessing</ref> yearns for their
                    prayers and supplications, as it is written <quotation cite="SongOfSongs2:14">O
                        my dove, you on the clefts of the rock let Me see your face, let Me hear
                        your voice</quotation></quote>
                <ref bibverse="SongOfSongs2:14">Song of Songs 2:14</ref>: Why did I make you barren?
                In order to <quotation cite="SongOfSongs2:14">see your face... hear your
                    voice</quotation>. <ref rabbi="Azariah">Rabbi Azariah</ref> said in the name of
                    <ref rabbi="Yochanan_bar_Papa">Rabbi Yochanan bar Papa</ref>: <quote
                    speaker="Azariah">So that their husbands might cling to them in their
                    beauty.</quote>
                <ref rabbi="Huna">Rabbi Huna</ref> in the name of <ref rabbi="Hiya bar Abba">Rabbi
                    Hiya bar Abba</ref> said: <quote speaker="Huna">So that they might pass the
                    greater part of their life without hard work.</quote>
                <ref rabbi="Huna">Rabbi Huna</ref> and <ref rabbi="Avun">R. Avun</ref> in the name
                of <ref rabbi="Meir">Rabbi Meir</ref>: <quote speaker="Huna Avun">So that their
                    husbands might derive pleasure from them, for when a woman is with child she is
                    disfigured and does not care for her appearance.</quote> The ninety years that
                    <ref character="sarah">Sarah</ref> did not bear she was like a bride in her
                canopy. Ladies would come to ask how she was, and she would say to them, <speech
                    speaker="sarah">Go and ask about the welfare of this wretched woman
                        <paren>Hagar</paren><!-- elected not to consider this a character reference b/c Hagar is alluded to and only named in the translation -->!</speech>
                <ref character="hagar">Hagar</ref> would tell them: <speech speaker="hagar">My
                    mistress <ref character="sarah sarai">Sarai</ref> is not inside what she is
                    outside: she appears to be righteous but she is not righteous, had she been a
                    righteous woman, see how many years have passed without her conceiving, whereas
                    I conceived in one night!</speech> Said <ref character="sarah">Sarah</ref>:
                    <speech speaker="sarah">Am I going to argue with this woman?! I should argue
                    with her master!...</speech></p>
            <p>'And <ref character="abraham">Avram</ref> said to <ref character="sarah sarai"
                    >Sarai</ref>: <speech speaker="abraham">do it her what is good in your
                    eyes!</speech>
                <paren><ref bibverse="genesis19:6">Gen. 19:6</ref></paren> He said to her: <speech
                    speaker="abraham">what do I care about her well being or her harm?
                        <paren>But</paren> It is written: <quotation cite="deuteronomy21:14">You
                        will not deal with her as a slave since you humbled her</quotation>
                    <paren><ref bibverse="deuteronomy21:14">Deuteronomy 21:14</ref></paren>, and
                    this one, after we made her suffer, we will enslave her? I don't care about her
                    well being or her harm. <paren>But</paren> It is written <quotation
                        cite="exodus21:8">he shall not have the right to sell her to foreigners,
                        since he broke faith with her</quotation>
                    <paren><ref bibverse="exodus21:8">Exodus 21:8</ref></paren> and this one, after
                    we made her a master we will make her a slave? I don't care about her well being
                    or her harm.</speech>
                <ref bibverse="genesis16:6">Then <ref character="sarah sarai">Sarai</ref> treated
                    her harshly, and she ran away from her.</ref>
                <ref rabbi="Aba_bar_Kahana">Rabbi Aba bar Kahana</ref> said: <quote
                    speaker="Aba_bar_Kahana">she forbade her from having sexual relations.</quote>
                <ref rabbi="Berachia">Rabbi Berachia</ref> said: <quote speaker="Berachia">she
                    slapped her face with a slipper.</quote>
                <ref rabbi="Berachia">Rabbi Berachia</ref> in the name of <ref
                    rabbi="Aba_Bar_Kahana">Rabbi Aba Bar Kahana</ref> said: <quote
                    speaker="Berachia">She made her carry water buckets and bath towels to the
                    baths.</quote> And she called the name of <ref god="Ad-nai">Ad-nai</ref> who
                talked to her <quotation cite="genesis16:13">You are <ref god="El-Roi"
                    >El-Roi</ref></quotation>
                <paren><ref bibverse="genesis16:13">Gen. 16:13</ref></paren>
                <ref rabbi="Yehuda_bar_Simon">Rabbi Yehuda bar Simon</ref> and <ref rabbi="Yochanan"
                    >Rabbi Yochanan</ref> said, in the name of <ref rabbi="Eleazar_Bar Shimeon"
                    >Rabbi Eleazar Bar Shimeon</ref>: <quote speaker="Yochanan Yochanan">The <ref
                        god="Holy_One_of_Blessing">Holy One of Blessing</ref> did not grant speaking
                    with women, with the exception of that righteous one <paren>Sarah</paren>, and
                    even that had a particular reason.</quote>
                <ref rabbi="Aba">Rabbi Aba</ref> said, in the name of <ref rabbi="Beiri">Rabbi
                    Beiri</ref>: <quote speaker="Aba">How many roundabouts He did in order to talk
                    to her!</quote>
                <ref bibverse="genesis18:15">He said: 'no, you did laugh!'</ref>
                <paren><ref bibverse="genesis18:16">Gen. 18:16</ref></paren> But it is written:
                    <quotation cite="genesis16:13">and she called the name of <ref god="Ad-nai"
                        >Ad-nai</ref></quotation> who talked to her '<quotation cite="genesis16:13"
                    >You are El-Roi</quotation>''! <ref rabbi="Yehoshua_Bar_Nechemiah">Rabbi
                    Yehoshua Bar Nechemiah</ref> said: <quote speaker="Yehoshua_Bar_Nechemiah">it
                    was through an angel.</quote> But it is written: <quotation cite="genesis25:23"
                    >And God said to her</quotation><paren><ref bibverse="genesis25:23">Gen.
                        25:23</ref></paren>! Said <ref rabbi="Levi">Rabbi Levi</ref>, in the name of
                    <ref rabbi="Eleazar">Rabbi Eleazar</ref>, in the name of <ref
                    rabbi="Yosi_ben_Zimra">Rabbi Yosi ben Zimra</ref>: <quote speaker="Levi">it was
                    through a name.</quote> '<quotation cite="genesis16:13">You are El
                    Roi</quotation>' - said <ref rabbi="Aivu">Rabbi Aivu</ref>: <quote
                    speaker="Aivu">You are the one who sees the sufferings of the
                    persecuted.</quote> 'Since she said: also, here
                    <paren><hebrew>halom</hebrew></paren>], <quotation cite="genesis16:13">I have
                    seen after the One Who sees me.</quotation> She said: Not only I was granted a
                talk, but even royalty, as it is written: <quotation cite="IISamuel7:18">You that
                    brought me this far</quotation>
                <paren><hebrew>halom</hebrew></paren>
                <paren><ref bibverse="IISamuel7:18">II Sam. 7:18</ref></paren>. <speech
                    speaker="hagar">Not only I was granted to see with my mistress, but even if my
                    mistress were with me right now she would not have seen.</speech> Another
                interpretation: <speech speaker="hagar">Not only I was granted to see with my
                    mistress, but now even when I am alone!</speech>
                <ref rabbi="Shmuel_Bar_Nachman">Rabbi Shmuel Bar Nachman</ref> said: <quote
                    speaker="Shmuel_Bar_Nachman">this is similar to a lady to whom the king said
                        <quotation cite="genesis32:17">pass before me</quotation>.</quote> She
                passed before him but was relying on her slave, and hiding her face, and she did not
                see the king - but the slave did. </p>
        </midrashim>
        <midrashim book="BereishitRabbah">
            <!-- associated with gen 17:15 -->
            <source>
                <midtext>Bereishit Rabbah</midtext>
                <midpass>47:1</midpass>
            </source>
            <p><ref god="God">God</ref> said...,<quotation cite="genesis17:15">Sarai your
                    wife...</quotation> In <ref bibverse="proverbs12:4">Proverbs
                    <paren>12:4</paren></ref>, it is written, <quotation cite="proverbs12:4">A woman
                    of valor is a crown to her husband.</quotation>
                <ref rabbi="Aha">Rabbi Aha</ref> said, <quote>Her husband was crowned through her,
                    but she was not crowned through her husband.</quote> Our rabbis taught that she
                ruled over her husband. In all places, the man gives orders, but here <paren><ref
                        bibverse="genesis21:12">Genesis 21:12</ref></paren>, <quotation
                    cite="genesis21:12">In all that Sarah orders you, listen to her
                    voice.</quotation> Said <ref rabbi="Yehoshua_Ben_Korcha">Rabbi Yehoshua Ben
                    Korcha</ref>: <ref item="yud">The Yud</ref> that <ref god="Holy_One_of_Blessing"
                    >the Holy One of Blessing</ref> took from <ref character="sarah sarai"
                    >Sarai</ref> was given half to <ref character="sarah">Sarah</ref>, and half to
                    <ref character="abraham">Avraham</ref>. Said <ref rabbi="Shime'on Bar Yochai"
                    >Rabbi Shime'on Bar Yochai</ref>: The <ref item="yud">Yud</ref> that <ref
                    god="Holy_One_of_Blessing">the Holy One of Blessing</ref> took from <ref
                    character="sarah sarai">Sarai</ref> flew and posted itself in front of the <ref
                    item="throne">Throne</ref> of <ref god="Holy_One">the Holy One</ref>, and said:
                    <speech speaker="yud"><ref god="Master_of_the_Universe">Master of the
                        Universe</ref>! Because I am the smallest letter You took me out of the name
                    of <ref character="sarah sarai">Sarai</ref> the Righteous!!</speech>
                <ref god="Holy_One">The Holy One</ref> said: <speech speaker="god">In the past you
                    were in the name of a woman, and in the end of the name! Now I will put you in
                    the name of a man, and on the beginning of the name, as it is written</speech>
                <quotation cite="numbers13:16">And <ref character="moses">Moshe</ref> called <ref
                        character="joshua">Hosea Bin Nun</ref>
                    <ref character="joshua">Yehoshua</ref></quotation>
                <paren><ref bibverse="numbers13:16">Numbers 13:16</ref></paren>. Said <ref
                    rabbi="Mana">Rabbi Mana</ref>: <quote speaker="Mana"><ref
                        character="sarah sarai">Sarai</ref> was just <paren>a princess</paren> for
                    herself, now she will be a princess for all the world.</quote></p>
        </midrashim>
        <midrashim book="BereishitRabbah">
            <source>
                <midtext>Bereishit Rabbah</midtext>
                <midpass>53</midpass>
            </source>
            <p>AND <ref character="sarah">SARAH</ref> SAID: <quotation cite="genesis21:6">GOD HAS
                    MADE JOY FOR ME; EVERY ONE THAT HEARS WILL REJOICE WITH ME</quotation>
                <paren><ref bibverse="genesis21:6">Gen. 21:6</ref></paren>. <ref rabbi="Berekiah">R.
                    Berekiah</ref>, <ref rabbi="Judah_b._R._Simon">R. Judah b. R. Simon</ref>, and
                    <ref rabbi="Hanan">R. Hanan</ref> in the name of <ref rabbi="Samuel_b._R._Isaac"
                    >R. Samuel b. R. Isaac</ref> said: <quote speaker="Samuel_b._R._Isaac">If <ref
                        character="reuben">Reuben</ref> has cause to rejoice, what does it matter to
                        <ref character="simeon">Simeon</ref>? Similarly, if <ref character="sarah"
                        >Sarah</ref> was remembered, what did it matter to others? But when the
                    matriarch <ref character="sarah">Sarah</ref> was remembered <paren>gave
                        birth</paren>, many other barren women were remembered with her; many deaf
                    gained their hearing; many blind had their eyes opened, many insane became sane.
                    For <quote>making</quote>
                    <paren>HAS MADE</paren> is mentioned here, and also elsewhere, viz. And he made
                    a release to the provinces <paren><ref bibverse="ester2:18">Est. II,
                        18</ref></paren>. As the making mentioned there means that a gift was
                    granted to the world,l so the making mentioned here means that a gift was
                    granted to the world.</quote>
                <ref rabbi="Levi">R. Levi</ref> said: She increased the light of the luminaries:
                    <quote>making</quote> is mentioned here, viz. <ref bibverse="genesis21:6">GOD
                    HAS MADE FOR ME</ref>, while elsewhere it says, And <ref god="God">God</ref>
                made the two lights <paren><ref bibverse="genesis1:16">Gen. I, 16</ref></paren>.</p>
            <p><quotation cite="genesis21:9">AND SARAH SAW THE SON OF HAGAR THE EGYPTIAN</quotation>
                etc - <ref rabbi="Shimeon_bar_Yohai">Rabbi Shimeon bar Yohai</ref> said: <quote
                    speaker="Shimeon_bar_Yohai"><ref rabbi="Akiva">Rabbi Akiva</ref> used to
                    interpret this to his <paren>Ishmael’s</paren> shame,</quote>
                <ref rabbi="Akiba">Rabbi Akiba</ref> lectured: <quotation cite="genesis21:9">AND
                    SARAH SAW <paren>THE SON OF HAGAR THE EGYPTIAN, WHOM SHE HAD BORNE TO AVRAHAM,
                        MAKING SPORT.</paren></quotation> Now <quotation cite="genesis21:9">making
                    sport</quotation> refers to nothing else but sexual immorality, as in the verse,
                    <quotation cite="genesis39:17">The Hebrew servant, whom you have brought to us,
                    came in to make sport of me.</quotation>
                <paren><ref bibverse="genesis39:17">Gen. 39:17</ref></paren>. This teaches that <ref
                    character="sarah">Sarah</ref> saw <ref character="ishmael">Ishmael</ref> ravish
                maidens, seduced married women and dishonored them. <ref rabbi="R._Ishmael">R.
                    Ishmael</ref> taught: This term <quotation cite="genesis21:9">making
                    sport</quotation> refers to idolatry, as in the verse, <quotation
                    cite="exodus32:6">And the people sat to eat and drink and got up to make
                    sport</quotation>
                <paren><ref bibverse="exodus32:6">Exodus 32:6</ref></paren>. This teaches that <ref
                    character="sarah">Sarah</ref> saw <ref character="ishmael">Ishmael</ref> build
                altars, catch locusts, and sacrifice them. <ref bibverse="Eleazar">R. Eleazar</ref>
                said: <quote speaker="Eleazar">The term <quotation cite="genesis21:9">making
                        sport</quotation> refers to bloodshed, as in the verse, <quotation
                        cite="IIsam2:14">Let the young men, please, arise and make sport before
                        us</quotation>
                    <paren><ref bibverse="IISam2:14">II Sam. 2:14</ref></paren></quote>
                <ref rabbi="Azariah">Rabbi Azariah</ref> said in <ref rabbi="Levi">Rabbi
                    Levi’s</ref> name: <ref character="ishmael">Ishmael</ref> said to <ref
                    character="isaac">Isaac</ref>: <speech speaker="ishmael">Let us go and see our
                    pieces in the field</speech> and he would pick up the bow and shoot arrows,
                aiming in <ref character="isaac">Itzchak's</ref> direction, while pretending to be
                playing <paren>making sport</paren>, as it is written: <quotation
                    cite="proverbs26:18">as a madman who casts fire-brands, arrows, and death; so is
                    the man that deceives his neighbor</quotation>, and said: <quotation
                    cite="proverbs26:19">I am just joking <paren>making sport</paren></quotation>.
                And I <paren>Rabbi Shimon bar
                    Yochai<!-- not including because it's parenthetical --></paren> say that this is
                to be interpreted to the praise <paren>of Ishmael</paren>. This expression of making
                sport is only used as <quote>inheritance</quote>. In the moment that <ref
                    character="isaac">Itzchak</ref> our father was born all were happy. <ref
                    character="ishmael">Ishmael</ref> said to them: <speech speaker="ishmael">are
                    you dumb? I am the first-born, I am going to receive double portion</speech>
                <paren>of the inheritance</paren>, that from the answer of <ref character="sarah"
                    >Sarah</ref> our mother to <ref character="abraham">Avraham</ref>
                <quotation cite="genesis21:10">because the son of this maidservant will not inherit
                    with my son, with Itzchak</quotation> you learn that he would not inherit
                    <quotation cite="genesis21:10">with my son</quotation> - even if he wasn't <ref
                    character="isaac">Itzchak</ref> - and <quotation cite="genesis21:10">with <ref
                        character="isaac">Itzchak</ref></quotation> - even if he wasn't my son. All
                the more so <paren>this is true</paren>
                <quotation cite="genesis21:10">with my son, with <ref character="isaac"
                        >Itzchak</ref></quotation>.</p>
        </midrashim>
        <midrashim book="BereishitRabbah">
            <source>
                <midtext>Bereishit Rabbah</midtext>
                <midpass>58</midpass>
            </source>
            <p>...<quotation cite="ecclesiastics1:5">The sun rises and goes down</quotation>"
                        <paren><ref bibverse="ecclesiastics1:5">Ecclesiastics 1:5</ref></paren>.
                    <ref rabbi="Aba_bar_Kahana">Rabbi Aba bar Kahana</ref> said: <quote
                    speaker="Aba_bar_Kahana">Don't we know that the sun rises and goes down? Rather
                        <paren>this is what it means</paren>: When <ref god="Holy_One_of_Blessing"
                        >the Holy One of Blessing</ref> causes the sun of a righteous person to set,
                    he causes the sun of his fellow to shine forth. The day that <ref rabbi="Akiba"
                        >Rabbi Akiba</ref> died, our rabbi <ref rabbi="Judah_the_Prince"
                            ><paren>Judah the Prince</paren></ref> was born and it was written about
                    him <quotation cite="ecclesiastes1:5">The sun rises and the sun goes
                        down.</quotation> On the day that our rabbi died <ref rabbi="Ada_Bar_Ahava"
                        >Rabbi Ada Bar Ahava</ref> was born and it was written about him <ref
                        bibverse="ecclesiastes1:5"><quotation cite="ecclesiastes1:5">The sun rises
                            and the sun goes down.</quotation></ref> On the day that <ref
                        rabbi="Ada_Bar_Ahava">Rabbi Ada Bar Ahava</ref> died, <ref rabbi="Avin"
                        >Rabbi Avin</ref> was born and it was written about him <ref
                        bibverse="ecclesiastes1:5"><quotation cite="ecclesiastes1:5">The sun rises
                            and the sun goes down.</quotation></ref> On the day that <ref
                        rabbi="Avin">Rabbi Avin</ref> died, his son <ref rabbi="Avin">Rabbi
                        Avin</ref> was born. The day that <ref rabbi="Avin">Rabbi Avin</ref> died,
                        <ref rabbi="Aba_Hoshaya_from_Traya">Aba Hoshaya from Traya</ref> was born.
                    The day that <ref rabbi="Aba_Hoshaya_from_Traya">Aba Hoshaya</ref> died <ref
                        rabbi="Hoshaya">Rabbi Hoshaya</ref> was born and it was written about him
                        <ref bibverse="ecclesiastes1:5"><quotation cite="ecclesiastes1:5">The sun
                            rises and the sun goes down.</quotation></ref> Before the sun of <ref
                        character="moses">Moses</ref> set the sun of <ref character="joshua"
                        >Joshua</ref> shone forth as it is written, <quotation cite="numbers27:18"
                        >God said to Moses, take Joshua Son of Nun</quotation>
                    <paren><ref bibverse="numbers27:18">Numbers 27:18</ref></paren>. Before the sun
                    of <ref character="joshua">Joshua</ref> set the sun of <ref character="itaniel"
                        >Itaniel</ref> son of <ref character="kenaz">Kenaz</ref> shone forth as it
                    is said, <quotation cite="judges1:13">Itaniel son of Kenaz took it</quotation>
                    <paren><ref bibverse="judges1:13">Judges 1:13</ref></paren>. Before the sun of
                        <ref character="eli">Eli</ref> the priest set, the sun of <ref
                        character="samuel">Samuel</ref> shone forth, <quotation cite="1sam3:3">the
                        lamp of God had not yet gone out and Samuel lay on the sanctuary of
                        God</quotation>
                    <paren><ref bibverse="1sam3:3">1 Sam 3:3</ref></paren>. <ref rabbi="Yochanan"
                        >Rabbi Yochanan</ref> said, <quote speaker="yochanan">like a perfect
                        calf.</quote> Before the <ref god="God">God</ref> causes the sun of <ref
                        character="sarah">Sarah</ref> to set, he causes the sun of <ref
                        character="rebecca">Rebecca</ref> to shine forth. For first it says
                        <quotation cite="genesis22:20">Behold Malkah also bore children</quotation>
                    <paren><ref bibverse="genesis22:20">Gen 22:20</ref></paren> and after <quotation
                        cite="genesis23:1">and the life Sarah was one hundred
                    years...</quotation></quote></p>
            <p><ref rabbi="Akiva">Rabbi Akiva</ref> was once sitting and lecturing, and the
                community <paren>his students</paren> was falling asleep. To arouse them, he said:
                    <quote speaker="Avika">How could <ref character="esther">Esther</ref> rule over
                    one hundred and twenty seven provinces? It should be that <ref
                        character="esther">Esther</ref>, a descendant of <ref character="sarah"
                        >Sarah</ref> who lived to one hundred and twenty seven, to rule over one
                    hundred and twenty seven provinces.</quote></p>
            <p>And <ref character="abraham">Avraham</ref> came to eulogize <ref character="sarah"
                    >Sarah</ref>-From where did he come? <ref rabbi="Levi">Rabbi levi</ref> said:
                    <quote speaker="Levi">He came to <ref character="sarah">Sarah</ref> from the
                    burial of <ref character="terach">Terach</ref>.</quote>
                <ref rabbi="Yossi">Rabbi Yossi</ref> said to him: <quote speaker="Yossi">And did not
                    the burial of <ref character="terach">Terach</ref> precede the burial of <ref
                        character="sarah">Sarah</ref> by two years?! Rather, from where did he come?
                    From Mount Moriah.</quote></p>
        </midrashim>

        <midrashim book="BereishitRabbah">
            <source>
                <midtext>Bereishit Rabbah</midtext>
                <midpass>60</midpass>
            </source>
            <p><quotation cite="genesis24:67"><ref bibverse="genesis24:67">And <ref
                            character="isaac">Isaac</ref> brought her into the tent of <ref
                            character="sarah">Sarah</ref>, his mother-</ref></quotation> All the
                days that <ref character="sarah">Sarah</ref> was alive, a <ref item="cloud"
                    >cloud</ref> was connected
                    <paren><!-- it would be nice to get the hebrew word here bc this is an editors or translators choice -->lit.
                    tied</paren> to the entrance of her tent. When she died, the <ref item="cloud"
                    >cloud</ref> stopped <paren>resting at her tent.</paren> And when <ref
                    character="rebecca">Rebecca</ref> came, the <ref item="cloud">cloud</ref>
                returned. All the days that <ref character="sarah">Sarah</ref> was alive, the <ref
                    item="tentDoor">doors</ref> were open wide. When she died, the wideness stopped.
                And when <ref character="rebecca">Rebecca</ref> came, <ref item="tentDoor">the
                    wideness returned</ref>. And all the days that <ref character="sarah"
                    >Sarah</ref> was alive, there was a blessing in her <ref item="dough"
                    >dough</ref>, and when <ref character="sarah">Sarah</ref> died, that blessing
                ended. When <ref character="rebecca">Rebecca</ref> came, <paren>the blessing</paren>
                returned. All the days that <ref character="sarah">Sarah</ref> was alive, there was
                a <ref item="candle">candle</ref> that would burn from <ref
                    holyDay="Sabbath SabbathEve">Sabbath Eve</ref> to <paren>the next</paren>
                <ref holyDay="Sabbath SabbathEve">Sabbath Eve</ref>, and when she died, <ref
                    item="candle">the candle</ref> stopped <paren>burning for so long</paren>. And
                when <ref character="rebecca">Rebecca</ref> came, <paren>the week-long flame of the
                    candle</paren> returned. And as soon as <paren><ref character="isaac"
                        >Isaac</ref></paren> saw her, that <litdev motif="purity">she did the deeds
                    of his mother, separating her <ref item="challah">challah</ref> in purity and
                    separating her <ref item="dough">dough</ref> in purity</litdev>, he brought her
                into the tent. <ref rabbi="Yudan">Rabbi Yudan</ref> said, <quote speaker="Yudan">The
                    Torah teaches you, that if a man has grown-up sons, he should marry them off
                    first and then he should marry. Who do you learn <paren>this teaching</paren>
                    from? From <ref character="abraham">Abraham</ref>: first, <quotation
                        cite="genesis24:67">And Isaac brought her into the tent of Sarah his
                        mother,</quotation> and afterwards, <quotation cite="genesis25:1">And
                        Abraham took another wife, and her name was Keturah</quotation>.</quote></p>
        </midrashim>
        <!-- Genesis 17:15 -->
        <midrashim book="EinYaakov">
            <source>
                <midtext>Ein Yaakov</midtext>
                <edition>Glick Edition</edition>
                <midpass>Rosh Hashanah 1:10</midpass>
            </source>
            <p><ref rabbi="Isaac">R. Isaac</ref> said: <quote speaker="Isaac">A year which is poor
                        <paren>Israel appears humble</paren> in the beginning, will be rich in the
                    end <paren>Israel's request will be granted</paren>. What is the reason for it?
                    For it is written <paren><ref bibverse="deuteronomy11 deuteronomy12">Deut. 11,
                            12</ref></paren> From the beginning of the year even unto the end of the
                    year; i.e., there are two parts in a year, the beginning and the end."</quote>
                <paren>Ib. b</paren>
                <!-- This is the talmud not the torah -->
                <ref rabbi="K._Isaac">K. Isaac</ref> said again: <quote speaker="K._Isaac">A man is
                    judged only according to his deeds at the time of sentence; as it is said
                            <paren><ref bibverse="genesis21 genesis17">Gen. 21, 17</ref></paren> God
                    heard the voice of the lad, as he then was.</quote> Another thing <ref
                    rabbi="R._Isaac">R. Isaac</ref> said: <quote speaker="R._Isaac">Three things
                    cause a man's record of sins to be recalled. Three occasions cause the sins of
                    man to be brought to mind : a threatening wall, calculating during prayer, and
                    one who appeals to the Lord for judgment on his neighbor; for <ref
                        rabbi="R._Chanin">R. Chanin</ref> said: <quote speaker="R._Chanin">Whoever
                        appeals to the Lord for judgment on his neighbor is first punished; as we
                        find in the case of <ref character="sarah">Sarah</ref>, who said <paren><ref
                                bibverse="genesis16 genesis5">Gen. 16, 5</ref></paren> I suffer
                        wrong through thee, may the Lord judge between me and thee. And shortly
                        after this we read <paren><ref bibverse="psalm23 psalm2">Ib. 23,
                            2</ref></paren> And <quotation cite="genesis23:2"><ref
                                character="abraham">Abraham</ref> came to mourn <ref
                                character="sarah">Sarah</ref> and to weep for
                        her.</quotation></quote></quote> Another thing said <ref rabbi="R._Isaac">R.
                    Isaac</ref>: <quote speaker="R._Isaac">Four things cause an evil decree which is
                    passed on man to be torn <paren>annulled</paren>. They are charity, prayer,
                    change of name and change of conduct: Charity, as it is written <paren><ref
                            bibverse="proverbs10:2">Prov. 10, 2</ref></paren>
                    <quotation cite="proverbs10:2">Charity delivereth from death</quotation>;
                    prayer, as it is Written <paren><ref bibverse="psalm97 psalms19">Ps. 97,
                            19</ref></paren>
                    <quotation cite="psalm107:19">They cry unto the Lord when they are in distress,
                        and He saveth them out of their afflictions</quotation>; change of name, as
                    it is written <paren><ref bibverse="genesis17:15">Gen. 17, 15</ref></paren>
                    <quotation cite="genesis17:15">As for Sarai, thy wife, thou shalt not call her
                        name Sarai, but Sarah shall her name be</quotation>: and the text continues
                    saying: <quotation cite="genesis17:16">Then will I bless her, and give thee a
                        son</quotation> also, because of her change of conduct; as it is written
                            <paren><ref bibverse="jonah3:10">Jonah 3, 10</ref></paren>
                    <quotation cite="jonah3:10">And God saw their works that they had turned from
                        their evil ways</quotation>; and immediately following: <quotation
                        cite="jonah3:10">And God bethought Himself of the evil He had said He would
                        do unto them, and He did it not.</quotation></quote> Some add also the
                change of location ; as it is said <paren><ref bibverse="genesis12:1 genesis12:2"
                        >Gen. 12, 1-2</ref></paren>
                <quotation cite="genesis12:1">And God said to Abraham, get thee out from thy
                    land</quotation>
                <paren>and afterwards</paren>
                <quotation cite="genesis12:2">I will make of thee a great nation</quotation>. But
                the former authority claims that the latter one was on account of the merits of the
                land of Israel.</p>
        </midrashim>

        <midrashim book="PirkeiDeRabbiEliezer">
            <source>
                <midtext>Pirkei DeRabbi Eliezer</midtext>
                <midpass>29:5</midpass>
            </source>
            <p><ref rabbi="Gamaliel">Rabban Gamaliel</ref>, the son of <ref
                    rabbi="Jehudah_the_Prince">Rabbi Jehudah the Prince</ref>, said: <quote
                    speaker="Jehudah_the_Prince">When our father <ref character="abraham"
                        >Abraham</ref> was circumcised, on the third day he was very sore, in order
                    to test him. What did the <ref god="Holy_One,_blessed_be_He">Holy One, blessed
                        be He</ref>, do? He pierced one hole in the midst of Gehinnom, and He made
                    the day hot, like the day of the wicked. He went forth, and sat down at the
                    entrance of the tent in the cool of the day, as it is said, <quotation
                        cite="genesis18:1">And he sat at the tent door <paren>in the heat of the
                            day</paren></quotation>
                    <paren><ref bibverse="genesis18:1">Gen. 18:1</ref></paren>. <ref
                        god="Holy_One,_blessed_be_He">The Holy One, blessed be He</ref>, said to the
                    ministering angels: <speech speaker="god">Come ye, let us descend and visit the
                        sick, for the virtue of visiting the sick is great before Me.</speech>
                    <ref god="Holy_One,_blessed_be_He">The Holy One, blessed be He</ref>, and the
                    angels descended to visit our father <ref character="abraham">Abraham</ref>, as
                    it is said, <quotation cite="genesis18:1">And the Lord appeared unto
                        him</quotation>
                    <paren>ibid.</paren>. <ref god="Holy_One,_blessed_be_He">The Holy One, blessed
                        be He</ref>, said to the ministering angels: <speech speaker="god">Come ye
                        and see ye the power of circumcision. Before <ref character="abraham"
                            >Abraham</ref> was circumcised he fell on his face <paren>before
                            Me</paren>, and afterwards I spake with him, as it is said, <quotation
                            cite="genesisi17:17">And Abraham fell upon his face</quotation>
                        <paren><ref bibverse="genesis17:17">Gen. 17:17</ref></paren>. Now that he is
                        circumcised he sits and I stand.</speech> Whence do we know that the <ref
                        god="Holy_One,_blessed_be_He">Holy One, blessed be He</ref>, was standing?
                    Because it is said, <quotation cite="genesis18:2">And he looked, and, lo, three
                        men stood over against him</quotation>
                    <paren><ref bibverse="genesis18:2">Gen. 18:2</ref></paren>.</quote></p>
        </midrashim>
        <!-- Genesis 17:19 -->
        <midrashim book="PirkeiDeRabbiEliezer">
            <source>
                <midtext>Pirkei DeRabbi Eliezer</midtext>
                <midpass>30:3</midpass>
            </source>
            <p><ref rabbi="Jehudah">Rabbi Jehudah</ref> said: <quote speaker="Jehudah">In that night
                        <ref god="Holy_One,_blessed_be_He">the Holy One, blessed be He,</ref> was
                    revealed unto him. He said to him: <quote speaker="god"><ref character="abraham"
                            >Abraham</ref>! Dost thou not know that <ref character="sarah"
                            >Sarah</ref> was appointed to thee for a wife from her mother's womb?
                        She is thy companion, and the wife of thy covenant; <ref character="sarah"
                            >Sarah</ref> is not called thy handmaid, but thy wife; neither is <ref
                            character="hagar">Hagar</ref> called thy wife, but thy handmaid; and all
                        that <ref character="sarah">Sarah</ref> has spoken she has uttered
                        truthfully. Let it not be grievous in thine eyes, as it is said, <quotation
                            cite="genesis21:12">And God said unto Abraham, Let it not be grievous in
                            thy sight</quotation></quote>
                    <paren><ref bibverse="genesis21:12">Gen. 21:12</ref></paren>.</quote></p>
        </midrashim>
        <midrashim book="PirkeiDeRabbiEliezer">
            <!-- this one most deals with the alphabet -->
            <source>
                <midtext>Pirkei DeRabbi Eliezer</midtext>
                <midpass>32:3</midpass>
            </source>
            <p>How do we know <paren>this with reference to</paren>
                <ref character="isaac">Isaac</ref>? Because it is said, <quotation
                    cite="genesis17:19">And God said, Sarah thy wife shall bear thee a son indeed;
                    and thou shalt call his name Isaac</quotation>
                <paren><ref bibverse="genesis17:19">Gen. 17:19</ref></paren>. Why was his name
                called <ref character="isaac">Isaac</ref>? Because <ref item="yod">Yad</ref>
                <paren>the first Hebrew letter of Isaac indicates</paren> the ten trials wherewith
                our father <ref character="abraham">Abraham</ref> was tried; and he withstood them
                all. <ref item="zaddi">Zaddi</ref>
                <paren>the second letter indicates</paren> the ninety <paren>years</paren>, for his
                mother was ninety years <paren>at the birth of Isaac</paren>, as it is said,
                    <quotation cite="genesis17:17">And shall Sarah, that is ninety years old,
                    bear?</quotation>
                <paren><ref bibverse="genesis17:17">Gen. 17:17</ref></paren>. <ref item="cheth"
                    >Cheth</ref>
                <paren>the third letter points to</paren> the eighth <paren>day</paren>, for he was
                circumcised on the eighth day, as it is said, <quotation cite="genesis21:4">And
                    Abraham circumcised his son Isaac, being eight days old</quotation>
                <paren><ref bibverse="genesis21:4">Gen. 21:4</ref></paren>. <ref item="kuf"
                    >Ḳuf</ref>
                <paren>the fourth letter of the name marks</paren> the hundred <paren>years</paren>,
                for his father was an hundred years old <paren>at Isaac's birth</paren>, as it is
                said, <quotation cite="genesis21:5">And Abraham was an hundred years old</quotation>
                <paren><ref bibverse="genesis21:5">Gen. 21:5</ref></paren>.</p>
        </midrashim>
    </section>

    <!-- Ben's -->

    <section user="Ben">
        <!-- genesis 22:1- -->
        <verse>
            <versenum>Genesis 22:1</versenum>
            <versetext>Some time afterward, God put Abraham to the test. He said to him, “Abraham,”
                and he answered, “Here I am.”</versetext>
        </verse>
        <midrashim book="MidrashTanchuma">
            <source>
                <midtext>Midrash Tanchuma</midtext>
                <midpass>Vayera 19:1</midpass>
            </source>
            <p><quotation cite="genesis22:1">And it came to pass after these words that God did
                    prove Abraham</quotation>
                <paren><ref bibverse="genesis22:1">Gen. 22:1</ref></paren>. Scripture states
                elsewhere in reference to this verse: <quotation cite="ecclesiastes8:4-5">Forasmuch
                    as the king’s word hath power; and who may say unto him: “What dost thou?” whoso
                    keepeth the commandment shall know no evil thing</quotation>
                <paren><ref bibverse="ecclesiastes8:4 ecclesiastes8:5">Eccles. 8:4–5</ref></paren>.
                What is meant by this verse? Whatsoever the <ref god="Holy_One,_blessed_be_He">Holy
                    One, blessed be He</ref>, desires to do, He may do, and none may stay His hand.
                What then can be the meaning of <quotation cite="ecclesiastes8:4 ecclesiastes8:5"
                    >And who may say unto Him: “What doest Thou?” whoso keepeth the commandment,
                    etc.</quotation>? These words <ref bibverse="ecclesiastes8:4">whoso keepeth the
                    commandment</ref> allude to the righteous men who perform the commandments of
                the <ref god="Holy_One,_blessed_be_He">Holy One, blessed be He</ref>. And it is
                their decree that He fulfills, as it is written: <quotation cite="job22:28">Thou
                    shalt also decree a thing and it shall be established unto thee, and the light
                    shall shine upon thy ways</quotation>
                <paren><ref bibverse="job22:28">Job 22:28</ref></paren>. An example of this is what
                occurred after they made the golden calf. Though the <ref
                    god="Holy_One,_blessed_be_He">Holy One, blessed be He</ref>, desired to destroy
                them, our master, <ref character="moses">Moses</ref>, restrained the <ref
                    god="Holy_One,_blessed_be_He">Holy One, blessed be He</ref>, as though that were
                possible, just as a man restrains his companion. Hence the <ref
                    god="Holy_One,_blessed_be_He">Holy One, blessed be He</ref>, said to him:
                    <quotation cite="exodus32:10">And now let Me be</quotation>
                <paren><ref bibverse="exodus32:10">Exod. 32:10</ref></paren>. We learn this as well
                from the verse: <quotation cite="deuteronomy9:14">Let Me alone that I may destroy
                    them</quotation>
                <paren><ref bibverse="deuteronomy9:14">Deut. 9:14</ref></paren>. Therefore Scripture
                says: <quotation cite="ecclesiastes8:4-5">Who may say unto him: “What doest thou?”
                    whoso keepeth the commandment.</quotation></p>
        </midrashim>

        <verse>
            <versenum>Genesis 22:2</versenum>
            <versetext>And He said, “Take your son, your favored one, Isaac, whom you love, and go
                to the land of Moriah, and offer him there as a burnt offering on one of the heights
                that I will point out to you.”</versetext>
        </verse>
        <midrashim book="BereishitRabbah">
            <source>
                <midtext>Bereishit Rabbah</midtext>
                <midpass>55:7</midpass>
            </source>
            <p><quotation cite="genesis22:2">And He said: Take, please, your son, etc.</quotation>
                <paren><ref bibverse="genesis22:2">22:2</ref></paren>. Said <ref character="god"
                    >God</ref> to him: <quotation cite="genesis22:2">Take, I beg you" — please —Your
                    son.</quotation>
                <speech speaker="abraham">Which son? I have two sons</speech> he said. <speech
                    speaker="god">Your only son,</speech> replied He. <speech speaker="abraham">This
                    one is the only one of his mother, and this one is the only one of his
                    mother.</speech>
                <speech speaker="god">The one you love</speech>—<speech speaker="abraham">Is there a
                    limit to the affections?</speech>
                <speech speaker="god"><ref character="isaac">Itzchak</ref></speech> said He. And why
                did <ref character="god">God</ref> not reveal it to him without delay? In order to
                make him <paren>Itzchak</paren> even more beloved in his eyes and reward him for
                each and every word spoken. This agrees with the opinion of <ref rabbi="Yohanan"
                    >Rabbi Yohanan</ref>, who said: <quote speaker="Yohanan"><quotation
                        cite="genesis12:1">Get out of your country</quotation>
                    <paren><ref bibverse="genesis12:1">Gen. 12:1</ref></paren> means from your
                    province; <quotation cite="genesis12:1">And from your kindred</quotation>
                    <paren><ref bibverse="genesis12:1">Gen. 12:1</ref></paren>—from your
                    neighborhood; <quotation cite="genesis12:1">And from your father’s
                        house</quotation><paren><ref bibverse="genesis12:1">Gen.
                    12:1</ref></paren>—literally your father’s house.</quote>
                <quotation cite="genesis12:1">To the land that I will show you</quotation>
                <paren><ref bibverse="genesis12:1">Gen. 12:1</ref></paren>. Why did He not reveal it
                to him there and then? In order to make it more beloved in his eyes and to reward
                him for each and every word said, and for each and every step taken. <ref
                    rabbi="Levi_b._Hayata">Rabbi Levi b. Hayata</ref> said: <quote
                    speaker="Levi_b._Hayata">‘Get you’ is written twice, and we do not know which
                    was more precious <paren>in the eyes of God</paren> the first or the second. But
                    when it is written, <quotation cite="genesis22:2">And get you to the land of
                        Moriah</quotation>
                    <paren><ref bibverse="genesis22:2">22:2</ref></paren> it follows that the second
                    occasion was more precious than the first.</quote>
                <quotation cite="genesis22:2">And go yourself to the land of Moriah</quotation>
                <ref rabbi="Chiya_Raba">Rabbi Chiya Raba</ref> and <ref rabbi="Yanai">Rabbi
                    Yanai</ref>
                <paren>disagree</paren>: one says <quote speaker="Chiya_Raba Rabbi_Yanai"
                    ><!-- that is a tricky one to mark with the or -->to the place from which
                        <translation heb="hora'ah">instruction</translation>
                    <paren><hebrew>hora’ah</hebrew></paren> goes out to the world</quote>, and the
                other says <quote speaker="Chiya_Raba Rabbi_Yanai">to the place from which
                        <translation heb="yirah">awe</translation>
                    <paren><hebrew>yirah</hebrew></paren> goes out to the world</quote>. Similarly
                regarding the <translation heb="devir">Holy of Holies</translation>
                <paren><hebrew>devir</hebrew></paren>, <ref rabbi="Chiya">Rabbi Chiya</ref> and <ref
                    rabbi="Yanai">Rabbi Yanai</ref>
                <paren>disagree</paren>: one says <quote speaker="Chiya_Raba Rabbi_Yanai">from the
                    place from which the <translation heb="dibra'ot">commandments</translation>
                    <paren><hebrew>dibra’ot</hebrew></paren> go out to the world</quote>, and one
                says <quote speaker="Chiya_Raba Rabbi_Yanai">from the place from which <translation
                        heb="dibur">speech</translation>
                    <paren><hebrew>dibur</hebrew></paren> goes out to the world</quote>. Similarly
                regarding the <translation heb="aron">ark</translation>
                <paren><hebrew>aron</hebrew></paren>, <ref rabbi="Chiya">Rabbi Chiya</ref> and <ref
                    rabbi="Yanai">Rabbi Yanai</ref>
                <paren>disagree</paren>: one says <quote speaker="Chiya_Raba Rabbi_Yanai">to the
                    place from which the <translation heb="ha'orah">light</translation>
                    <paren><hebrew>ha’orah</hebrew></paren> goes out to the world</quote>, and one
                says <quote speaker="Chiya_Raba Rabbi_Yanai">to the place where awe
                            <paren><hebrew>yirah</hebrew></paren> goes out to the world</quote>.
                    <ref rabbi="Yehoshua_ben_Levi">Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi</ref> said that <quote
                    speaker="Yehoshua_ben_Levi">from there the <ref character="holy one">Holy
                        One</ref>
                    <translation heb="mor'eh">instructs</translation>
                    <paren><hebrew>mor'eh</hebrew></paren> the nations of the world and <translation
                        heb="moridam">brings them down</translation>
                    <paren><hebrew>moridam</hebrew></paren> to Gehinnom.</quote>
                <ref rabbi="Shimon_bar_Yochai">Rabbi Shimon bar Yochai</ref> said, <quote
                    speaker="Shimon_bar_Yochai">to the place which is <translation heb="ra'ui"
                        >aligned</translation>
                    <paren><hebrew>ra'ui</hebrew></paren> with the Holy Temple above. </quote><ref
                    rabbi="Yudan">Rabbi Yudan</ref> said, <quote speaker="Yudan">to the place where
                    there will be an <translation heb="mar'eh">appearance</translation>
                    <paren><hebrew>mar'eh</hebrew></paren> to you.</quote>
                <ref rabbi="Pinchas">Rabbi Pinchas</ref> said, <quote speaker="Pinchas">to the place
                    of the <ref god="Master_of_the_World"><translation heb="marvatah"
                            >Master</translation>
                        <paren><hebrew>marvatah</hebrew></paren> of the World</ref>.</quote>
                <ref rabbi="Rabbis">The Rabbis</ref> said, <quote speaker="Rabbis">to the place
                    where the incense is offered – this is what it says “…I will go to the mountain
                    of myrrh and to the hill of frankincense.” <paren><ref item="shirHashirim4:6"
                            >Shir HaShirim 4:6</ref></paren>
                    <quotation cite="genesis22:2">And offer Him there as a
                        burnt-offering</quotation>
                    <paren><ref bibverse="genesis22:2">Gen. 22:2</ref></paren>.</quote>
                <ref rabbi="Yudan_bar_Simon">Rabbi Yudan bar Simon</ref> said: <quote
                    speaker="Yudan_bar_Simon">He <paren>Avraham</paren> said to Him: <speech
                        speaker="abraham"><ref character="Master_of_the_Universe">Master of the
                            Universe</ref>! Can there be a sacrifice without a priest?</speech> The
                        <ref character="Holy_one_of_Blessing">Holy One of Blessing</ref> replied
                        <speech speaker="god">I have already appointed you to be a priest</speech>
                    as it is written, <quotation cite="psalm110:4">You are a priest for
                        ever</quotation>
                    <paren><ref bibverse="psalm110:4">Ps. 110:4</ref></paren>. <quotation
                        cite="genesis22:2">On one of the mountains which I will tell you
                        of</quotation>
                    <paren><ref bibverse="genesis22:2">Gen. 22:2</ref></paren>.</quote>
                <ref rabbi="Huna">Rabbi Huna</ref> said in the name of <ref rabbi="Eliezer">Rabbi
                    Eliezer</ref> the son of <ref rabbi="Yosei_HaGelili">Rabbi Yosei HaGelili</ref>:
                    <quote speaker="Huna">The <ref character="Holy_one_of_Blessing">Holy One of
                        Blessing</ref> first places the righteous in doubt and suspense, and then
                    reveals to them the real meaning of the matter, as it is written <quotation
                        cite="genesis12:1">the land that I will show you</quotation>
                    <paren><ref bibverse="genesis12:1">Gen. 12:1</ref></paren>; <quotation
                        cite="genesis12:1">On one of the mountains which I will tell
                    you</quotation>; <quotation cite="jonah3:2">And make to it the proclamation that
                        I bid you</quotation>
                    <paren><ref bibverse="jonah3:2">Jonah 3:2</ref></paren>; similarly, <quotation
                        cite="ezekiel3:22">Arise, go out into the plain and I will there speak with
                        you</quotation>
                    <paren><ref bibverse="ezekiel3:22">Ezek. 3:22</ref></paren>.</quote></p>
        </midrashim>

        <verse>
            <versenum>Genesis 22:2</versenum>
            <versetext>And He said, “Take your son, your favored one, Isaac, whom you love, and go
                to the land of Moriah, and offer him there as a burnt offering on one of the heights
                that I will point out to you.”</versetext>
            <versenum>Genesis 22:4</versenum>
            <versetext>On the third day Abraham looked up and saw the place from afar.</versetext>
        </verse>
        <midrashim book="MidrashTanchuma">
            <source>
                <midtext>Midrash Tanchuma</midtext>
                <midpass>Shmini, Siman 2:1</midpass>
            </source>
            <p><paren><ref bibverse="leviticus9:1">Lev. 9:1</ref></paren>
                <quotation cite="leviticus9:1">And it came to pass on the eighth day….</quotation>
                This text is related <paren>to <ref bibverse="psalm75:5">Ps. 75:5</ref></paren>,
                    <quotation cite="psalm75:5">I say to the merrymakers, ‘Do not make
                    merry….’</quotation> What is the meaning of <paren>the words</paren>, <quotation
                    cite="psalm75:5">I say to the merrymakers <paren>rt.: hll</paren>, ‘do not make
                    merry <paren>rt.: hll</paren>?’</quotation>4 <paren>The verse refers</paren> to
                whoever sings in a mahanaim <translation heb="mahol">dance</translation>
                <paren><hebrew>mahol</hebrew></paren>,5 and so it says <paren>in <ref
                        bibverse="judges21:21">Jud. 21:21</ref></paren>, <quotation
                    cite="judges21:21">to <translation heb="lehol">dance</translation>
                    <paren><hebrew>lehol</hebrew></paren> in the dances.</quotation>
                <paren>Because no happiness endures for a mortal</paren>
                <paren><ref bibverse="psalm75:5">Ps. 75:5</ref></paren>, <quotation cite="psalm75:5"
                    >I say to the merrymakers, ‘Do not make merry <paren>rt.:
                    hll</paren>.’</quotation> Why? The one who is happy today shall not be happy
                tomorrow; and the one who is depressed today shall not be depressed tomorrow. And so
                it says <paren>in <ref bibverse="ecclesiastes2:2">Eccl. 2:2</ref></paren>,
                    <quotation cite="ecclesiastes2:2">Of laughter I said, ‘It is mad <paren>rt.:
                        hll</paren>….’</quotation>6 Are you willing to understand? As behold, even
                the happiness of the <ref god="Holy_One,_blessed_be_He">Holy One, blessed be
                    He</ref>, did not endure. When? When the <ref god="Holy_One,_blessed_be_He">Holy
                    One, blessed be He</ref>, created His world. He was very happy, as stated
                    <paren>in <ref bibverse="psalm104:31">Ps. 104:31</ref></paren>, <quotation
                    cite="psalm104:31">the Lord shall be happy in His works.</quotation> It also
                says <paren>in <ref bibverse="genesis1:31">Gen. 1:31</ref></paren>, <quotation
                    cite="genesis1:31">Then God saw everything which He had made; and behold, it was
                    very good.</quotation>
                <paren>These verses are</paren> to teach you that the <ref
                    god="Holy_One,_blessed_be_He">Holy One, blessed be He</ref>, found pleasure in
                and took pride in His works. Then He gave the first <ref character="adam">Adam</ref>
                an easy commandment, but he did not fulfill it. Immediately He rendered him a
                verdict7 <paren>of death</paren>, as stated <paren>in <ref bibverse="genesis3:19"
                        >Gen. 3:19</ref></paren>, <quotation cite="genesis3:19">for dust you are,
                    and unto dust you shall return.</quotation> So He, as it were, did not remain in
                His happiness but said, <speech speaker="god">I created everything only for the
                    human, and now he dies. What pleasure is there for Me?</speech>
                <paren>Now surely if the Holy One, blessed be He,</paren> did not remain
                    <paren>happy</paren>, how much the less shall people <paren>remain
                    happy!</paren> It is therefore stated <paren>in <ref bibverse="psalm75:5">Ps.
                        75:5</ref></paren>, <quotation cite="psalm75:5">I say to the merrymakers,
                    ‘do not make merry.’</quotation> How happy <ref character="abraham"
                    >Abraham</ref> was! He was blessed in the world, magnified, slew some kings and
                handed over heaven and earth to the <ref god="Holy_One,_blessed_be_He">Holy One,
                    blessed be He</ref>. Also when the <ref god="Holy_One,_blessed_be_He">Holy One,
                    blessed be He</ref>, gave him a son at age one hundred, he circumcised him and
                reared him. Then finally he was told <paren>in <ref bibverse="genesis22:2">Gen.
                        22:2</ref></paren>, <quotation cite="genesis22:2">Please take your son, your
                    only son…, and go unto the land of Moriah, and offer him there as a burnt
                    offering.</quotation> So he made a three-day journey, as stated <paren>in <ref
                        bibverse="genesis22:4">Gen. 22:4</ref></paren>, <quotation
                    cite="genesis22:4">On the third day….</quotation> When he returned from Mount
                Moriah, he buried <ref character="sarah">Sarah</ref>. He did not find a place to
                bury her until he bought one for four hundred silver shekels. Then after that, old
                age came upon him. Now surely if such was the case with <ref character="abraham"
                    >Abraham</ref> the righteous, how much the more is it the case with the wicked!
                    <ref character="isaac">Isaac</ref> did not remain in his happiness: He escaped
                from the sword and from the men of Gerar. And <ref god="God">God</ref> informed them
                about who he was, so that they came to him. Thus it is stated <paren>in <ref
                        bibverse="genesis26:26 genesis26:28"/></paren>, <quotation
                    cite="genesis26:26,28">Then <ref character="abimelech">Abimelech</ref> came unto
                    him from Gerar</quotation> and they said, <quotation cite="genesis26:28">We have
                    clearly seen that the Lord is with you. But he did not remain in his happiness.
                    Rather <paren>according to <ref bibverse="genesis27:1">Gen. 27:1</ref></paren>,
                        <quotation cite="genesis27:1">Now it came to pass, that when Isaac was old
                        and his eyes were too weak to see.</quotation> So just as <paren>this loss
                        of happiness</paren> happened in the case of <ref character="isaac"
                        >Isaac</ref> the burnt offering of the <ref god="Holy_One,_blessed_be_He"
                        >Holy One, blessed be He</ref>, <paren>according to <ref
                            bibverse="genesis22:2">Gen. 22:2</ref></paren>, how much the more does
                    it happen in the case of the wicked! <ref character="jacob">Jacob</ref> was the
                    first-born of the <ref god="Holy_One,_blessed_be_He">Holy One, blessed be
                        He</ref>, as stated <paren>in <ref bibverse="exodus4:22">Exod.
                        4:22</ref></paren>, <quotation cite="exodus4:22">Israel is My first-born
                        son.</quotation> How happy he was! He saw a ladder, and <paren>according to
                            <ref bibverse="genesis28:12 genesis28:13">Gen. 28:12-13</ref></paren>
                    <quotation cite="genesis28:12 genesis28:13">the angels of god were ascending and
                        descending <paren>….</paren> And behold, the Lord stood upon it and said, I
                        am the Lord….</quotation> Then he went to <ref character="laban"
                    >Laban</ref>, fled from <ref character="esau">Esau</ref>, became <ref
                        character="laban">Laban</ref>'s servant for twenty years and in the end
                    became wealthy, sired children and returned in peace. He also met <ref
                        character="esau">Esau</ref> and was saved from him, and paid his vow. But in
                    the end he did not remain in his happiness. Instead <paren>according to <ref
                            bibverse="genesis34:1">Gen. 34:1</ref></paren>, <quotation
                        cite="genesis34:1">Now Dinah <paren>the daughter whom Leah had borne to
                            Jacob</paren> went out…,</quotation> and was raped. There also came upon
                    him the trouble over <ref character="joseph">Joseph</ref>. Now surely if <ref
                        character="jacob">Jacob</ref> the righteous – one to whom the <ref
                        god="Holy_One,_blessed_be_He">Holy One, blessed be He</ref>, had said,
                        <quotation cite="isaiah49:3">In whom I will be glorified,</quotation> as
                    stated <paren>in <ref bibverse="isaiah49:3">Is. 49:3</ref></paren>, <quotation
                        cite="isaiah49:3">Israel, in whom I will be glorified</quotation> – did not
                    remain in his happiness, how much the less will the wicked <paren>so remain! It
                        is therefore stated <paren>in <ref bibverse="psalm75:5">Ps.
                            75:5</ref></paren>, <quotation cite="psalm75:5">I say to the
                            merrymakers, ‘Do not make merry.’</quotation></paren> How happy <ref
                        character="joshua">Joshua</ref> was! He slew thirty-one kings, gave Israel
                    the land to possess, and distributed it. In addition all Israel gave him a
                        <paren>helping</paren> hand and said <paren>in <ref bibverse="joshua1:18"
                            >Josh. 1:18</ref></paren>, <quotation cite="joshua1:18">Anyone who
                        disobeys your command… <paren>shall be put to death. Such an honor
                            was</paren></quotation> something of which <paren>even</paren>
                    <ref character="moses">Moses</ref> our master did not merit. Still he
                        <paren>i.e., <ref character="joshua">Joshua</ref></paren> did not remain in
                    his happiness, but rather died childless. It is therefore stated <paren>in <ref
                            bibverse="psalm75:5">Ps. 75:5</ref></paren>, <quotation cite="psalm75:5"
                        >I say to the merrymakers, ‘Do not make merry.’</quotation> How happy <ref
                        character="eli">Eli</ref> was, when he was king, chief justice, and high
                    priest! It is so stated <paren>in <ref bibverse="ISamuel1:9">I Sam.
                        1:9</ref></paren>, <quotation cite="ISamuel1:9">now Eli <paren>the
                            priest</paren> was sitting on the throne by the doorpost of the Temple
                        of the Lord.</quotation>
                    <quotation cite="ISamuel1:9">Now Eli the priest was sitting on the
                        throne,</quotation> because he was king. <paren>He was</paren>
                    <quotation cite="ISamuel1:9">by the doorpost of the Temple of the
                        Lord,</quotation> because he was chief justice. Still he did not remain in
                    his happiness. Instead <paren>according to <ref bibverse="ISamuel4:18">I Sam.
                            4:18</ref></paren>, <quotation cite="ISamuel4:18">And it came to pass
                        that when he <paren>i.e., a messenger</paren> mentioned the ark of God, he
                            <paren>i.e., Eli</paren> fell backward from off the throne….</quotation>
                    Moreover, his two sons, <ref character="hophni">Hophni</ref> and <ref
                        character="phinehas">Phinehas</ref> died. So just as this <paren>shift in
                        fortune</paren> happened with <ref character="eli">Eli</ref> the righteous,
                    how much the more <paren>does it happen with</paren> the wicked! You find
                    neither man nor woman who saw joys like <ref character="elisheba_bat_amminadab"
                        >Elisheba bat Amminadab</ref>, <paren>the wife of <ref character="aaron"
                            >Aaron</ref>, as stated <paren>in <ref bibverse="exodus6:23">Exod.
                                6:23</ref></paren>, <quotation cite="exodus6:23">And Aaron took for
                            a wife Elisheba bat Amminadab</quotation></paren>.8 She saw her husband
                    become high priest serving in the high priesthood and <paren>as a</paren>
                    prophet. In addition, <ref character="moses">Moses</ref>, her husband's brother,
                    was king and prophet. Moreover, her sons were deputies <paren>to the high
                        priest</paren> in the priesthood, and her brother <ref character="nahshon"
                        >Nahshon</ref> was head of all of the princes of Israel.9 Still she did not
                    remain in her happiness. Rather, when two of her sons went in to offer a
                    sacrifice, <paren>according to <ref bibverse="leviticus10:2">Lev.
                        10:2</ref>,</paren>
                    <quotation cite="leviticus10:2">Fire came forth from before the Lord and
                        consumed them, so that they died before the Lord.</quotation> It is
                    therefore stated <paren>in <ref bibverse="psalm75:5">Ps. 75:5</ref></paren>,
                        <quotation cite="psalm75:5">I say to the merrymakers, ‘Do not make
                        merry.’</quotation> And so <ref character="solomon">Solomon</ref> said
                        <paren>in <ref bibverse="ecclesiastes2:2">Eccl. 2:2</ref></paren>,
                        <quotation cite="ecclesiastes2:2">Of laughter I said, ‘It is
                        mad.’</quotation> There is a story about one of the great Babylonian
                        <paren>scholars</paren>, who married off his son,10 and made a great banquet
                    for the sages. He said to his son, <quote speaker="Babylonian_scholar">Go up and
                        bring us a jar of such and such a wine from the attic.</quote> He went up to
                    the attic. <paren>There</paren> a snake <paren>from</paren> among the jars bit
                    him, and he died. His father remained with those who were reclining <paren>at
                        his table</paren>. So he delayed and did not come. <paren>Finally,</paren>
                    his father said, <quote speaker="Babylonian_scholar">Let me go up and see what
                        my son is doing.</quote> His father went up <paren>and</paren> found him
                    cast down dead among the jars. What did that saint do? He waited by himself
                    until the guests had eaten and drunk sufficiently. When they had finished, he
                    said, <quote speaker="Babylonian_scholar">You came to say a bridegrooms'
                        blessing over my son. <paren>But instead</paren> say a mourners' blessing
                        over him. You came to bring my son to the wedding canopy.
                            <paren>Instead</paren> bring him to <paren>his</paren> grave.</quote>
                    They said about <ref rabbi="Zakkay_of_Kabul">R. Zakkay of Kabul</ref> and they
                    opened about him <paren>in the words of <ref bibverse="ecclesiastes2:2">Eccl.
                            2:2</ref></paren>, <quotation cite="ecclesiastes2:2">Of laughter I said,
                        ‘It is mad; and what does joy do?’</quotation></quotation></p>
        </midrashim>

        <verse>
            <versenum>Genesis 22:6</versenum>
            <versetext>Abraham took the wood for the burnt offering and put it on his son Isaac. He
                himself took the firestone and the knife; and the two walked off
                together.</versetext>
            <versenum>Genesis 22:8</versenum>
            <versetext>And Abraham said, “God will see to the sheep for His burnt offering, my son.”
                And the two of them walked on together.</versetext>
        </verse>
        <midrashim book="MidrashTanchumaBuber">
            <source>
                <midtext>Midrash Tanchuma Buber</midtext>
                <midpass>Vayera 46:9</midpass>
            </source>
            <p>Another interpretation <paren>of <ref bibverse="genesis22:6">Gen. 22:6</ref>,
                    cont.</paren>: <quotation cite="genesis22:6">SO BOTH OF THEM WENT OFF
                    TOGETHER</quotation>. <ref rabbi="Abbin_Berabbi_the_Levite">R. Abbin Berabbi the
                    Levite</ref> said: <quote speaker="Abbin_Berabbi_the_Levite">While they were
                    walking, <ref character="satan">Satan</ref> came to <ref character="isaac"
                        >Isaac</ref> on his right hand and said: <speech speaker="satan">Alas,
                        wretched son of a wretched woman, how many fasts did your mother fast until
                        you came? 172 Now the old man has gone mad in his old age, and here he is
                        going to slaughter you.</speech>
                    <ref character="isaac">Isaac</ref> turned back and said to his father: <speech
                        speaker="isaac">Look at what this one is saying to me!</speech> He said to
                    him: <speech speaker="abraham">He has come to confuse you, but the <ref
                            god="Holy_One">Holy One</ref> shall not confuse us</speech>, as stated
                        <paren>in <ref bibverse="genesis22:8">Gen. 22:8</ref></paren>: <quotation
                        cite="genesis22:8">GOD WILL SEE TO THE LAMB FOR A BURNT
                    OFFERING</quotation>. So nevertheless <paren>according to <ref
                            bibverse="genesis22:6">Gen. 22:6</ref></paren>: <quotation
                        cite="genesis22:6">SO BOTH OF THEM WENT OFF TOGETHER</quotation>. How old
                    was <ref character="isaac">Isaac</ref>? He was thirty-seven years
                    old.173</quote></p>
        </midrashim>

        <verse>
            <versenum>Genesis 22:7</versenum>
            <versetext>Then Isaac said to his father Abraham, “Father!” And he answered, “Yes, my
                son.” And he said, “Here are the firestone and the wood; but where is the sheep for
                the burnt offering?”</versetext>
            <versenum>Genesis 22:8</versenum>
            <versetext>And Abraham said, “God will see to the sheep for His burnt offering, my son.”
                And the two of them walked on together.</versetext>
        </verse>
        <midrashim book="BereishitRabbah">
            <source>
                <midtext>Bereishit Rabbah</midtext>
                <midpass>56:4</midpass>
            </source>
            <p><quotation cite="genesis22:7">And Itzchak spoke to Avraham his father, and said: My
                    father</quotation>
                <paren><ref bibverse="genesis22:7">Gen. 22:7</ref></paren>. <ref character="samael"
                    >Samael</ref> went to the our father <ref character="abraham">Avraham</ref> and
                said: <speech speaker="samael">Old man, old man! Have you lost your mind <paren>lit.
                        have you lost your heart</paren>? You are going to slay a son given to you
                    at the age of a hundred!</speech>
                <speech speaker="abraham">Even this I do,</speech> replied he. <paren><ref
                        character="samael">Samael</ref> said:</paren>
                <speech speaker="samael">And if He sets you an even greater test, can you stand
                    it?!</speech>
                <paren>as it is written</paren>
                <quotation cite="job4:2">If a thing be put to you as a trial, will you be
                    wearied</quotation>
                <paren><ref bibverse="job4:2">Job 4:2</ref></paren>? <speech speaker="abraham">Even
                    more than this,</speech> he replied. <paren><ref character="samael">Samael</ref>
                    said:</paren>
                <speech speaker="samael">Tomorrow He will say to you, “You are guilty of murder, you
                    murdered your son!”</speech> He replied: <speech speaker="abraham">Still I
                    go</speech>. Seeing that he could achieve nothing with him, he approached <ref
                    character="isaac">Itzchak</ref> and said: <speech speaker="samael">Son of an
                    unhappy mother! He is going to slay you!</speech> He replied: <speech
                    speaker="isaac">Still I go</speech>. <ref character="samael">Samael</ref> said:
                    <speech speaker="Samael">If so, all those fine tunics which your mother made be
                    a legacy for <ref character="ishmael">Ishmael</ref>, the hated of her house, and
                    you don't care <paren>lit. don't let it enter your heart</paren>?</speech> If a
                word is not completely effective, it may yet be effective in part, that’s why it is
                written, <quotation cite="genesis22:7">And Itzchak spoke to Avraham his father, and
                    said: My father</quotation>: why <paren>his</paren> father, <paren>my</paren>
                father twice? So that he should be filled with compassion for him. <quotation
                    cite="genesis22:7">And he said: Behold, the fire and the wood.</quotation>
                <ref character="abraham">Avraham</ref> said to him: <speech speaker="abraham">May
                    that man who has thus seduced him be drowned! Any way, <quotation
                        cite="genesis22:8">God will provide himself the lamb, my son</quotation>;
                    and if not you are <quotation cite="genesis22:8">the lamb for the burnt-offering
                        my son.</quotation></speech> So <quotation cite="genesis22:8">"they went
                    both of them together"</quotation>
                <paren><ref bibverse="genesis22:8">Gen. 22:8</ref></paren> — one to slaughter and
                the other to be slaughtered.</p>
        </midrashim>

        <verse>
            <versenum>Genesis 22:2</versenum>
            <versetext>And He said, “Take your son, your favored one, Isaac, whom you love, and go
                to the land of Moriah, and offer him there as a burnt offering on one of the heights
                that I will point out to you.”</versetext>
            <versenum>Genesis 22:11</versenum>
            <versetext>Then an angel of the LORD called to him from heaven: “Abraham! Abraham!” And
                he answered, “Here I am.”</versetext>
            <versenum>Genesis 22:12</versenum>
            <versetext>And he said, “Do not raise your hand against the boy, or do anything to him.
                For now I know that you fear God, since you have not withheld your son, your favored
                one, from Me.”</versetext>
        </verse>
        <midrashim book="BereishitRabbah">
            <source>
                <midtext>Bereishit Rabbah</midtext>
                <midpass>56:8</midpass>
            </source>
            <p>Another explanation: <ref rabbi="Itzchak">Rabbi Itzchak</ref> said, <quote
                    speaker="Itzchak">At the time that <ref character="abraham">Avraham</ref> sought
                    to bind <ref character="isaac">Itzchak</ref>, his son, <paren>the latter</paren>
                    said to him, <speech speaker="isaac">Father, I am a young man and I am concerned
                        lest my body shake from fear of the knife and I will trouble you, and lest
                        the slaughtering will be invalid and it will not be considered a sacrifice
                        for you. Rather, tie me very well.</speech> Immediately, <quotation
                        cite="genesis22:8">and he bound Itzchak.</quotation> Could he really tie up
                    a man of thirty-seven <paren>a different version: of twenty six years</paren>?
                    Rather, it was with his agreement. Immediately. <quotation cite="genesis22:9"
                        >And Avraham sent his hand.</quotation> He sends his hand to take the knife
                    and his eyes brings down tears and the tears fall onto the eyes of <ref
                        character="isaac">Itzchak</ref> from the mercy of his father. And
                    nonetheless, the heart was happy to do the will of <ref god="Maker">his
                        Maker</ref>. And the angels gathered in many groups above them. What did
                    they yell out? <quotation cite="isaiah33:7">The ways have become desolate, the
                        wayfarer has ceased; He has rescinded His covenant; He has become disgusted
                        with the cities</quotation>
                    <paren><ref bibverse="isaiah33:7">Isaiah 33:7</ref></paren> – He does not desire
                    Jerusalem and the Temple that he had in mind to bequeath to the children of <ref
                        character="isaac">Itzchak</ref>. 'He did not consider a man' – merit did not
                    stand <ref character="abraham">Avraham</ref> well: 'No creation has importance
                    in front of Me.'</quote>
                <ref rabbi="Acha">Rabbi Acha</ref> said, <quote speaker="Acha"><ref
                        character="abraham">Avraham</ref> started to wonder, <speech
                        speaker="abraham">These words are only words of wonder. Yesterday, you told
                        me <paren><ref bibverse="genesis21:12">Genesis 21:12</ref></paren>,
                            <quotation cite="genesis21:12">Because in Itzchak will your seed be
                            called.</quotation> And <paren>then</paren> you went back and said,
                            <quotation cite="genesis22:2">Please take your son.</quotation> And now
                        You say to me, <quotation cite="genesis22:12">Do not send your hand to the
                            youth.</quotation> It is a wonder!</speech> The <ref
                        god="Holy_One,_blessed_be_He">Holy One, blessed be He</ref>, said, <speech
                        speaker="God">'<ref character="abraham">Avraham</ref>, <quotation
                            cite="psalm89:35">I will not profane My covenant and the utterances of
                            My lips, I will not change</quotation>
                        <paren><ref bibverse="psalm89:35">Psalms 89:35</ref></paren> – When I said,
                            <quotation cite="genesis22:2">Please take your son,</quotation> I did
                        not say, "slaughter him," but rather, "and bring him up." For the sake of
                        love did I say <paren>it</paren> to you: I said to you, "Bring him up," and
                        you have fulfilled My words. And now, bring him down.’</speech>
                    <paren>A different version: They said a parable about a king that said to his
                        friend, <speech speaker="king">Bring up your son to my table.</speech> His
                        friend brought him up and his knife was in his hand. The king said, <speech
                            speaker="king">And did I say to you, "Bring him up to eat him?" I said
                            to you, "Bring him up"</speech> – <paren>and this was</paren> because of
                            <paren>the king's</paren> love.) This is <paren>the meaning of</paren>
                        what is written <paren><ref bibverse="jeremiah19:5">Jeremiah
                            19:5</ref></paren>, <quotation cite="jeremiah19:5">it did not come up on
                            My heart</quotation> – that is <ref character="isaac"
                        >Itzchak</ref>.</paren></quote></p>
        </midrashim>

        <verse>
            <versenum>Genesis 22:11</versenum>
            <versetext>Then an angel of the LORD called to him from heaven: “Abraham! Abraham!” And
                he answered, “Here I am.”</versetext>
            <versenum>Genesis 22:12</versenum>
            <versetext>And he said, “Do not raise your hand against the boy, or do anything to him.
                For now I know that you fear God, since you have not withheld your son, your favored
                one, from Me.”</versetext>
        </verse>
        <midrashim book="BereishitRabbah">
            <source>
                <midtext>Bereishit Rabbah</midtext>
                <midpass>56:7</midpass>
            </source>
            <p><quotation cite="genesis22:11">And the angel of Ad-nai called to him out of heaven,
                    and said: Abraham, Abraham</quotation>
                <paren><ref bibverse="genesis22:11">Gen. 22:11</ref></paren>. <ref rabbi="Hiya"
                    >Rabbi Hiya</ref> taught: <quote speaker="Hiya">This is an expression of love,
                    this is an expression of urging.</quote>
                <ref rabbi="Eliezer_ben_Yaakov">Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov</ref> said: <quote
                    speaker="Eliezer_ben_Yaakov">He spoke to him and to future generations, there is
                    no generation which does not contain people like <ref character="abraham"
                        >Avraham</ref>, and there is no generation which does not contain people
                    like <ref character="yaakov">Yaakov</ref>, <ref character="moses">Moshe</ref>,
                    and <ref character="samuel">Shmuel</ref>. <quotation cite="genesis22:12">And he
                        said: "Do not lay your hand etc."</quotation>
                    <paren><ref bibverse="genesis22:12">Gen. 22:12</ref></paren> Where was the knife? Three
                    tears had fallen from the angels of service and the knife dissolved. <ref
                        character="abraham">Avraham</ref> said: <speech speaker="abraham">I will
                        strangle him,</speech> He said: <quotation cite="genesis22:12">Do not lay
                        your hand upon the lad.</quotation>
                    <paren><ref character="abraham">Avraham</ref></paren> said <speech
                        speaker="abraham">I will take a drop of blood from him</speech> - He said to
                    him: ‘Neither do <translation heb="me'uma">anything</translation>
                    <paren><hebrew>me'uma</hebrew></paren> to him’ <paren>meaning</paren> inflict no
                        <translation heb="muma">blemish</translation>
                    <paren><hebrew>muma</hebrew></paren> upon him. "Because now I know"
                        <paren>meaning</paren> I have made it known to all that you love Me,
                        <quotation cite="genesis22:12">"and you have not withheld, etc"</quotation>.
                    And do not say that all ills that do not affect one’s own body are not ills,
                    rather I ascribe merit to you as though I had told to you to sacrifice yourself
                    and you did not refuse.</quote></p>
        </midrashim>

        <verse>
            <versenum>Genesis 22:13</versenum>
            <versetext>When Abraham looked up, his eye fell upon a ram, caught in the thicket by its
                horns. So Abraham went and took the ram and offered it up as a burnt offering in
                place of his son.</versetext>
        </verse>
        <midrashim book="MidrashTanchuma">
            <source>
                <midtext>Midrash Tanchuma</midtext>
                <midpass>Vayera 23:9</midpass>
            </source>
            <p>The <ref god="Holy_One,_blessed_be_He">Holy One, blessed be He</ref>, answered:
                    <quote speaker="God">You have spoken what was in you heart, now I will say what
                    I wish to say. In the future <ref character="isaac">Isaac</ref>’s descendants
                    will sin against Me, and I will judge them on <ref holyDay="Rosh_Hashanah">Rosh
                        Hashanah</ref>. If they want Me to discover something to their credit, and
                    to recall for their advantage the binding of <ref character="isaac">Isaac</ref>,
                    let them blow upon this shofar.</quote>
                <ref character="abraham">Abraham</ref> asked: <speech speaker="Abraham">What
                    shofar?</speech> The <ref god="Holy_One,_blessed_be_He">Holy One, blessed be
                    He</ref>, said: <quote speaker="God">Turn around.</quote> Then it was that <ref
                    character="abraham">Abraham</ref> lifted up his eyes, and looked, and behold,
                behind a ram caught in the thicket by his horns <paren><ref bibverse="genesis22:13"
                        >Gen. 22:13</ref></paren>. This was one of the ten things that were created
                at twilight.17</p>
        </midrashim>

        <verse>
            <versenum>Genesis 22:1-19</versenum>
            <versetext>Some time afterward, God put Abraham to the test. He said to him, “Abraham,”
                and he answered, “Here I am.” And He said, “Take your son, your favored one, Isaac,
                whom you love, and go to the land of Moriah, and offer him there as a burnt offering
                on one of the heights that I will point out to you.” So early next morning, Abraham
                saddled his ass and took with him two of his servants and his son Isaac. He split
                the wood for the burnt offering, and he set out for the place of which God had told
                him. On the third day Abraham looked up and saw the place from afar. Then Abraham
                said to his servants, “You stay here with the ass. The boy and I will go up there;
                we will worship and we will return to you.” Abraham took the wood for the burnt
                offering and put it on his son Isaac. He himself took the firestone and the knife;
                and the two walked off together. Then Isaac said to his father Abraham, “Father!”
                And he answered, “Yes, my son.” And he said, “Here are the firestone and the wood;
                but where is the sheep for the burnt offering?” And Abraham said, “God will see to
                the sheep for His burnt offering, my son.” And the two of them walked on together.
                They arrived at the place of which God had told him. Abraham built an altar there;
                he laid out the wood; he bound his son Isaac; he laid him on the altar, on top of
                the wood. And Abraham picked up the knife to slay his son. Then an angel of the LORD
                called to him from heaven: “Abraham! Abraham!” And he answered, “Here I am.” And he
                said, “Do not raise your hand against the boy, or do anything to him. For now I know
                that you fear God, since you have not withheld your son, your favored one, from Me.”
                When Abraham looked up, his eye fell upon a ram, caught in the thicket by its horns.
                So Abraham went and took the ram and offered it up as a burnt offering in place of
                his son. And Abraham named that site Adonai-yireh, whence the present saying, “On
                the mount of the LORD there is vision.” The angel of the LORD called to Abraham a
                second time from heaven, and said, “By Myself I swear, the LORD declares: Because
                you have done this and have not withheld your son, your favored one, I will bestow
                My blessing upon you and make your descendants as numerous as the stars of heaven
                and the sands on the seashore; and your descendants shall seize the gates of their
                foes. All the nations of the earth shall bless themselves by your descendants,
                because you have obeyed My command.” Abraham then returned to his servants, and they
                departed together for Beer-sheba; and Abraham stayed in Beer-sheba.</versetext>
        </verse>
        <midrashim book="SeferHaYashar">
            <source>
                <midtext>Sefer HaYashar (midrash)</midtext>
                <midpass>Book of Genesis, Vayera 18</midpass>
            </source>
            <p>And while <ref character="abraham">Abraham</ref> was pursuing his journey with his
                son <ref character="isaac">Isaac</ref>, behold <ref character="satan">Satan</ref>
                came and ‎appeared to <ref character="abraham">Abraham</ref> in the figure of a very
                old man, of a very modest and humble spirit. And ‎ approaching <ref
                    character="abraham">Abraham</ref> he said unto him: <speech speaker="satan">Art
                    thou a fool or an idiot that thou goest to do such a ‎thing this day and even to
                    thy only son? For behold the <ref god="Lord">Lord</ref> had given him unto thee
                    in the last of thy days and in thy old age, and now wilt thou go and slaughter
                    him without any wrong ‎action of his, and destroy the life of thy only son?
                    Knowest thou not, and hast thou not heard ‎of it, that such a thing could never
                    have come from the <ref god="Lord">Lord</ref>, for the <ref god="Lord"
                        >Lord</ref> hath never done ‎unto man a great evil like this upon the earth
                    to say unto a man go and slay thy son?</speech> And ‎<ref character="abraham"
                    >Abraham</ref> hearing these words knew at once that it was the voice of <ref
                    character="satan">Satan</ref> who attempted to ‎lead him astray from the way of
                the <ref god="Lord">Lord</ref>, and <ref character="abraham">Abraham</ref> refused
                to hearken to the voice of ‎<ref character="satan">Satan</ref>. And <ref
                    character="abraham">Abraham</ref> rebuked him severely and <ref
                    character="satan">Satan</ref> went away from him. And <ref character="satan"
                    >Satan</ref> soon ‎returned and came to <ref character="isaac">Isaac</ref>,
                appearing unto him in the guise of a young man of good figure ‎and pleasant looks.
                And he approached <ref character="isaac">Isaac</ref> and said unto him: <speech
                    speaker="satan">Knowest thou or hast thou ‎heard of it, that thy old and foolish
                    father carries thee to the slaughter to-day without any cause? And now, my boy,
                    do not listen unto him and do not obey him, for he is old and foolish, ‎and do
                    not suffer thy precious life and thy handsome person to perish from the
                    earth.</speech> And ‎when <ref character="isaac">Isaac</ref> had heard these
                words he turned unto <ref character="abraham">Abraham</ref> saying: <speech
                    speaker="isaac">Hast thou heard, oh, my ‎father, the words of this man, such and
                    such are his remarks.</speech> And <ref character="abraham">Abraham</ref>
                answered unto his ‎son <ref character="isaac">Isaac</ref> saying: <speech
                    speaker="abraham">Beware of him my son, do not listen unto his word and pay no
                    attention unto ‎him, for that is <ref character="satan">Satan</ref>, who is
                    resolved to turn us this day from following the commandments of ‎our <ref
                        god="Lord">Lord</ref>.</speech> And <ref character="abraham">Abraham</ref>
                rebuked <ref character="satan">Satan</ref> once more, and he went away from them.
                And when ‎<ref character="satan">Satan</ref> saw that he could not succeed in that
                manner, he disappeared suddenly and went on ‎before them on their road, and changed
                himself into a mighty river full of water on the road. ‎And when <ref
                    character="abraham">Abraham</ref> and <ref character="isaac">Isaac</ref> and his
                two young men reached that place they saw a river, ‎large and very powerful like
                unto the mighty waters. And they went into the river, the waters ‎of which reached
                up to their legs and they passed on through it. But the waters grew always ‎deeper
                and reached finally to their necks, when they were all terrified on account of the
                ‎water. And as they passed on <ref character="abraham">Abraham</ref> at once
                recognized the place, and <ref character="abraham">Abraham</ref> knew that ‎there
                hath never been a river before on that place. And <ref character="abraham"
                    >Abraham</ref> said unto his son <ref character="isaac">Isaac</ref>: <speech
                    speaker="abraham">I ‎know this place well and there hath never been before
                    neither a river nor any water, and it is ‎only the work of <ref
                        character="satan">Satan</ref>, who is doing these things in order to turn us
                    this day from the ‎commandments of the <ref god="Lord">Lord</ref>.</speech> And
                    <ref character="abraham">Abraham</ref> rebuked <ref character="satan"
                    >Satan</ref> saying unto him: <speech speaker="abraham">May the <ref god="Lord"
                        >Lord</ref> ‎rebuke thee, oh <ref character="satan">Satan</ref>, get thee
                    behind us for we are following the order of our <ref god="Lord"
                    >Lord</ref>.</speech> And ‎<ref character="satan">Satan</ref> became terrified
                at <ref character="abraham">Abraham</ref>'s voice and he departed from them,</p>
        </midrashim>

        <verse>
            <versenum>Genesis 22:1-19</versenum>
            <versetext>Some time afterward, God put Abraham to the test. He said to him, “Abraham,”
                and he answered, “Here I am.” And He said, “Take your son, your favored one, Isaac,
                whom you love, and go to the land of Moriah, and offer him there as a burnt offering
                on one of the heights that I will point out to you.” So early next morning, Abraham
                saddled his ass and took with him two of his servants and his son Isaac. He split
                the wood for the burnt offering, and he set out for the place of which God had told
                him. On the third day Abraham looked up and saw the place from afar. Then Abraham
                said to his servants, “You stay here with the ass. The boy and I will go up there;
                we will worship and we will return to you.” Abraham took the wood for the burnt
                offering and put it on his son Isaac. He himself took the firestone and the knife;
                and the two walked off together. Then Isaac said to his father Abraham, “Father!”
                And he answered, “Yes, my son.” And he said, “Here are the firestone and the wood;
                but where is the sheep for the burnt offering?” And Abraham said, “God will see to
                the sheep for His burnt offering, my son.” And the two of them walked on together.
                They arrived at the place of which God had told him. Abraham built an altar there;
                he laid out the wood; he bound his son Isaac; he laid him on the altar, on top of
                the wood. And Abraham picked up the knife to slay his son. Then an angel of the LORD
                called to him from heaven: “Abraham! Abraham!” And he answered, “Here I am.” And he
                said, “Do not raise your hand against the boy, or do anything to him. For now I know
                that you fear God, since you have not withheld your son, your favored one, from Me.”
                When Abraham looked up, his eye fell upon a ram, caught in the thicket by its horns.
                So Abraham went and took the ram and offered it up as a burnt offering in place of
                his son. And Abraham named that site Adonai-yireh, whence the present saying, “On
                the mount of the LORD there is vision.” The angel of the LORD called to Abraham a
                second time from heaven, and said, “By Myself I swear, the LORD declares: Because
                you have done this and have not withheld your son, your favored one, I will bestow
                My blessing upon you and make your descendants as numerous as the stars of heaven
                and the sands on the seashore; and your descendants shall seize the gates of their
                foes. All the nations of the earth shall bless themselves by your descendants,
                because you have obeyed My command.” Abraham then returned to his servants, and they
                departed together for Beer-sheba; and Abraham stayed in Beer-sheba.</versetext>
        </verse>
        <midrashim book="SeferHaYashar">
            <source>
                <midtext>Sefer HaYashar (midrash)</midtext>
                <midpass>Book of Genesis, Vayera 21</midpass>
            </source>
            <p>And <ref character="abraham">Abraham</ref> slew the ram upon the altar for a burnt
                offering before the <ref god="Lord">Lord</ref> instead of his ‎son <ref
                    character="isaac">Isaac</ref>; and <ref character="abraham">Abraham</ref>
                sprinkled of the blood of the ram upon the altar, and he exclaimed, ‎saying: <speech
                    speaker="abraham">This is instead of my son, and may it be considered as the
                    blood of my son before the ‎<ref god="Lord">Lord</ref>, even on this
                    day</speech>; and whatsoever <ref character="abraham">Abraham</ref> performed
                upon that occasion he always ‎accompanied it by these words: <speech
                    speaker="abraham">This is in the place of my son, and may it be considered this
                    ‎day before the <ref god="Lord">Lord</ref> in place of my son.</speech> And when
                    <ref character="abraham">Abraham</ref> had completed the services at the ‎altar,
                and the offering was accepted by the <ref god="Lord">Lord</ref>, it was actually
                considered as if it had been ‎<ref character="isaac">Isaac</ref> that was
                sacrificed. And the <ref god="Lord">Lord</ref> blessed <ref character="abraham"
                    >Abraham</ref> and his seed on that day. And <ref character="Satan">Satan</ref>
                ‎hurried unto <ref character="sarah">Sarah</ref> and appeared unto her in the guise
                of a very humble and lowly old man, ‎while <ref character="abraham">Abraham</ref>
                was still performing his duties at the altar before the Lord. And <ref
                    character="satan">Satan</ref> said unto ‎<ref character="sarah">Sarah</ref>:
                    <speech speaker="satan">Knowest thou not the work that <ref character="abraham"
                        >Abraham</ref> hath done with thine only son to-day? Verily, ‎he hath taken
                        <ref character="isaac">Isaac</ref> and built an altar and killed him and
                    brought him for a burnt offering upon ‎the altar; and <ref character="isaac"
                        >Isaac</ref> was weeping and praying before his father, but he never heeded
                    his cries ‎and he had no mercy upon him.‎‏</speech> ‏And after repeating his
                story, <ref character="satan">Satan</ref> departed from <ref character="sarah"
                    >Sarah</ref>; and ‎<ref character="sarah">Sarah</ref> having heard these words
                of <ref character="satan">Satan</ref>, took him for one of the sons of man who had
                been ‎with her son and who had come to tell her these words.‎‏ ‏And <ref
                    character="sarah">Sarah</ref> lifted up her voice and she ‎wept and cried
                bitterly over the loss of her son; and she lay down upon the ground and she
                ‎scattered dust upon her head, and she exclaimed: <speech speaker="sarah">Oh, my
                    son, <ref character="isaac">Isaac</ref> | oh, my son would that I ‎had died
                    to-day in thy place |</speech> And she continued weeping and crying: <speech
                    speaker="sarah">It grieves me for thy ‎sake, oh, my son I Would that I had died
                    to-day in thy place!</speech> And she kept on lamenting, and ‎she said: <speech
                    speaker="sarah">It grieves me for thy sake, now after I have raised thee and
                    brought thee up, my joy ‎hath been turned into mourning for thee, I who was
                    yearning for thee, I who have been crying ‎and praying to the <ref god="Lord"
                        >Lord</ref> for thee until I bare thee at the age of ninety years, and now
                    hast thou ‎been given up to-day to the knife and to the fire to be made a burnt
                    offering; yet I will take ‎comfort, my son, in the thought that all hath been
                    caused by the word of the <ref god="Lord">Lord</ref>, as thou ‎hast performed
                    the commandment of thy <ref god="God">God</ref>, and who can rebel against the
                    word of <ref god="God">God</ref> in ‎whose hand is the <ref item="soul"
                        >soul</ref> of every living creature? Thou art just, O <ref
                        god="Lord_our_God">Lord our God</ref>, and all thy ‎works are justice and
                    righteousness; and I am exceedingly glad at the words of thy command, ‎and
                    though mine eye weepeth, my heart rejoiceth within me.</speech>‎‏ ‏And <ref
                    character="sarah">Sarah</ref> placed her head ‎upon the bosom of one of her maid
                servants and she became silent like a rock. And soon after ‎she arose and went about
                to make inquiries until she reached Hebron. And she questioned ‎every passer-by that
                she met on the road, but no one could tell her anything concerning the ‎fate of her
                son.‎</p>
        </midrashim>
    </section>

    <!-- Thyra's -->

    <section user="Thyra">
        <verse>
            <versenum>Psalm 24.1</versenum>
            <versetext>Of David. A psalm. The earth is the LORD’s and all that it holds, the world
                and its inhabitants.</versetext>
            <versenum>Psalm 24.2</versenum>
            <versetext>For He founded it upon the ocean, set it on the nether-streams.</versetext>
            <versenum>Psalm 24.3</versenum>
            <versetext>Who may ascend the mountain of the LORD? Who may stand in His holy
                place?—</versetext>
            <versenum>Psalm 24.4</versenum>
            <versetext>He who has clean hands and a pure heart, who has not taken a false oath by My
                life or sworn deceitfully.</versetext>
            <versenum>Psalm 24.5</versenum>
            <versetext>He shall carry away a blessing from the LORD, a just reward from God, his
                deliverer.</versetext>
            <versenum>Psalm 24.6</versenum>
            <versetext>Such is the circle of those who turn to Him, Jacob, who seek Your
                presence.Selah.</versetext>
            <versenum>Psalm 24.7</versenum>
            <versetext>O gates, lift up your heads! Up high, you everlasting doors, so the King of
                glory may come in!</versetext>
            <versenum>Psalm 24.8</versenum>
            <versetext>Who is the King of glory?— the LORD, mighty and valiant, the LORD, valiant in
                battle.</versetext>
            <versenum>Psalm 24.9</versenum>
            <versetext>O gates, lift up your heads! Lift them up, you everlasting doors, so the King
                of glory may come in!</versetext>
            <versenum>Psalm 24.10</versenum>
            <versetext>Who is the King of glory?— the LORD of hosts, He is the King of
                glory!Selah.</versetext>
        </verse>

        <midrashim book="MidrashEinYaakov">
            <source>
                <midtext>Midrash Ein Yaakov</midtext>
                <edition>Glick Edition</edition>
                <midpass>Rosh Hashanah 4:1</midpass>
            </source>
            <p><paren>Fol. 31</paren> We are taught in a Baraitha: <ref rabbi="Juda">R. Juda</ref>
                said, in the name of <ref rabbi="Akiba">R. Akiba</ref>: <quote speaker="Juda">What
                        <paren>song</paren> did <paren>the Levites</paren> chant on the first day of
                    the week? <paren><ref bibverse="psalm24">Ps. 24</ref></paren>
                    <quotation cite="psalm24">The earth is the Lord's and the fulness thereof,
                        because He <paren>the Lord, in establishing the world</paren> took
                        possession and gave <paren>His creatures</paren> possession <paren>invested
                            them with life</paren>, and <paren>became</paren> the Sovereign of the
                        world.</quotation> What did they sing on the second day? <paren><ref
                            bibverse="psalm48">Ib. 48</ref></paren>
                    <quotation cite="psalm48">Great is the Lord and greatly to be praised, because
                            <paren>on that day</paren> He divided His works <paren>the heavens from
                            the earth</paren> and reigned over them.</quotation> On the third day
                    they sang <paren><ref bibverse="psalm82">Ib. 82</ref></paren>
                    <ref bibverse="psalm82"><ref god="God">God</ref> standeth in the congregation of
                        the mighty, because <paren>on that day</paren> He, in His wisdom, caused the
                        earth to be revealed and the world to be prepared for its occupants.</ref>
                    On the fourth day they sang <paren><ref bibverse="psalm94">Ib. 94</ref></paren>
                    <ref bibverse="psalm94">O <ref god="Lord">Lord</ref>, to whom retribution
                        belongeth, because <paren>on that day</paren> He created the sun and moon,
                        and in the future He will punish those who would worship them.</ref> On the
                    fifth day they sang <paren><ref bibverse="psalm81">Ib. 81</ref></paren>
                    <ref bibverse="psalm81">Sing aloud unto <ref god="God">God</ref>, our strength,
                        because <paren>on that day</paren> He created the birds and the fishes
                            <paren>which bring</paren> praise to His name.</ref> On the sixth day
                    they sang, <paren><ref bibverse="psalm93">Ib. 93</ref></paren>
                    <ref bibverse="psalm93">The <ref god="Lord">Lord</ref> reigneth. He is clothed
                        in majesty, because <paren>on that day</paren> He finished His works and
                        became sovereign over them.</ref> On the seventh day they sang <paren><ref
                            bibverse="psalm92">Ib. 92</ref></paren>
                    <ref bibverse="psalm92">A psalm, a song, for the <ref holyDay="Sabbath">Sabbath
                            day</ref>; i.e., for the day that is a perfect rest.</ref></quote>
                <ref rabbi="Nechemia">R. Nechemia</ref> said : <quote speaker="Nechemia">What reason
                    had <ref rabbi="Akiba">R. Akiba </ref>to make distinctions among these sections,
                        <paren>for the last refers to a future event, while all the others refer to
                        the past</paren>? We must therefore say that they sang that psalm on the
                        <ref holyDay="Sabbath">Sabbath</ref> day, because He rested.</quote> This is
                contrary to the opinion of <ref rabbi="K'tina">R. K'tina</ref>, for <ref
                    rabbi="K'tina">R. K'tina</ref> said: <quote speaker="K'tina">The world will last
                    six thousand years, and one thousand years it will be waste; as it is said
                            <paren><ref bibverse="isaiah2:11">Is. 2, 11</ref></paren>
                    <ref bibverse="isaiah2:11">And exalted shall be the <ref god="Lord">Lord</ref>
                        alone on that day</ref>"</quote>
                <ref rabbi="Abaye">Abaye</ref>, however, said: <quote speaker="Abaye">Two thousand
                    years it will waste; as it is said <paren><ref bibverse="hosea6:2">Hos. 6,
                            2</ref></paren>
                    <ref bibverse="hosea6:2">He will revive us after two days.</ref></quote></p>
        </midrashim>

        <midrashim book="MidrashEinYaakov">
            <source>
                <midtext>Midrash Ein Yaakov </midtext>
                <edition>Glick Edition</edition>
                <midpass>Berakhot 6:2</midpass>
            </source>
            <p>Our Rabbis taught: <quote speaker="Rabbis">It is prohibited to enjoy anything of this
                    world without saving a benediction, and he who enjoys <paren>the least
                        thing</paren> in this world without saving a benediction defrauds
                            <paren><ref god="Lord">the Lord</ref></paren>. What shall his remedy be?
                    Let him go to a learned man.</quote> What can a learned man do for him when he
                already has transgressed the prohibition? <quote speaker="Raba">But,</quote> said
                    <ref rabbi="Raba">Raba</ref>, <quote speaker="Raba">let him go unto a learned
                    man first; study the laws of benedictions that he may avoid sacrilege.</quote>
                <ref rabbi="Juda">R. Juda</ref> said in the name of <ref character="samuel"
                    >Samuel</ref> : <quote speaker="Juda">He who enjoys <paren>the least
                        thing</paren> in this world without having said a benediction is considered
                    as if he had enjoyed something of the things dedicated to Heaven, for it is said
                            <paren><ref bibverse="psalm24:1">Ps. 24, 1.</ref></paren> Unto the <ref
                        god="Lord">Lord</ref> belongeth the earth and all that filleth it.</quote>
                <ref rabbi="Levi">R. Levi</ref> pointed out the following contradiction: <quote
                    speaker="Levi">It is written <paren><ref bibverse="psalm24:1">Ib.
                        ib.</ref></paren>
                    <ref bibverse="psalm24:1">Unto the <ref god="Lord">Lord</ref> belongeth the
                        earth and all that filleth it</ref>, and it is also written <paren><ref
                            bibverse="psalm115:16">Ib. 115, I6.</ref></paren>
                    <ref bibverse="psalm115:16">The Heavens are the Heavens of the <ref god="Lord"
                            >Lord</ref>; but the earth hath He given to the children of man.</ref>
                    It is not difficult to reconcile <paren>these two verses</paren>. The former
                    refers to the time before he pronounced the benediction <ref
                        bibverse="psalm115:16"><paren>it still belongs to Heaven</paren></ref>,
                        <paren>Ib. b.</paren> and the latter refers to the time after he pronounced
                    the benediction <ref bibverse="psalm115:16"><paren>then it belongs to
                            man</paren></ref>."</quote>
                <ref rabbi="Chanina_b._Papa">R. Chanina b. Papa</ref> said: <quote
                    speaker="Chanina_b._Papa">He who enjoys <paren>anything</paren> in this world
                    without saying a benediction is considered as if he has robbed the <ref
                        god="Holy_One,_praised_be_He">Holy One, praised be He</ref>! and the
                    Congregation of Israel, for it is said <paren><ref bibverse="proverbs28:24">Pr.
                            28, 24.</ref></paren>
                    <ref bibverse="proverbs28:24">Whoso robbeth his father or his mother and saith
                        it is no transgression, he is the companion of a destroyer.</ref> His
                    father, refers to the <ref god="Holy_One,_praised_be_He">Holy One, praised be
                        He</ref>! as it is said <paren><ref bibverse="deuteronomy32:6">Deu. 32,
                            6.</ref></paren>
                    <ref bibverse="deuteronomy32:6">Is He not thy father who hath bought thee</ref>;
                    Or his mother, refers to nothing else but the Congregation of Israel., as it is
                    said <paren><ref bibverse="proverbs1:8">Pr. 1, 8.</ref></paren>
                    <ref bibverse="proverbs1:8">Hear, my son, the instructions of your father and
                        cast not aside the teaching of your mother</ref>.</quote> What is meant by
                He is a companion of a destroyer? <ref rabbi="Chanina_b._Papa">R. Chanina b.
                    Papa</ref> said: <quote speaker="Chanina_b._Papa">He is a companion of <ref
                        character="jeroboam">Jeroboam</ref>, the son of <ref character="nebat"
                        >Nebat</ref>, who has corrupted Israel in their relation to their <ref
                        god="Heavenly_Father">Heavenly Father</ref>."</quote></p>
        </midrashim>
        <midrashim book="MidrashEinYaakov">
            <source>
                <midtext>Midrash Ein Yaakov</midtext>
                <edition>Glick Edition</edition>
                <midpass>Shabbat 16:12</midpass>
            </source>
            <p><ref character="joseph">Joseph</ref>, who honored the <ref holyDay="Sabbath"
                    >Sabbath</ref>, had a very rich neighbor. This neighbor was told by the
                Chaldeans <paren><function definition="Chaldeans">soothsayers</function></paren>
                that all his wealth would eventually be eaten up by <ref character="joseph"
                    >Joseph</ref>. The neighbor, therefore, sold his estate and with the proceeds
                bought a large diamond, which he fixed in his turban. One day, while crossing a
                bridge, a gust of wind blew his turban into the water and a fish swallowed it. This
                fish <paren>being caught</paren> was brought <paren>to the market</paren> on a
                Friday. <quote speaker="fishermen">Who wants to buy fish to-day?</quote> they
                inquired. They were told to go to <ref character="joseph">Joseph</ref>, who honors
                the <ref holyDay="Sabbath">Sabbath</ref> and usually buys fish that day. So they
                brought the fish to him and he bought it. When the fish was cut up, the jewel was
                found and <ref character="joseph">Joseph</ref> sold it for thirteen purses of gold
                denarim. When that old man met him, he said to <ref character="joseph">Joseph</ref>:
                    <quote speaker="old_man">He, who lends to the <ref holyDay="Sabbath"
                        >Sabbath</ref>
                    <paren>incurring additional expenses in its honor</paren> the Sabbath will
                    repay.</quote>
                <ref character="Rabbi">Rabbi</ref> asked <ref rabbi="Ishmael">R. Ishmael</ref>, the
                son of <ref rabbi="Jose">R. Jose</ref>, <quote speaker="Rabbi">What merited the rich
                    people of Palestine who become so wealthy?</quote> He answered thus: <quote
                    speaker="Ishmael">Because they gave their tithes in due season, as it is said
                            <paren><ref bibverse="deuteronomy14:22">Deu. 14, 22.</ref></paren> Thou
                    shalt tithe the tithe, i.e., give tithes, in order that thou mayest become
                    rich."</quote>
                <quote speaker="Rabbi">What merited the rich of Babylon <paren>where people are
                        exempt from tithes</paren> ?</quote>
                <quote speaker="Ishmael">Because,</quote> said <ref rabbi="Ishmael">R.
                Ishmael</ref>, <quote speaker="Ishmael">they honor the Torah.</quote>
                <quote speaker="Rabbi">And what merited the rich of other countries that made them
                    so wealthy ?</quote>
                <quote speaker="Ishmael">Because,</quote> said he, <quote speaker="Ishmael">they
                    honored the <ref holyDay="Sabbath">Sabbath</ref>; for <ref rabbi="Chiya_b._Abba"
                        >R. Chiya b. Abba</ref> said:<quote speaker="Chiya_b._Abba">I sojourned once
                        with a wealthy man in Ludki. and I saw that they brought before him a golden
                        table carried by sixteen men, and having sixteen silver links depending from
                        it ; in these links were fixed bowls, cups, pitchers and dishes, all filled
                        with various kinds of victuals, and all sorts of rare fruits and spices.
                        When setting the table, they said: <ref bibverse="psalm24:1">Unto the <ref
                                god="Lord">Lord</ref> belongs the earth with what filleth it</ref>
                        <paren><ref bibverse="psalm24:1">Ps. 24, 1</ref></paren>. And when they
                        removed the table, they said <ref bibverse="psalm115:16">The heavens are the
                            heavens of the <ref god="Lord">Lord</ref>; but the earth hath he given
                            to the children of men</ref>
                        <paren><ref bibverse="psalm115:16">Ib. 115, 16</ref></paren>. I said to him
                            <quote speaker="Chiya_b._Abba">My son, how have you merited this
                            prosperity?</quote> He said to me: <quote speaker="wealthy_man">I was
                            formerly a butcher, and I always selected the finest cattle to be
                            slaughtered for the <ref holyDay="Sabbath">Sabbath</ref>.</quote> I then
                        said to him : <quote speaker="Chiya_b._Abba">Happy art thou for being so
                            merited and blessed be the <ref god="Lord">Lord</ref> who hath rewarded
                            thee with all this.</quote></quote></quote></p>
        </midrashim>
        <midrashim book="MidrashEinYaakov">
            <source>
                <midtext>Midrash Ein Yaakov </midtext>
                <edition>Glick Edition</edition>
                <midpass>Bava Batra 5:23</midpass>
            </source>
            <p>When <ref rabbi="Dimi">R. Dimi</ref> came from Palestine, he said in the name of <ref
                    rabbi="Jonathan">R. Jonathan</ref>, <quote speaker="Dimi">what is the meaning of
                    the passage <paren><ref bibverse="psalm24:2">Ps. 24, 2</ref></paren><ref
                        bibverse="psalm24:2"> For upon seas he hath founded it, and upon rivers he
                        hath established it?</ref> i.e. the seven seas and four rivers which
                    surround the land of Israel <paren>Palestine</paren>, the seven seas are the
                    seas of Tiberia, Sodom, Chirat, Chiltha, Sipchi, Aspamia, and the ocean; and the
                    four rivers are Jordan, Jarmuch, Kirumyun, and Phiga.</quote> When <ref
                    rabbi="Dimi">R. Dimi</ref> came, he said in the name of <ref rabbi="Jonathan">R.
                    Jonathan</ref> : <quote speaker="Dimi">In the future the angel <ref
                        character="gabriel">Gabriel</ref>
                    <paren>Fol. 75</paren> will go hunting for the <ref character="leviathan"
                        >leviathan</ref>, as it is said <paren><ref bibverse="Job40:25">Job 40,
                            25</ref></paren>
                    <ref bibverse="Job40:25">Canst thou draw out the crocodile
                            <paren>leviathan</paren> with a fishhook or cause his tongue to sink
                        into the baited rope?</ref> And if not for the help of the <ref
                        god="Holy_One,_praised_be_He">Holy One, praised be He</ref>! he would not
                    conquer him, as it is said <paren><ref bibverse="Job40:25">Ib.</ref></paren>
                    <ref bibverse="Job40:25">He is the first in rank . . . he that hath made him can
                        alone bring his sword near to him</ref>.</quote> When <ref rabbi="Dimi">R.
                    Dimi</ref> came, he said also in the name of <ref rabbi="Jochanan">R.
                    Jochanan</ref> : <quote speaker="Dimi">When the <ref character="leviathan"
                        >leviathan</ref> becomes hungry, he expels from his mouth a gas which makes
                    all the waters in the deep boil, as it is said <paren><ref bibverse="Job41:23"
                            >Ib. 41, 23</ref></paren>
                    <ref bibverse="Job41:23">He maketh the deep to boil like a pot. And should he
                        put his head in paradise, not one of the creatures could withstand the bad
                        smell of the gas</ref>, as it is said <paren><ref bibverse="Job41:23"
                            >Ib.</ref></paren>
                    <ref bibverse="Job41:23">He maketh the sea like a seething mixture. And when he
                        gets thirsty, he makes the sea hollow like beds</ref>, as it is said: <ref
                        bibverse="Job41:23">Behind him he causeth his pathway to
                    shine.</ref></quote> And <ref rabbi="Acha_b._Jacob">R. Acha b. Jacob</ref> said:
                    <quote speaker="Acha_b._Jacob">The deep does not come to its natural way before
                    seventy years, as it is said <paren><ref bibverse="Job41:23">Ib.</ref></paren>
                    <ref bibverse="Job41:23">Men esteem the deep to be hoary</ref> — and hoary is
                    not less than seventy years."</quote></p>
        </midrashim>
        <midrashim book="MidrashEinYaakov">
            <source>
                <midtext>Midrash Ein Yaakov </midtext>
                <edition>Glick Edition</edition>
                <midpass>Moed Katan 1:4</midpass>
            </source>
            <p><paren><ref bibverse="deuteronomy9">Ib. 9</ref></paren> But whence do we learn that
                one joy must not be mixed with another? Said <ref rabbi="Juda">R. Juda</ref> in the
                name of <ref character="samuel">Samuel</ref> : <quote speaker="Juda">It is written
                            <paren><ref bibverse="IKings8:65">I Kings 8, 65</ref></paren>
                    <ref bibverse="IKings8:65">And <ref character="Solomon">Solomon</ref> held at
                        the time the feast, etc., seven days and seven days, even fourteen
                        days</ref>. Now, if it be true that one joy may be mixed with another, why
                    then did <ref character="Solomon">Solomon</ref> not postpone his feast until the
                    festival ; for then the seven days of the festival would have served for
                    both?</quote>
                <ref rabbi="Parnach">R. Parnach</ref>, in the name of <ref rabbi="Jochanan">R.
                    Jochanan</ref>, said : <quote speaker="Parnach">In that year the Israelites had
                    not observed the <ref holyDay="Day_of_Atonement">Day of Atonement</ref> and they
                    were perturbed over the sin that might cause them destruction. Whereupon a
                    heavenly voice came forth and said unto them: <speech speaker="heavenly_voice"
                        >All of you are destined for the future world</speech>"</quote> And whence
                do we learn that they were pardoned for that sin? <ref rabbi="Tachlipha">R.
                    Tachlipha</ref> was taught.</p>
        </midrashim>

        <midrashim book="MidrashEinYaakov">
            <source>
                <midtext>Midrash Ein Yaakov </midtext>
                <edition>Glick Edition</edition>
                <midpass>Shabat 2:10</midpass>
            </source>
            <p><paren>Fol. 30a</paren> The following question was asked of <ref
                    rabbi="Tanchum_of_Noy">R. Tanchum of Noy</ref>: <quote>Is it permissible to
                    extinguish the light on the <ref holyDay="Sabbath">Sabbath</ref> for the sake of
                    a sick person ?</quote> He began his answer by saying: <quote
                    speaker="Tanchum_of_Noy">O thou <ref character="Solomon">King Solomon</ref>!
                    Where is thy wisdom and where is thy understanding? Not only do the words
                    contradict your father's words but <paren>they are at variance with</paren>
                    thine own utterances also. Thy father <ref character="David">David</ref> said
                            <paren><ref bibverse="psalm116:17">Ps. 116, 17.</ref></paren>
                    <ref bibverse="psalm116:17">Not the dead can praise the <ref god="Lord"
                            >Lord</ref></ref>, and thou sayest <paren><ref
                            bibverse="Ecclesiastes4:2">Ecc. 4, 2.</ref></paren>
                    <ref bibverse="Ecclesiastes4:2">Thereupon praise I the dead that are already
                        dead</ref>, and again thou sayest <paren><ref bibverse="Ecclesiastes9:4">Ib.
                            9., 4.</ref></paren>
                    <quotation cite="Ecclesiastes9:4">For a living dog fareth better than a dead
                        lion</quotation>. But this is not difficult to explain. When <ref
                        character="David">David</ref> said. Not the dead can praise the <ref
                        god="Lord">Lord</ref>, he meant thus: <speech speaker="David">A man should
                        always occupy himself with the study of the <ref item="Torah">Torah</ref>
                        and meritorious deeds before he dies; for, as soon as he dies, he becomes
                        free from the obligation of <paren>studying</paren> the <ref item="Torah"
                            >Torah</ref> and <paren>fulfilling</paren> meritorious deeds and the
                            <ref god="Holy_One,_praised_be_He">Holy One, praised be He</ref>!
                        accepts no praise of him.</speech> This is what <ref rabbi="Jochanan">R.
                        Jochanan</ref> said : <quote speaker="Jochanan">'What is meant by the
                        passage <paren><ref bibverse="psalm88:61">Ps. 88, 61.</ref></paren> Free
                        among the dead, i.e., as soon as a man dies he is freed from the obligation
                        of <paren>studying</paren> the <ref item="Torah">Torah</ref> and
                            <paren>fulfilling</paren> meritorious deeds, And when <ref
                            character="Solomon">Solomon</ref> says <paren><ref
                                bibverse="Ecclesiastes4:2">Ecc. 4. 2.</ref></paren>
                        <quotation cite="Ecclesiastes4:2">Thereupon praise I the dead that are
                            already dead,</quotation> he refers to the time when Israel sinned in
                        the deserts. <ref character="Moses">Moses</ref> stood up before the <ref
                            god="Holy_One,_praised_be_He">Holy One, praised be He</ref>! and offered
                        many prayers and supplications unto Him but was not answered. However, as
                        soon as he said <paren><ref bibverse="Exodus32:13">Ex 32, 13.</ref></paren>
                        Remember <ref character="Abraham">Abraham</ref>, <ref character="Isaac"
                            >Isaac</ref> and <ref character="Israel">Israel</ref>, Thy servants, he
                        was forthwith answered. Now, did not <ref character="Solomon">Solomon</ref>
                        say properly <quotation cite="Ecclesiastes4:2">Thereupon praise I the dead
                            that are already dead.</quotation></quote></quote> It may be explained
                in another way also. The usage of the world is that if a mortal prince issue a
                decree, it is doubtful whether it will be complied with or not; even if it be
                complied with while the prince lives it may not be complied with when he is dead.
                But <ref character="Moses">Moses</ref>, our teacher, has issued many decrees and
                established many ordinances and they endure forever and ever. Now did not <ref
                    character="Solomon">Solomon</ref> say properly <paren><ref
                        bibverse="Ecclesiastes4:2">Ecc. 4, 2.</ref></paren>
                <quotation cite="Ecclesiastes4:2">Thereupon praise I the dead that are already
                    dead!</quotation> The passage, <quotation cite="Ecclesiastes4:2">Thereupon
                    praise I the dead</quotation>, etc., may also be explained in another way, as
                    <ref rabbi="Juda">R. Juda</ref> said in the name of <ref rabbi="Rab">Rab</ref> ;
                for <ref rabbi="Juda">R. Juda</ref> in the name of <ref rabbi="Rab">Rab</ref> said :
                    <quote speaker="Juda">What is meant by the passage <paren><ref
                            bibverse="psalm86:17">Ps. 86, 17.</ref></paren>
                    <quotation cite="psalm86:17">Display on me a sign for good that those who hate
                        me may see it</quotation>. Thus said <ref character="David">David</ref>
                    before the <ref god="Holy_One,_praised_be_He">Holy One, praised be He</ref>!
                        <speech speaker="David"><ref god="Sovereign_of_the_Universe">Sovereign of
                            the universe</ref>, forgive me this sin <paren>of <ref
                                character="Bath_Sheba">Bath Sheba</ref></paren>.'</speech>
                    <speech speaker="Lord">Thou art forgiven.</speech> answered the <ref god="Lord"
                        >Lord</ref>. <ref character="David">David</ref> then said to the <ref
                        god="Lord">Lord</ref> : <quote speaker="David">Show me a sign while I
                        live.</quote> Whereupon He answered, <quote speaker="Lord">During thy life I
                        shall not make it known but during the life of <ref character="Solomon"
                            >Solomon</ref>, thy son, I shall make it known.</quote>
                    <function allegory="importance_of_faith_in_God">When <ref character="Solomon"
                            >Solomon</ref> had built the Temple he desired to place the <ref
                            item="ark">ark</ref> in the <ref item="holy_of_holies">holy of
                            holies</ref>, but the gates had become fastened to each other <paren>and
                            they could not be opened</paren>. <ref character="Solomon">Solomon</ref>
                        then offered twenty-four prayer-songs but was not answered. He then began
                        the prayer <paren><ref bibverse="psalm24:7">Ps. 24, 7.</ref></paren>
                        <ref bibverse="psalm24"><quotation cite="psalm24:7">Raise your heads, O ye
                                gates and be raised wide, ye everlasting gates, and let the king of
                                glory enter.</quotation> Thereupon the gates ran after him and
                            opened their mouths and wanted to swallow him up, saying: Who is the
                                <ref god="King_of_glory">King of glory</ref>?</ref>
                        <paren><ref bibverse="psalm24:7">Ib.</ref></paren>
                        <ref character="Solomon">Solomon</ref> replied. <ref bibverse="psalm24:7"
                            >The <ref god="Lord">Lord</ref>, strong and mighty</ref>
                        <paren><ref bibverse="psalm24:7">Ib.</ref></paren>. <quotation
                            cite="psalm24:7">He then repeated Raise your heads, O ye gates, and
                            raise up, ye everlasting doors, and let the King of glory
                            enter.</quotation> Who is the <ref god="King_of_glory">King of
                            glory</ref>, the <ref god="Lord_of_Hosts">Lord of Hosts</ref>, He is the
                            <ref god="King_of_glory">King of glory</ref>, <hebrew>Selah</hebrew>
                        <paren>
                            <ref bibverse="psalm24:7">Ib.</ref></paren>. Still he was not answered;
                        but as soon as he said <ref bibverse="psalm24.7"><ref god="Lord_God">O Lord
                                God</ref> turn not away the face of thy anointed, remember the pious
                            deeds of <ref character="David">David</ref> thy servant,</ref>
                        <paren><ref bibverse="2Chronicles6:12">II Chr. 6, 12</ref></paren>, he was
                        immediately answered. <quotation cite="2Chronicles6:12">At that moment the
                            faces of <ref character="David">David's</ref> enemies turned black like
                            the bottom of a pot and then it was known to all that the <ref
                                god="Holy_One,_praised_be_He">Holy One, praised be He</ref>! had
                            forgiven <ref character="David">David</ref> that
                        sin.</quotation></function> Therefore, did not <ref character="Solomon"
                        >Solomon</ref> properly say. <speech speaker="Solomon">Thereupon, praise I
                        the dead, etc.</speech> This is meant by the passage <paren><ref
                            bibverse="IKings8:66">I Kings 8, 66.</ref></paren>
                    <function allegory="faith+divineGlory">On the eighth day he dismissed the
                        people; they blessed the king and went unto their tents, glad of heart,
                        because of all the good that the <ref god="Lord">Lord</ref> had done for
                            <ref character="David">David</ref> his servant and for Israel his
                        people, i.e.. And they went unto their tents, meaning they found their wives
                        levitically pure. Joyful, because of having enjoyed the <ref
                            item="Divine_Glory">Divine Glory</ref>; glad of heart, each man's wife
                        had become pregnant with a male child; because of all the good which <ref
                            god="God">God</ref> had done unto <ref character="David">David</ref> his
                        servant, that he forgave him that sin; and Israel his people, for they were
                        forgiven their neglect of the observance of the <ref
                            holyDay="day_of_Atonement">day of Atonement</ref>.</function> And when
                        <ref character="Solomon">Solomon</ref> said <paren><ref
                            bibverse="Ecclesiastes9:4">Ecc. 9, 4.</ref></paren></quote>
                <litdev metaphor="appreciate_that_you_are_alive"><ref bibverse="Ecclesiastes9:4">For
                        a living dog fareth better than a dead lion</ref></litdev>, he meant that
                which <ref rabbi="Juda">R. Juda</ref> said in the name of <ref rabbi="Rab">Rab</ref>
                ; for <ref rabbi="Juda">R. Juda</ref> in the name of <ref rabbi="Rab">Rab</ref>,
                said: <quote speaker="Juda">"What is meant by the passage <paren><ref
                            bibverse="psalm39:5">Ps. 39, 5.</ref></paren>
                    <ref bibverse="psalm39:5">Let me know, O <ref god="Lord">Lord</ref>, my end, and
                        what the measure of my days is, I wish to know when I shall cease to
                        be,</ref> i.e., thus said <ref character="David">David</ref> before the <ref
                        god="Holy_One,_praised_be_He">Holy One, praised be He</ref>! <quote
                        speaker="David">'<ref god="Sovereign_of_the_Universe">Sovereign of the
                            universe</ref> let me know my end.'</quote> Whereupon the <ref
                        god="Lord">Lord</ref> answered him : <quote speaker="Lord">It has been
                        decreed by me that the time of the death of mortal man shall not be
                        known;</quote>
                    <quote speaker="David">'<ref bibverse="psalm39:5">And the measures of my days
                            what are they</ref>'</quote>
                    <paren><ref bibverse="psalm39:5">Ib.</ref></paren>, <ref character="David"
                        >David</ref> again asked. <quote speaker="Lord">'It is decreed by
                        me'</quote> answered the <ref god="Lord">Lord</ref>,<quote speaker="Lord">'
                        that the measure of the days of a man shall not be known.'</quote> Again
                        <ref character="David">David</ref> asked: <quote speaker="David">'I wish to
                        know when I shall cease to be.'</quote> The <ref god="Lord">Lord</ref> then
                    said to him : <quote speaker="Lord">'Thou wilt die on the <ref holyDay="Sabbath"
                            >Sabbath</ref>.'</quote>
                    <quote speaker="David">'Let me die rather on the first day of the week,'</quote>
                    begged <ref character="David">David</ref>. <quote speaker="Lord">'The first day
                        of the week is the day on which thy son <ref character="Solomon"
                            >Solomon</ref> shall be king, and one kingdom must not encroach on the
                        other even by so much as a hair's breath.'</quote>
                    <quote speaker="David">'Let me then die on the <ref holyDay="Sabbath"
                            >Sabbath</ref> eve,'</quote> pleaded <ref character="David">David</ref>.
                    Whereupon the <ref god="Lord">Lord</ref> said <ref bibverse="psalm84:11">Far
                        better is a day in thy courts than a thousand</ref>
                    <paren><ref bibverse="psalm84:11">Ps. 84, 11</ref></paren>, i.e., <quote
                        speaker="Lord">'I like one day in which thou art studying the <ref
                            item="Torah">Torah</ref> better than a thousand burnt offerings which
                            <ref character="Solomon">Solomon</ref>, thy son, will sacrifice before
                        me upon the altar.'</quote> (Ib. b) Each <ref holyDay="Sabbath"
                        >Sabbath</ref> day he would sit and study. On that <ref holyDay="Sabbath"
                        >Sabbath</ref> when he was to die, the <ref character="angle_of_death">angel
                        of death</ref> came and stood before him, but was unable to do anything
                    because <ref character="David">David</ref> never once ceased studying.
                        <paren>Said the <ref character="angle_of_death">angel</ref> to
                        himself</paren>
                    <speech speaker="angle_of_death">What shall I do?</speech> There was an orchard
                    in the back of <ref character="David">David's</ref> house; the <ref
                        character="angle_of_death">angel of death</ref> went there and shook the
                    trees. <ref character="David">David</ref>
                    <paren>hearing the noise</paren> went out to see <paren>the cause of the
                        noise</paren> ; as he ascended the ladder the <ref
                        character="angle_of_death">angel</ref> caused it to break. <ref
                        character="David">David</ref> fell down and consequently stopped studying;
                    whereupon the <ref character="angle_of_death">angel of death</ref> took his
                    life. It so happened that <ref character="Solomon">Solomon</ref> sent to ask the
                    following questions in the academy: <quote speaker="Solomon">My father died and
                        lies in sun; what shall I do? <paren>Am I allowed to remove him from the
                            sun?</paren> And the dogs of my father's house are hungry, what shall I
                        do?</quote> They answered him: <quote speaker="academy">Cut up a carrion and
                        place the pieces before the dogs. As to thy father, place a loaf of bread or
                        an infant upon his body and then you may carry it away from the sun.</quote>
                    Did not <ref character="Solomon">Solomon</ref>, therefore, say properly? <speech
                        speaker="Solomon">For a living dog fareth better than a dead lion.</speech>
                    And as to the question, which I have been asked in your presence, I say this:
                        <litdev wordplay="lamp-Ner;soul-Ner">a <ref item="lamp">lamp</ref> is called
                            <hebrew>Ner</hebrew> and <ref item="soul">the soul</ref> is called
                            <hebrew>Ner</hebrew></litdev>; it is better that a human light
                            <paren><litdev metaphor="human_light">lamp</litdev></paren> be
                    extinguished than that <ref god="God">God's</ref> light <paren><litdev
                            metaphor="God's_light">life</litdev></paren> be
                extinguished.</quote></p>
        </midrashim>

        <midrashim book="MidrashEinYaakov">
            <source>
                <midtext>Midrash Ein Yaakov </midtext>
                <edition>Glick Edition</edition>
                <midpass>Menachot 4:3</midpass>
            </source>
            <p><ref rabbi="Eliezer_b._Jacob">R. Eliezer b. Jacob</ref> says: <quote
                    speaker="Eliezer_b._Jacob">Whoever wears <ref item="Phylacteries"
                        >Phylacteries</ref> upon his head, <ref item="Phylacteries"
                        >Phylacteries</ref> upon his hand, fringes on his cloak and has a <ref
                        item="Mezuzh">Mezuzah</ref> on his door-post, these all will preserve him
                    from sin, as it is said <paren><ref bibverse="Ecclesiastes4:12">Ecc. 4,
                        12</ref></paren>
                    <ref bibverse="Ecclesiastes4:12">And a <ref item="threefold_cord">threefold
                            cord</ref> is not quickly broken</ref>, and again there is another verse
                            <paren><ref bibverse="psalm24:8">Ps. 24, 8</ref></paren>
                    <ref bibverse="psalm24:8">The angel of the <ref god="Lord">Lord</ref> encampeth
                        round about them that fear the <ref god="Lord">Lord</ref></ref>.</quote></p>
        </midrashim>

        <midrashim book="MidrashEinYaakov">
            <source>
                <midtext>Midrash Ein Yaakov </midtext>
                <edition>Glick Edition</edition>
                <midpass>Sanhedrin 11:105</midpass>
            </source>
            <p><ref rabbi="Dusthai">R. Dusthai</ref>, of the city of Biri, lectured: <quote
                    speaker="Dusthai">Unto what may be likened the system of <ref character="David"
                        >David's</ref> praver?</quote>
                <quote speaker="Dusthai">Unto a peddler who wanted to sell out his stock little by
                    little. He said before the <ref god="Holy_One,_praised_be_He">Holy One, praised
                        be He</ref>! <paren><ref bibverse="psalm19:13 psalm19:14 psalm19:15">Ps.
                            19,13-15</ref></paren>
                    <ref bibverse="psalm19:13">"Sovereign of the Universe, who can guard against
                        errors?"</ref> And he was answered, <speech speaker="God">They will be
                        forgiven.</speech>
                    <paren>
                        <ref bibverse="psalm19:13 psalm19:14 psalm19:15">Ib.</ref></paren>
                    <ref bibverse="psalm19.13">"From secrets <paren>faults</paren> do Thou cleanse
                        me."</ref>
                    <speech speaker="God">They will be forgiven.</speech>
                    <paren><ref bibverse="psalm19:13 psalm19:14 psalm19:15">Ib.</ref></paren>
                    <quotation cite="psalm19:13">Also from presumptuous sins withhold Thy
                        servants.</quotation>
                    <speech speaker="god">This will <paren>also</paren> be forgiven.</speech>
                    <paren><ref bibverse="psalm19:13 psalm19:14 psalm19:15">Ib.</ref></paren>
                    <quotation cite="psalm19:13">Let them not have dominion over me,</quotation>
                    i.e., the <ref character="Rabbis">Rabbis</ref> shall not talk about me. <quote
                        speaker="God">This will <paren>also</paren> be allowed to you.</quote>
                    <paren><ref bibverse="psalm19:13 psalm19:14 psalm19:15">Ib.</ref></paren>
                    <quotation cite="psalm19:13 psalm19:14 psalm19:15">'Then shall I be
                        blameless,'</quotation> i.e., my sins shall not be written. And he was
                    answered, <quote speaker="God">'This is impossible, for, if the <ref item="Yud"
                            >Yud</ref> which I took away from the name of <ref
                            character="sarah sarai">Sarai</ref> complained before me several years,
                        until <ref character="Joshua">Joshua</ref> came and I added it to his name,
                        as it is said <paren><ref bibverse="Numbers13:16">Num. 13, 16</ref></paren>
                        <ref bibverse="Numbers13:16">And <ref character="Moses">Moses</ref> called
                                <ref character="Hoshea">Hoshea</ref>; the son of <ref
                                character="Nun">Nun</ref>, <ref character="Joshua"
                            >Joshua</ref></ref>, how much more <paren>will there be
                            complaints</paren> if I omit a whole portion of the <ref item="Torah"
                            >Torah</ref>?'</quote>
                    <paren><ref bibverse="psalm19">Ps. 19</ref></paren>
                    <ref bibverse="psalm19">Clear from any great transgression</ref>, i.e., He said
                    before him : <ref bibverse="psalm19"><quote><ref god="Sovereign_of_the_Universe"
                                >Sovereign of the Universe</ref>, forgive me the whole
                        sin.</quote></ref> And he was answered, <quote speaker="God">It is revealed
                        before Me what <ref character="Solomon">Solomon</ref>, thy son, will say in
                        his wisdom in the future <paren><ref
                                bibverse="proverbs6:27 proverbs6:28 proverbs6:29 proverbs6:30">Pr.
                                6, 27-30</ref></paren>
                        <quotation cite="proverbs6:27 proverbs6:28 proverbs6:29">Can a man take fire
                            in his bosom, and his clothes not be burnt? Or can one walk upon hot
                            coals, and shall his feet not be scorched? So he that goeth in to his
                            neighbor's wife; whosoever touches her shall not go
                            unpunished</quotation>.</quote> He then exclaimed, <quote
                        speaker="David">If so, then I am lost.</quote> And he was answered : <quote
                        speaker="God">Accept affliction upon thyself.</quote> Immediately <ref
                        character="David">David</ref> accepted affliction upon himself.</quote>
                <ref rabbi="Juda">R. Juda</ref> said in the name of <ref rabbi="Rab">Rab</ref>:
                    <quote speaker="Juda">Six months was <ref character="David">David</ref>
                    afflicted with leprosy; the <ref item="Shechina">Shechina</ref> left him, and
                    the <ref item="Sanhedrin">Sanhedrin</ref> separated themselves from him. He was
                    inflicted with leprosy, as it is written <paren><ref bibverse="psalm51:9">Ps.
                            51, 9</ref></paren>
                    <ref bibverse="psalm51:9">Purge me <paren>from sin</paren> with hyssop,
                        etc</ref>. The Shechina left him, as it is written <paren><ref
                            bibverse="proverbs6:14">Ib., ib., 14</ref></paren>
                    <quotation cite="psalm51:12">Restore unto me the gladness of Thy
                        salvation</quotation>. The Sanhedrin separated themselves from him, as it is
                    written <paren><ref bibverse="proverbs119:79">Ib. 119, 79</ref></paren>
                    <quotation cite="Proversb119:79">Let those that fear Thee return unto me and
                        they that know Thy testimonies</quotation>. That all this lasted fully six
                    months — when do we learn it ? From the following passage <paren><ref
                            bibverse="IKings2:11">I Kings, 2, 11</ref></paren>
                    <quotation cite="IKings2:11">And the days that David reigned over Israel were
                        forty years; (Ib. b) In Hebron he reigned thirty-three years over all Israel
                        and Judah.</quotation> Hence we see that the six months more <paren>which
                        are counted in <ref bibverse="IISamuel">II Samuel</ref></paren> are not
                    counted <paren>in <ref bibverse="IKings">I Kings</ref></paren>, and this was
                    because the six months in which he was inflicted with leprosy were not
                    counted.</quote>
                <paren><ref bibverse="psalm86:17">Ps. 86, 17</ref></paren><quotation
                    cite="psalm86:17"> Display on me a sign for good, etc.</quotation> Thus said
                    <ref character="David">David</ref> before the <ref god="Holy_One">Holy
                    One</ref>,<speech speaker="David">praised be He</speech>! <quote speaker="David"
                        ><ref god="Sovereign_of_the_Universe">Sovereign of the universe</ref>,
                    forgive me this sin <paren>of <ref character="Bath_Sheba">Bath
                        Sheba</ref></paren>.</quote>
                <quote speaker="Lord">Thou art forgiven,</quote> answered the <ref god="Lord"
                    >Lord</ref>. <ref character="David">David</ref> then said to the <ref god="Lord"
                    >Lord</ref> : <quote speaker="David">Show me a sign while I live.</quote>
                Whereupon He answered, <quote speaker="Lord">During thy life I shall not make it
                    known but during the life of <ref character="Solomon">Solomon</ref>, thy son, I
                    shall make it known.</quote> When <ref character="Solomon">Solomon</ref> had
                built the Temple he desired to place the ark in the holy of holies, but the gates
                had become fastened to each other <paren>and they could not be opened</paren>. <ref
                    character="Solomon">Solomon</ref> then offered twenty-four prayer-songs but was
                not answered. He then said the prayer <paren><ref bibverse="psalm24:9">Ps. 24,
                        9</ref></paren>
                <quotation cite="psalm24:9 psalm24:10">Raise your heads, O ye gates, and raise up,
                    ye everlasting doors, and let the King of glory enter. Who is the King of glory,
                    the Lord of Hosts, He is the King of glory, <hebrew>Selah</hebrew></quotation>
                <paren><ref bibverse="2Chronicles6:12">II Chr. 6, l2</ref></paren>. <ref
                    bibverse="2Chronicles6.12">Still he was not answered; but as soon as he said O
                        <ref god="Lord_God">Lord God</ref>, turn not away the face of Thy anointed,
                    remember the pious deeds of <ref character="David">David</ref> Thy servant, he
                    was immediately answered.</ref> At that moment the faces of <ref
                    character="David">David's</ref> enemies turned black like the bottom of a pot
                and then it was known to all that the <ref god="Holy_One,_praised_be_He">Holy One,
                    praised be He</ref>! had forgiven <ref character="David">David</ref> that
                sin.</p>
        </midrashim>

        <midrashim book="MidrashTanchuma">
            <source>
                <midtext>Midrash Tanchuma</midtext>
                <midpass>Masei 10:1</midpass>
            </source>
            <p><paren><ref bibverse="Numbers34:2">Numb. 34:2</ref></paren>, <quotation
                    cite="Numbers34:2">This is the land that shall fall to you as an
                    inheritance.</quotation> What is the meaning of <quotation cite="Numbers34:2">to
                    you?</quotation>
                <ref bibverse="Numbers23:11">To you it is fitting.</ref>
                <paren>The matter</paren> is comparable to a king who had male and female slaves and
                would have his male slaves marry female slaves from another estate and his female
                slaves <paren>marry</paren> male salves from a different estate.30 The <ref
                    character="king">king</ref> stopped and reflected. He said, <speech
                    speaker="king">The male slaves are mine and the female slaves are mine. It would
                    be better for me to marry my <translation heb="'avadim">male
                        slaves</translation>
                    <paren><hebrew>'avadim</hebrew></paren> to my female slaves, my own to my
                    own.</speech> Similarly the <ref god="Holy_One,_blessed_be_He">Holy One, blessed
                    be He</ref>, said, <quote speaker="God">The land is Mine, as stated in
                            <paren><ref bibverse="psalm24:1">Ps. 24:1</ref></paren>, <quotation
                        cite="psalm24:1">The land is the <ref god="Lord">Lord's</ref> and all that
                        is in it.</quotation> Moreover Israel is Mine, as stated <paren>in <ref
                            bibverse="Leviticus25:55">Lev. 25:55</ref></paren>, <quotation
                        cite="Leviticus25:55">For to Me the Children of Israel are <translation
                            heb="'avadim">servants</translation>
                        <paren><hebrew>'avadim</hebrew></paren>.</quotation>
                    <paren>It is</paren> better for Me to bequeath My land to my servants who belong
                    to Me, My own to My own.</quote> It is therefore stated <paren>in <ref
                        bibverse="Numbers34:2">Numb. 34:2</ref></paren>,<quotation
                    cite="Numbers34:2"> this is the land that shall fall to you.</quotation> Another
                interpretation <paren>of <ref bibverse="Numbers34:2">Numb. 34:2</ref></paren>,
                    <quotation cite="Numbers34:2">“this is the land”</quotation>: This text is
                related <paren>to <ref bibverse="psalm111:6">Ps. 111:6</ref></paren>, <quotation
                    cite="psalm111:6">“He revealed to His people His powerful works.”</quotation>
                The <ref god="Holy_One,_blessed_be_He">Holy One, blessed be He</ref>, said to
                Israel, <speech speaker="God">I could have created a different desirable land for
                    you. But in order to show you My strength, I am expelling your enemies in front
                    of you and giving you their land, to fulfill that which is stated, <quotation
                        cite="psalm111:6">He revealed His powerful
                works....</quotation></speech></p>
        </midrashim>
        <midrashim book="MidrashTanchuma">
            <source>
                <midtext>Midrash Tanchuma </midtext>
                <midpass>Beshalach 11:2</midpass>
            </source>
            <p>A mortal king is praised as mighty, though he may be weak, and as rich, merciful, and
                handsome, because they wish to flatter him. But concerning the <ref
                    god="Holy_One,_blessed_be_He">Holy One, blessed be He</ref>, they say: <ref
                    bibverse="deuteronomy10:17">The <ref god="great_God">great God</ref>, the <ref
                        god="mighty_God"> mighty God</ref>, and the awful</ref>
                <paren><ref bibverse="deuteronomy10:17">Deut. 10:17</ref></paren>; <quotation
                    cite="Isaiah42:13">The Lord will go forth as a mighty man</quotation>
                <paren><ref bibverse="Isaiah42:13">Isa. 42:13</ref></paren>; <quotation
                    cite="psalm86:8">There is none like unto thee, O Lord</quotation>
                <paren><ref bibverse="Jeremiah10.6">Jer. 10:6</ref></paren>. They say He is rich,
                and indeed there are no limits to his wealth, <quotation cite="deuteronomy10:14">For
                    behold, unto the Lord thy God belongeth the heaven, and the heaven of
                    heavens</quotation>
                <paren><ref bibverse="deuteronomy10:14">Deut. 10:14</ref></paren>. And it is written
                also: <quotation cite="psalm95:5">The sea is His, and He made it, and His hands
                    formed the dry land</quotation>
                <paren><ref bibverse="psalm95:5">Ps. 95:5</ref></paren>; <quotation cite="psalm24:1"
                    >The earth is the Lord’s, and the fullness thereof</quotation>
                <paren><ref bibverse="psalm24:1">ibid. 24:1</ref></paren>; <quotation
                    cite="Haggai2:8">Mine is the silver, and Mine is the gold</quotation>
                <paren><ref bibverse="Haggai2:8">Hag. 2:8</ref></paren>; <quotation
                    cite="Ezekiel18:4">Behold, all souls are Mine; as the soul of the father, so
                    also the soul of the son</quotation>
                <paren><ref bibverse="Ezekiel18:4">Ezek. 18:4</ref></paren>.</p>
        </midrashim>
        <midrashim book="MidrashTanchuma">
            <source>
                <midtext>Midrash Tanchuma </midtext>
                <midpass>Ki Tisa 14:3</midpass>
            </source>
            <p><ref rabbi="Nehemiah">R. Nehemiah</ref> declared: <quote speaker="Nehemiah">When we
                    examine our actions, we are filled with shame. Usually when a man gives his
                    field to a tenant to work, the tenant supplies the seed and the labor, and they
                    share equally in the produce. But the <ref god="Holy_One,_blessed_be_He">Holy
                        One, blessed be He</ref>, of whom it is written: <quotation cite="psalm24:1"
                        >The Earth is the Lord’s and the fullness thereof</quotation>
                    <paren><ref bibverse="psalm24:1">Ps. 24:1</ref></paren>, causes the rain and the
                    dew to descend and protects everything, yet He desires only one tenth as tithe
                    and one fiftieth as the priestly offering. Hence, <quotation cite="Daniel9:7"
                        >Unto Thee, O Lord, belongeth righteousness, but unto us confusion of
                        face</quotation>
                    <paren><ref bibverse="Daniel9:7">Dan. 9:7</ref></paren>.</quote>
                <ref rabbi="Yosé">R. Yosé</ref> said: <quote speaker="Yosé">Was there a more
                    shameful act than this? Israel crossed the Red Sea, and the idol <ref
                        character="Micah">Micah</ref>
                    <paren>had made</paren> was carried with them when, as it is said: <ref
                        bibverse="Zechariah10:11">And over the tree affliction shall pass</ref>
                    <paren><ref bibverse="Zechariah10:11">Zech. 10:11</ref></paren>. Nevertheless
                    the sea split asunder for them. Therefore, <quotation cite="Daniel9:7">Unto
                        Thee, O Lord, belongeth righteousness, but unto us confusion of
                        face.</quotation></quote></p>
        </midrashim>
    </section>

</midrash>
