<midrash>
    
    <verse>  
        <versenum>Genesis 22:1</versenum>
        <versetext>Some time afterward, God put Abraham to the test. He said to him, “Abraham,” and he answered, “Here I am.”</versetext>
    </verse>
    <midrashim>
        <source>
            <midtext>Midrash Tanchuma</midtext> 
            <midpass>Vayera 19:1</midpass>
        </source>
        <p><quotation cite="genesis22:1">And it came to pass after these words that God did prove Abraham</quotation> <paren><ref bibverse="genesis22:1">Gen. 22:1</ref></paren>. Scripture states elsewhere in reference to this verse: <quotation cite="ecclesiastes8:4-5">Forasmuch as the king’s word hath power; and who may say 
            unto him: “What dost thou?” whoso keepeth the commandment shall know no evil thing</quotation> <paren><ref bibverse="ecclesiastes8:4-5">Eccles. 8:4–5</ref></paren>. What is meant by this verse? Whatsoever the <ref god="Holy_One">Holy One</ref>, blessed be He, desires to do, He may 
            do, and none may stay His hand. What then can be the meaning of <quotation cite="ecclesiastes8:4-5">And who may say unto Him: “What doest Thou?” whoso keepeth the commandment, etc.</quotation>? These words whoso keepeth the commandment 
            allude to the righteous men who perform the commandments of the <ref god="Holy_One">Holy One</ref>, blessed be He. And it is their decree that He fulfills, as it is written: Thou shalt also decree a thing and it shall 
            be established unto thee, and the light shall shine upon thy ways <paren><ref bibverse="job22:28">Job 22:28</ref></paren>. An example of this is what occurred after they made the golden calf. Though the <ref god="Holy_One">Holy One</ref>, blessed be He, desired 
            to destroy them, our master, <ref character="moses">Moses</ref>, restrained the <ref god="Holy_One">Holy One</ref>, blessed be He, as though that were possible, just as a man restrains his companion. Hence the <ref god="Holy_One">Holy One</ref>, blessed be He, said to 
            him: <quotation cite="exodus32:10">And now let Me be</quotation> <paren><ref bibverse="exodus32:10">Exod. 32:10</ref></paren>. We learn this as well from the verse: <quotation cite="deuteronomy9:14">Let Me alone that I may destroy them</quotation> <paren><ref bibverse="deuteronomy9:14">Deut. 9:14</ref></paren>. Therefore Scripture says: <quotation cite="ecclesiastes8:4-5">Who may say unto him: “What doest 
                thou?” whoso keepeth the commandment.</quotation></p>
    </midrashim>
    
    <verse>  
        <versenum>Genesis 22:2</versenum>
        <versetext>And He said, “Take your son, your favored one, Isaac, whom you love, and go to the land of Moriah, and offer him there as a burnt offering on one of the heights that I will 
            point out to you.”</versetext>
    </verse>
    <midrashim>
        <source>
            <midtext>Bereishit Rabbah</midtext>
            <midpass>55:7</midpass>
        </source>
        <p><quotation cite="genesis22:2">And He said: Take, please, your son, etc.</quotation> <paren><ref bibverse="genesis22:2">22:2</ref></paren>. Said <ref character="god">God</ref> to him: <speech speaker="god">Take, I beg you" — please —Your son.</speech> <speech speaker="abraham">Which son? I have two sons</speech> he said. <speech speaker="god">Your only son,</speech> replied He. 
            <speech speaker="abraham">This one is the only one of his mother, and this one is the only one of his mother.</speech> <speech speaker="god">The one you love</speech>—<speech speaker="abraham">Is there a limit to the affections?</speech> <speech speaker="god"><ref character="Itzchak">Itzchak</ref></speech> said He. And why did <ref character="god">God</ref> 
            not reveal it to him without delay? In order to make him [<ref character="itzchak">Itzchak</ref>] even more beloved in his eyes and reward him for each and every word spoken. This agrees with the opinion of 
            <ref rabbi="Yohanan">Rabbi Yohanan</ref>, who said: <quote speaker="Rabbi_Yohanan"><quotation cite="genesis12:1">Get out of your country</quotation> <paren><ref bibverse="genesis12:1">Gen. 12:1</ref></paren> means from your province; <quotation cite="genesis12:1">And from your kindred</quotation> <paren><ref bibverse="genesis12:1">Gen. 12:1</ref></paren>—from your neighborhood; <quotation cite="genesis12:1">And from your father’s 
                house</quotation><paren>(<ref bibverse="genesis12:1">Gen. 12:1</ref>)</paren>—literally your father’s house.</quote> <quotation cite="genesis12:1">To the land that I will show you</quotation> <paren><ref bibverse="genesis12:1">Gen. 12:1</ref></paren>. Why did He not reveal it to him there and then? In order to make it more beloved 
            in his eyes and to reward him for each and every word said, and for each and every step taken. <ref rabbi="Levi b. Hayata">Rabbi Levi b. Hayata</ref> said: <quote speaker="Rabbi_Levi_b._Hayata">‘Get you’ is written twice, and we do not know which was 
                more precious [in the eyes of <ref character="god">God</ref>] the first or the second. But when it is written, <quotation cite="genesis22:2">And get you to the land of Moriah</quotation> <paren><ref bibverse="genesis22:2">22:2</ref></paren> it follows that the second occasion was more 
                precious than the first.</quote> <quotation cite="genesis22:2">And go yourself to the land of Moriah</quotation> <ref rabbi="Chiya Raba">Rabbi Chiya Raba</ref> and <ref rabbi="Yanai">Rabbi Yanai</ref> [disagree]: one says <quote speaker="Rabbi_Chiya_Raba_or_Rabbi_Yanai">to the place from which <translation heb="hora'ah">instruction</translation> <paren><hebrew>hora’ah</hebrew></paren> goes out to 
                    the world</quote>, and the other says <quote speaker="Rabbi_Chiya_Raba_or_Rabbi_Yanai">to the place from which <translation heb="yirah">awe</translation> <paren><hebrew>yirah</hebrew></paren> goes out to the world</quote>. Similarly regarding the <translation heb="devir">Holy of Holies</translation> <paren><hebrew>devir</hebrew></paren>, <ref rabbi="Chiya">Rabbi Chiya</ref> and <ref rabbi="Yanai">Rabbi Yanai</ref> [disagree]: 
            one says <quote speaker="Rabbi_Chiya_Raba_or_Rabbi_Yanai">from the place from which the <translation heb="dibra'ot">commandments</translation> <paren><hebrew>dibra’ot</hebrew></paren> go out to the world</quote>, and one says <quote speaker="Rabbi_Chiya_Raba_or_Rabbi_Yanai">from the place from which <translation heb="dibur">speech</translation> <paren><hebrew>dibur</hebrew></paren> goes out to the world</quote>. Similarly 
            regarding the <translation heb="aron">ark</translation> <paren><hebrew>aron</hebrew></paren>, <ref rabbi="Chiya">Rabbi Chiya</ref> and <ref rabbi="Yanai">Rabbi Yanai</ref> [disagree]: one says <quote speaker="Rabbi_Chiya_Raba_or_Rabbi_Yanai">to the place from which the <translation heb="ha'orah">light</translation> <paren><hebrew>ha’orah</hebrew></paren> goes out to the world</quote>, and one says <quote speaker="Rabbi_Chiya_Raba_or_Rabbi_Yanai">to the place where awe 
                <paren><hebrew>yirah</hebrew></paren> goes out to the world</quote>. <ref rabbi="Yehoshua ben Levi">Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi</ref> said that <quote speaker="Rabbi_Yehoshua_ben_Levi">from there the <ref character="holy one">Holy One</ref> <translation heb="mor'eh">instructs</translation> [<hebrew>mor'eh</hebrew>] the nations of the world and <translation heb="moridam">brings them down</translation> [<hebrew>moridam</hebrew>] to Gehinnom.</quote> 
            <ref rabbi="Shimon bar Yochai">Rabbi Shimon bar Yochai</ref> said, to the place which is <translation heb="ra'ui">aligned [ra'ui]</translation> with the Holy Temple above. <ref rabbi="Yudan">Rabbi Yudan</ref> said, to the place where there will be an appearance [mar'eh] to you. 
            <ref rabbi="Pinchas">Rabbi Pinchas</ref> said, to the place of the <ref character="master of the world"><translation heb="marvatah">Master</translation> [<hebrew>marvatah</hebrew>] of the World</ref>. <ref rabbi="Rabbis">The Rabbis</ref> said, <quote speaker="Rabbis">to the place where the incense is offered – this is what it says “…I will go to the 
                mountain of myrrh and to the hill of frankincense.” <paren><ref item="shirHashirim4:6">Shir HaShirim 4:6</ref></paren> <quotation cite="genesis22:2">And offer Him there as a burnt-offering</quotation> <paren><ref bibverse="genesis22:2">Gen. 22:2</ref></paren>.</quote> <ref rabbi="Yudan bar Simon">Rabbi Yudan bar Simon</ref> said: <quote speaker="Rabbi_Yudan_bar_Simon">He [<ref character="abraham">Avraham</ref>] said to 
                    Him: ‘<ref character="master of the universe">Master of the Universe</ref>! Can there be a sacrifice without a priest?’ The <ref character="holy one of blessing">Holy One of Blessing</ref> replied ‘I have already appointed you to be a priest’ as it is written, <quotation cite="psalm110:4">You 
                        are a priest for ever</quotation> <paren><ref bibverse="psalm110:4">Ps. 110:4</ref></paren>. <quotation cite="genesis22:2">On one of the mountains which I will tell you of</quotation> <paren><ref bibverse="genesis22:2">Gen. 22:2</ref></paren>.</quote> <ref rabbi="Huna">Rabbi Huna</ref> said in the name of <ref rabbi="Eliezer">Rabbi Eliezer</ref> the son of <ref rabbi="Yosei HaGelili">Rabbi Yosei HaGelili</ref>: 
            <quote speaker="Rabbi_Huna">The <ref character="holy one of blessing">Holy One of Blessing</ref> first places the righteous in doubt and suspense, and then reveals to them the real meaning of the matter, as it is written "to the land that I will show 
                you <paren><ref bibverse="genesis12:1">Gen. 12:1</ref></paren>; <quotation cite="genesis12:1">On one of the mountains which I will tell you</quotation>; <quotation cite="jonah3:2">And make to it the proclamation that I bid you</quotation> <paren><ref bibverse="jonah3:2">Jonah 3:2</ref></paren>; similarly, <quotation bibverse="ezekiel3:22">Arise, go out into the plain and I will 
                    there speak with you</quotation> <paren><ref bibverse="ezekiel3:22">Ezek. 3:22</ref></paren>.</quote></p>
    </midrashim>
    
    <verse>  
        <versenum>Genesis 22:2</versenum>
        <versetext>And He said, “Take your son, your favored one, Isaac, whom you love, and go to the land of Moriah, and offer him there as a burnt offering on one of the heights that I will 
            point out to you.”</versetext>
        <versenum>Genesis 22:4</versenum>
        <versetext>On the third day Abraham looked up and saw the place from afar.</versetext>
    </verse>
    <midrashim>
        <source>
            <midtext>Midrash Tanchuma</midtext>
            <midpass>Shmini, Siman 2:1</midpass>
        </source>
        <p><paren><ref bibverse="leviticus9:1">Lev. 9:1</ref></paren> <quotation cite="leviticus9:1">And it came to pass on the eighth day….</quotation> This text is related <paren>to <ref bibverse="psalm75:5">Ps. 75:5</ref></paren>, <quotation cite="psalm75:5">“I say to the merrymakers, ‘Do not make merry….’”</quotation> What is the meaning of [the words], 
            <quotation cite="psalm75:5">I say to the merrymakers <paren>rt.: hll</paren>, ‘do not make merry <paren>rt.: hll</paren>?’</quotation>4 [The verse refers] to whoever sings in a mahanaim <translation heb="mahol">dance</translation> <paren><hebrew>mahol</hebrew></paren>,5 and so it says <paren>in <ref bibverse="judges21:21">Jud. 21:21</ref></paren>, <quotation cite="judges21:21">to 
                <translation heb="lehol">dance</translation> <paren><hebrew>lehol</hebrew></paren> in the dances.</quotation> [Because no happiness endures for a mortal] <paren><ref bibverse="psalm75:5">Ps. 75:5</ref></paren>, “I say to the merrymakers, ‘Do not make merry <paren>rt.: hll</paren>.’” Why? The one who is happy 
            today shall not be happy tomorrow; and the one who is depressed today shall not be depressed tomorrow. And so it says <paren>in <ref bibverse="ecclesiastes2:2">Eccl. 2:2</ref></paren>, <quotation cite="ecclesiastes2:2">Of laughter I said, ‘It is mad 
                <paren>rt.: hll</paren>….’</quotation>6 Are you willing to understand? As behold, even the happiness of the <ref god="Holy_One">Holy One</ref>, blessed be He, did not endure. When? When the <ref god="Holy_One">Holy One</ref>, blessed be He, created 
            His world. He was very happy, as stated <paren>in <ref bibverse="">Ps. 104:31</ref></paren>, <quotation cite="psalm104:31">the Lord shall be happy in His works.</quotation> It also says <paren>in <ref bibverse="">Gen. 1:31</ref></paren>, <quotation cite="genesis1:31">Then God saw everything which He had made; and 
                behold, it was very good.</quotation> [These verses are] to teach you that the <ref god="Holy_One">Holy One</ref>, blessed be He, found pleasure in and took pride in His works. Then He gave the first <ref character="adam">Adam</ref> an easy 
            commandment, but he did not fulfill it. Immediately He rendered him a verdict7 [of death], as stated <paren>in <ref bibverse="genesis3:19">Gen. 3:19</ref></paren>, <quotation cite="genesis3:19">for dust you are, and unto dust you shall return.</quotation> So He, 
            as it were, did not remain in His happiness but said, “I created everything only for the human, and now he dies. What pleasure is there for Me? [Now surely if the <ref god="Holy_One">Holy One</ref>, 
            blessed be He,] did not remain [happy], how much the less shall people [remain happy! It is therefore stated <paren>in <ref bibverse="psalm75:5">Ps. 75:5</ref></paren>, <quotation cite="psalm75:5">I say to the merrymakers, ‘do not make merry.’</quotation>] 
            How happy <ref character="abraham">Abraham</ref> was! He was blessed in the world, magnified, slew some kings and handed over heaven and earth to the <ref god="Holy_One">Holy One</ref>, blessed be He. Also when the <ref god="Holy_One">Holy One</ref>, blessed 
            be He, gave him a son at age one hundred, he circumcised him and reared him. Then finally he was told <paren>in <ref bibverse="genesis22:2">Gen. 22:2</ref></paren>, <quotation cite="genesis22:2">Please take your son, your only son…, [and go unto the 
                land of Moriah,] and offer him there as a burnt offering.</quotation> So he made a three-day journey, as stated <paren>in <ref bibverse="genesis22:4">Gen. 22:4</ref></paren>, <quotation cite="genesis22:4">On the third day….</quotation> When he returned from Mount Moriah, 
            he buried <ref character="sarah">Sarah</ref>. He did not find a place to bury her until he bought one for four hundred silver shekels. Then after that, old age came upon him. Now surely if such was the 
            case with Abraham the righteous, how much the more is it the case with the wicked! <ref character="isaac">Isaac</ref> did not remain in his happiness: He escaped from the sword and from the men of Gerar. 
            And [<ref god="God">God</ref>] informed them about who he was, so that they came to him. Thus it is stated <paren>in <ref bibverse="genesis26:26,28">Gen. 26:26, 28</ref></paren>, <quotation cite="genesis26:26,28">Then Abimelech came unto him from Gerar […. And they said, ‘We 
                have clearly seen that the Lord is with you.’]</quotation> But he did not remain in his happiness. Rather <paren>according to <ref bibverse="genesis27:1">Gen. 27:1</ref></paren>, <quotation cite="genesis27:1">“Now it came to pass, that when Isaac was old and his 
                    eyes were too weak to see.”</quotation> So just as [this loss of happiness] happened in the case of <ref character="isaac">Isaac</ref> the burnt offering of the <ref god="Holy_One">Holy One</ref>, blessed be He, <paren>according to <ref bibverse="genesis22:2">Gen. 22:2</ref></paren>, how 
            much the more does it happen in the case of the wicked! Jacob was the first-born of the <ref god="Holy_One">Holy One</ref>, blessed be He, as stated <paren>in <ref bibverse="exodus4:22">Exod. 4:22</ref></paren>, <quotation cite="exodus4:22">Israel is My first-born son.</quotation> How 
            happy he was! He saw a ladder, and <paren>according to <ref bibverse="genesis28:12-13">Gen. 28:12-13</ref></paren> <quotation cite="genesis28:12-13">the angels of god were ascending and descending [….] And behold, the Lord stood upon it and said, I am the 
                Lord….</quotation> Then he went to <ref character="laban">Laban</ref>, fled from <ref character="esau">Esau</ref>, became <ref character="laban">Laban</ref>'s servant for twenty years and in the end became wealthy, sired children and returned in peace. He also met <ref character="esau">Esau</ref> 
            and was saved from him, and paid his vow. But in the end he did not remain in his happiness. Instead <paren>according to <ref bibverse="genesis34:1">Gen. 34:1</ref></paren>, <quotation cite="genesis34:1">Now Dinah [the daughter whom Leah had borne to 
                Jacob] went out…,</quotation> and was raped]. There also came upon him the trouble over <ref character="joseph">Joseph</ref>. Now surely if <ref character="jacob">Jacob</ref> the righteous – one to whom the <ref god="Holy_One">Holy One</ref>, blessed be He, had said, <quotation cite="isaiah49:3">In 
                    whom I will be glorified,</quotation> as stated <paren>in <ref bibverse="isaiah49:3">Is. 49:3</ref></paren>, <quotation cite="isaiah49:3">Israel, in whom I will be glorified</quotation> – did not remain in his happiness, how much the less will the wicked [so remain! It is 
            therefore stated <paren>in <ref bibverse="psalm75:5">Ps. 75:5</ref></paren>, <quotation cite="psalm75:5">I say to the merrymakers, ‘Do not make merry.’</quotation>] How happy <ref character="joshua">Joshua</ref> was! He slew thirty-one kings, gave Israel the land to possess, and 
            distributed it. In addition all Israel gave him a [helping] hand and said <paren>in <ref bibverse="joshua1:18">Josh. 1:18</ref></paren>, <quotation cite="joshua1:18">Anyone who disobeys your command… [shall be put to death.</quotation> Such an honor was] 
            something of which [even] <ref character="moses">Moses</ref> our master did not merit. Still he <paren>i.e., <ref character="joshua">Joshua</ref></paren> did not remain in his happiness, but rather died childless. It is therefore stated <paren>in <ref bibverse="psalm75:5">Ps. 
                75:5</ref></paren>, <quotation cite="psalm75:5">I say to the merrymakers, ‘Do not make merry.’</quotation> How happy <ref character="eli">Eli</ref> was, when he was king, chief justice, and high priest! It is so stated <paren>in <ref bibverse="ISamuel1:9">I Sam. 1:9</ref></paren>, <quotation cite="ISamuel1:9">now Eli [the 
                    priest] was sitting on the throne by the doorpost of the Temple of the Lord.</quotation> <quotation cite="ISamuel1:9">Now Eli the priest was sitting on the throne,</quotation> because he was king. [He was] <quotation cite="ISamuel1:9">by the doorpost of 
                        the Temple of the Lord,</quotation> because he was chief justice. Still he did not remain in his happiness. Instead <paren>according to <ref bibverse="ISamuel4:18">I Sam. 4:18</ref></paren>, <quotation cite="ISamuel4:18">And it came to pass that when he <paren>i.e., a 
                            messenger</paren> mentioned the ark of God, he <paren>i.e., Eli</paren> fell backward from off the throne….</quotation> Moreover, his two sons, <ref character="hophni">Hophni</ref> and <ref character="phinehas">Phinehas</ref> died. So just as this [shift in fortune] 
            happened with <ref character="eli">Eli</ref> the righteous, how much the more [does it happen with] the wicked! You find neither man nor woman who saw joys like <ref character="elisheba bat amminadab">Elisheba bat Amminadab</ref>, [the wife of 
            <ref character="aaron">Aaron</ref>, as stated <paren>in <ref bibverse="exodus6:23">Exod. 6:23</ref></paren>, <quotation cite="exodus6:23">And Aaron took for a wife Elisheba bat Amminadab</quotation>].8 She saw her husband become high priest serving in the high priesthood and [as a] 
            prophet. In addition, <ref character="moses">Moses</ref>, her husband's brother, was king and prophet. Moreover, her sons were deputies [to the high priest] in the priesthood, and her brother Nahshon 
            was head of all of the princes of Israel.9 Still she did not remain in her happiness. Rather, when two of her sons went in to offer a sacrifice, <paren>according to <ref bibverse="leviticus10:2">Lev. 10:2</ref>,</paren> 
            <quotation cite="leviticus10:2">Fire came forth from before the Lord and consumed them, so that they died before the Lord.</quotation> It is therefore stated <paren>in <ref bibverse="psalm75:5">Ps. 75:5</ref></paren>, <quotation cite="psalm75:5">I say to the merrymakers, ‘Do not make 
                merry.’</quotation> And so <ref character="solomon">Solomon</ref> said <paren>in <ref bibverse="ecclesiastes2:2">Eccl. 2:2</ref></paren>, <quotation cite="ecclesiastes2:2">Of laughter I said, ‘It is mad.’</quotation> There is a story about one of the great Babylonian [scholars], who married off his son,10 and 
            made a great banquet for the sages. He said to his son, <quote speaker="Babylonian_scholar">Go up and bring us a jar of such and such a wine from the attic.</quote> He went up to the attic. [There] a snake [from] 
                among the jars bit him, and he died. His father remained with those who were reclining [at his table]. So he delayed and did not come. [Finally,] his father said, <quote speaker="Babylonian_scholar">Let me go 
                    up and see what my son is doing.</quote> His father went up [and] found him cast down dead among the jars. What did that saint do? He waited by himself until the guests had eaten 
                and drunk sufficiently. When they had finished, he said, <quote speaker="Babylonian_scholar">You came to say a bridegrooms' blessing over my son. [But instead] say a mourners' blessing over him. You came to 
                    bring my son to the wedding canopy. [Instead] bring him to [his] grave.</quote> They said about R. Zakkay of Kabul and they opened about him <paren>in the words of <ref bibverse="ecclesiastes2:2">Eccl. 2:2</ref></paren>, <quotation cite="ecclesiastes2:2">Of 
                        laughter I said, ‘It is mad; and what does joy do?’</quotation></p>
    </midrashim>
    
    <verse>  
        <versenum>Genesis 22:6</versenum>
        <versetext>Abraham took the wood for the burnt offering and put it on his son Isaac. He himself took the firestone and the knife; and the two walked off together.</versetext>
        <versenum>Genesis 22:8</versenum>
        <versetext>And Abraham said, “God will see to the sheep for His burnt offering, my son.” And the two of them walked on together.</versetext>
    </verse>
    <midrashim>
        <source>
            <midtext>Midrash Tanchuma Buber</midtext> 
            <midpass>Vayera 46:9</midpass>
        </source>
        <p>Another interpretation <paren>of <ref bibverse="genesis22:6">Gen. 22:6</ref>, cont.</paren>: <quotation cite="genesis22:6">SO BOTH OF THEM WENT OFF TOGETHER</quotation>. <ref rabbi="Abbin Berabbi the Levite">R. Abbin Berabbi the Levite</ref> said: <quote speaker="Rabbi_Abbin_Berabbi_the_Levite">While they were walking, <ref character="satan">Satan</ref> came to <ref character="isaac">Isaac</ref> on his right hand and said: 
            Alas, wretched son of a wretched woman, how many fasts did your mother fast until you came?172 Now the old man has gone mad in his old age, and here he is going to slaughter you. 
            <ref character="isaac">Isaac</ref> turned back and said to his father: Look at what this one is saying to me! He said to him: He has come to confuse you, but the <ref god="Holy_One">Holy One</ref> shall not 
            confuse us, as stated <paren>in <ref bibverse="genesis22:8">Gen. 22:8</ref></paren>: <quotation cite="genesis22:8">GOD WILL SEE TO THE LAMB FOR A BURNT OFFERING</quotation>. So nevertheless <paren>according to <ref bibverse="genesis22:6">Gen. 22:6</ref></paren>: <quotation cite="genesis22:6">SO BOTH OF THEM WENT OFF TOGETHER</quotation>. How old was <ref character="isaac">Isaac</ref>? He was 
            thirty-seven years old.173</quote></p>
    </midrashim>
    
    <verse>  
        <versenum>Genesis 22:7</versenum>
        <versetext>Then Isaac said to his father Abraham, “Father!” And he answered, “Yes, my son.” And he said, “Here are the firestone and the wood; but where is the sheep for the burnt 
            offering?”</versetext>
        <versenum>Genesis 22:8</versenum>
        <versetext>And Abraham said, “God will see to the sheep for His burnt offering, my son.” And the two of them walked on together.</versetext>
    </verse>
    <midrashim>
        <source>
            <midtext>Bereishit Rabbah</midtext> 
            <midpass>56:4</midpass>
        </source>
        <p><quotation cite="genesis22:7">And Itzchak spoke to Avraham his father, and said: My father</quotation> <paren><ref bibverse="genesis22:7">Gen. 22:7</ref></paren>. <ref character="samael">Samael</ref> went to the our father <ref character="abraham">Avraham</ref> and said: <speech speaker="samael">“Old man, old man! Have you lost your mind 
            [lit. have you lost your heart]? You are going to slay a son given to you at the age of a hundred!</speech> <speech speaker="abraham">Even this I do,</speech> replied he. [<ref character="samael">Samael</ref> said:] <speech speaker="samael">And if He sets you an 
                even greater test, can you stand it?!</speech> [as it is written] <quotation cite="job4:2">If a thing be put to you as a trial, will you be wearied</quotation> <paren><ref bibverse="job4:2">Job 4:2</ref></paren>? <speech speaker="abraham">Even more than this,</speech> he replied. [<ref character="samael">Samael</ref> 
            said:] <speech speaker="samael">Tomorrow He will say to you, “You are guilty of murder, you murdered your son!”</speech> He replied: <speech speaker="abraham">Still I go</speech>. Seeing that he could achieve nothing with him, he 
            approached <ref character="itzchak">Itzchak</ref> and said: <speech speaker="samael">Son of an unhappy mother! He is going to slay you!</speech> He replied: <speech speaker="itzchak">Still I go</speech>. <ref character="samael">Samael</ref> said: <speech speaker="Samael">If so, all those fine tunics which your mother 
                made be a legacy for <ref character="ishmael">Ishmael</ref>, the hated of her house, and you don't care [lit. don't let it enter your heart]?</speech> If a word is not completely effective, it may yet be 
            effective in part, that’s why it is written, <quotation cite="genesis22:7">“And Itzchak spoke to Avraham his father, and said: My father”</quotation>: why [his] father, [my] father twice? So that he should be 
            filled with compassion for him. <quotation cite="genesis22:7">And he said: Behold, the fire and the wood.</quotation> <ref character="abraham">Avraham</ref> said to him: <speech speaker="abraham">May that man who has thus seduced him be drowned! Any way, <quotation cite="genesis22:8">God will 
                provide himself the lamb, my son”</quotation>; and if not you are <quotation cite="genesis22:8">the lamb for the burnt-offering my son.</quotation></speech> So <quotation cite="genesis22:8">"they went both of them together"</quotation> <paren><ref bibverse="genesis22:8">Gen. 22:8</ref></paren> — one to slaughter and 
            the other to be slaughtered.</p>
    </midrashim>
    
    <verse>  
        <versenum>Genesis 22:2</versenum>
        <versetext>And He said, “Take your son, your favored one, Isaac, whom you love, and go to the land of Moriah, and offer him there as a burnt offering on one of the heights that I will 
            point out to you.”</versetext>
        <versenum>Genesis 22:11</versenum>
        <versetext>Then an angel of the LORD called to him from heaven: “Abraham! Abraham!” And he answered, “Here I am.”</versetext>
        <versenum>Genesis 22:12</versenum>
        <versetext>And he said, “Do not raise your hand against the boy, or do anything to him. For now I know that you fear God, since you have not withheld your son, your favored one, from 
            Me.”</versetext>
    </verse>
    <midrashim>
        <source>
            <midtext>Bereishit Rabbah</midtext> 
            <midpass>56:8</midpass>
        </source>
        <p>Another explanation: <ref rabbi="Itzchak">Rabbi Itzchak</ref> said, <quote speaker="Rabbi_Itzchak">At the time that <ref character="abraham">Avraham</ref> sought to bind <ref character="itzchak">Itzchak</ref>, his son, [the latter] said to him, <speech speaker="itzchak">Father, I am a young man and I am concerned lest my 
            body shake from fear of the knife and I will trouble you, and lest the slaughtering will be invalid and it will not be considered a sacrifice for you. Rather, tie me very well.</speech> 
            Immediately, <quotation cite="genesis22:8">and he bound Itzchak.</quotation> Could he really tie up a man of thirty-seven (a different version: of twenty six years)? Rather, it was with his agreement. Immediately. <quotation cite="genesis22:9">And 
                Avraham sent his hand.</quotation> He sends his hand to take the knife and his eyes brings down tears and the tears fall onto the eyes of <ref character="itzchak">Itzchak</ref> from the mercy of his father. And 
            nonetheless, the heart was happy to do the will of <ref god="Maker">his Maker</ref>. And the angels gathered in many groups above them. What did they yell out? <quotation cite="isaiah33:7">The ways have become desolate, the 
                wayfarer has ceased; He has rescinded His covenant; He has become disgusted with the cities</quotation> <paren><ref bibverse="isaiah33:7">Isaiah 33:7</ref></paren> – He does not desire Jerusalem and the Temple that he had in mind to 
            bequeath to the children of <ref character="itzchak">Itzchak</ref>. 'He did not consider a man' – merit did not stand <ref character="abraham">Avraham</ref> well: 'No creation has importance in front of Me.'</quote>
            <ref rabbi="Acha">Rabbi Acha</ref> said, <quote speaker="Rabbi_Acha"><ref character="abraham">Avraham</ref> started to wonder, <speech speaker="abraham">These words are only words of wonder. Yesterday, you told me <paren><ref bibverse="genesis21:12">Genesis 21:12</ref></paren>, <quotation cite="genesis21:12">Because in Itzchak will your seed be called.</quotation> And 
                [then] you went back and said, "Please take your son." And now You say to me, "Do not send your hand to the youth." It is a wonder!</speech> The <ref god="Holy_One">Holy One</ref>, blessed be He, said, <speech speaker="holy one">'<ref character="abraham">Avraham</ref>, 
                    <quotation cite="psalm89:35">I will not profane My covenant and the utterances of My lips, I will not change</quotation> <paren><ref bibverse="psalm89:35">Psalms 89:35</ref></paren> – When I said, "Please take your son," I did not say, "slaughter him," but 
                    rather, "and bring him up." For the sake of love did I say [it] to you: I said to you, "Bring him up," and you have fulfilled My words. And now, bring him down.’</speech> [A different 
                version: They said a parable about a king that said to his friend, <speech speaker="king">Bring up your son to my table.</speech> His friend brought him up and his knife was in his hand. The king said, <speech speaker="king">And 
                    did I say to you, "Bring him up to eat him?" I said to you, "Bring him up"</speech> – [and this was] because of [the king's] love.) This is [the meaning of] what is written <paren><ref bibverse="jeremiah19:5">Jeremiah 
                        19:5</ref></paren>, <quotation>it did not come up on My heart</quotation> – that is <ref character="itzchak">Itzchak</ref>.</quote>]</p>
    </midrashim>
    
    <verse>  
        <versenum>Genesis 22:11</versenum>
        <versetext>Then an angel of the LORD called to him from heaven: “Abraham! Abraham!” And he answered, “Here I am.”</versetext>
        <versenum>Genesis 22:12</versenum>
        <versetext>And he said, “Do not raise your hand against the boy, or do anything to him. For now I know that you fear God, since you have not withheld your son, your favored one, from 
            Me.”</versetext>
    </verse>
    <midrashim>
        <source>
            <midtext>Bereishit Rabbah</midtext> 
            <midpass>56:7</midpass>
        </source>
        <p><quotation cite="genesis22:11">And the angel of Ad-nai called to him out of heaven, and said: Abraham, Abraham</quotation> <paren><ref bibverse="genesis22:11">Gen. 22:11</ref></paren>. <ref rabbi="Hiya">Rabbi Hiya</ref> taught: <quote speaker="Rabbi_Hiya">This is an expression of love, this is an expression of 
            urging.</quote> <ref rabbi="Eliezer ben Yaakov">Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov</ref> said: <quote speaker="Rabbi_Eliezer_ben_Yaakov">He spoke to him and to future generations, there is no generation which does not contain people like <ref character="abraham">Avraham</ref>, and there is no 
                generation which does not contain people like <ref character="yaakov">Yaakov</ref>, <ref character="moshe">Moshe</ref>, and <ref character="shmuel">Shmuel</ref>. <quotation cite="genesis22:12">And he said: "Do not lay your hand etc."</quotation> <paren><ref bibverse="">Gen. 22:12</ref></paren> Where was the knife? Three tears had fallen 
                from the angels of service and the knife dissolved. <ref character="abraham">Avraham</ref> said: <speech speaker="abraham">I will strangle him,</speech> He said: <quotation cite="genesis22:12">Do not lay your hand upon the lad.</quotation> [<ref character="abraham">Avraham</ref>] said <speech speaker="abraham">I will take a drop 
                    of blood from him</speech> - He said to him: ‘Neither do <translation heb="me'uma">anything</translation> [<hebrew>me'uma</hebrew>] to him’ [meaning] inflict no <translation heb="muma">blemish</translation> [<hebrew>muma</hebrew>] upon him. "Because now I know" [meaning] I have made it 
                known to all that you love Me, <quotation cite="genesis22:12">"and you have not withheld, etc"</quotation>. And do not say that all ills that do not affect one’s own body are not ills, rather I ascribe merit to 
                you as though I had told to you to sacrifice yourself and you did not refuse.</quote></p>
    </midrashim>
    
    <verse>  
        <versenum>Genesis 22:13</versenum>
        <versetext>When Abraham looked up, his eye fell upon a ram, caught in the thicket by its horns. So Abraham went and took the ram and offered it up as a burnt offering in place of his son.</versetext>
    </verse>
    <midrashim>
        <source>
            <midtext>Midrash Tanchuma</midtext> 
            <midpass>Vayera 23:9</midpass>
        </source>
        <p>The <ref god="Holy_One">Holy One</ref>, blessed be He, answered: <quote speaker="Holy_One">You have spoken what was in you heart, now I will say what I wish to say. In the future <ref character="isaac">Isaac</ref>’s descendants will sin against Me, and I will judge them 
            on <ref holyDay="Rosh Hashanah">Rosh Hashanah</ref>. If they want Me to discover something to their credit, and to recall for their advantage the binding of <ref character="isaac">Isaac</ref>, let them blow upon this shofar.</quote> <ref character="abraham">Abraham</ref> asked: <quote speaker="Abraham">What shofar?</quote> 
            The <ref god="Holy_One">Holy One</ref>, blessed be He, said: <quote speaker="Holy_One">Turn around.</quote> Then it was that <ref character="abraham">Abraham</ref> lifted up his eyes, and looked, and behold, behind a ram caught in the thicket by his horns <paren><ref bibverse="genesis22:13">Gen. 22:13</ref></paren>. This was 
            one of the ten things that were created at twilight.17</p>
    </midrashim>
    
    <verse>  
    <versenum>Genesis 22:1-19</versenum>
    <versetext>Some time afterward, God put Abraham to the test. He said to him, “Abraham,” and he answered, “Here I am.”
        And He said, “Take your son, your favored one, Isaac, whom you love, and go to the land of Moriah, and offer him there as a burnt offering on one of the heights that I will point out 
        to you.”
        So early next morning, Abraham saddled his ass and took with him two of his servants and his son Isaac. He split the wood for the burnt offering, and he set out for the place of which 
        God had told him.
        On the third day Abraham looked up and saw the place from afar.
        Then Abraham said to his servants, “You stay here with the ass. The boy and I will go up there; we will worship and we will return to you.”
        Abraham took the wood for the burnt offering and put it on his son Isaac. He himself took the firestone and the knife; and the two walked off together.
        Then Isaac said to his father Abraham, “Father!” And he answered, “Yes, my son.” And he said, “Here are the firestone and the wood; but where is the sheep for the burnt offering?”
        And Abraham said, “God will see to the sheep for His burnt offering, my son.” And the two of them walked on together.
        They arrived at the place of which God had told him. Abraham built an altar there; he laid out the wood; he bound his son Isaac; he laid him on the altar, on top of the wood.
        And Abraham picked up the knife to slay his son.
        Then an angel of the LORD called to him from heaven: “Abraham! Abraham!” And he answered, “Here I am.”
        And he said, “Do not raise your hand against the boy, or do anything to him. For now I know that you fear God, since you have not withheld your son, your favored one, from Me.”
        When Abraham looked up, his eye fell upon a ram, caught in the thicket by its horns. So Abraham went and took the ram and offered it up as a burnt offering in place of his son.
        And Abraham named that site Adonai-yireh, whence the present saying, “On the mount of the LORD there is vision.”
        The angel of the LORD called to Abraham a second time from heaven,
        and said, “By Myself I swear, the LORD declares: Because you have done this and have not withheld your son, your favored one,
        I will bestow My blessing upon you and make your descendants as numerous as the stars of heaven and the sands on the seashore; and your descendants shall seize the gates of their foes.
        All the nations of the earth shall bless themselves by your descendants, because you have obeyed My command.”
        Abraham then returned to his servants, and they departed together for Beer-sheba; and Abraham stayed in Beer-sheba.</versetext>
</verse>
<midrashim>
    <source>
        <midtext>Sefer HaYashar (midrash)</midtext> 
        <midpass>Book of Genesis, Vayera 18</midpass>
    </source>
    <p>And while <ref character="abraham">Abraham</ref> was pursuing his journey with his son <ref character="isaac">Isaac</ref>, behold <ref character="satan">Satan</ref> came and ‎appeared to <ref character="abraham">Abraham</ref> in the figure of a very old man, of a very modest and humble spirit. And ‎
        approaching <ref character="abraham">Abraham</ref> he said unto him: <speech speaker="satan">Art thou a fool or an idiot that thou goest to do such a ‎thing this day and even to thy only son? For behold the <ref god="Lord">Lord</ref> had given him unto thee in 
            the last of thy days and in thy old age, and now wilt thou go and slaughter him without any wrong ‎action of his, and destroy the life of thy only son? Knowest thou not, and hast thou 
            not heard ‎of it, that such a thing could never have come from the <ref god="Lord">Lord</ref>, for the <ref god="Lord">Lord</ref> hath never done ‎unto man a great evil like this upon the earth to say unto a man go and slay thy 
            son?</speech> And ‎<ref character="abraham">Abraham</ref> hearing these words knew at once that it was the voice of <ref character="satan">Satan</ref> who attempted to ‎lead him astray from the way of the <ref god="Lord">Lord</ref>, and <ref character="abraham">Abraham</ref> refused to hearken to the voice 
        of ‎<ref character="satan">Satan</ref>. And <ref character="abraham">Abraham</ref> rebuked him severely and <ref character="satan">Satan</ref> went away from him. And <ref character="satan">Satan</ref> soon ‎returned and came to <ref character="isaac">Isaac</ref>, appearing unto him in the guise of a young man of good figure ‎and 
        pleasant looks. And he approached <ref character="isaac">Isaac</ref> and said unto him: <speech speaker="satan">Knowest thou or hast thou ‎heard of it, that thy old and foolish father carries thee to the slaughter to-day without any ‎
            cause? And now, my boy, do not listen unto him and do not obey him, for he is old and foolish, ‎and do not suffer thy precious life and thy handsome person to perish from the earth.</speech> And 
        ‎when <ref character="isaac">Isaac</ref> had heard these words he turned unto <ref character="abraham">Abraham</ref> saying: <speech speaker="isaac">Hast thou heard, oh, my ‎father, the words of this man, such and such are his remarks.</speech> And <ref character="abraham">Abraham</ref> answered unto his ‎son 
        <ref character="isaac">Isaac</ref> saying: <speech speaker="abraham">Beware of him my son, do not listen unto his word and pay no attention unto ‎him, for that is <ref character="satan">Satan</ref>, who is resolved to turn us this day from following the commandments of 
            ‎our <ref god="Lord">Lord</ref>.</speech> And <ref character="abraham">Abraham</ref> rebuked <ref character="satan">Satan</ref> once more, and he went away from them. And when ‎<ref character="satan">Satan</ref> saw that he could not succeed in that manner, he disappeared suddenly and went on ‎before them 
        on their road, and changed himself into a mighty river full of water on the road. ‎And when <ref character="abraham">Abraham</ref> and <ref character="isaac">Isaac</ref> and his two young men reached that place they saw a river, ‎large and very 
        powerful like unto the mighty waters. And they went into the river, the waters ‎of which reached up to their legs and they passed on through it. But the waters grew always ‎deeper and 
        reached finally to their necks, when they were all terrified on account of the ‎water. And as they passed on <ref character="abraham">Abraham</ref> at once recognized the place, and <ref character="abraham">Abraham</ref> knew that ‎there hath never 
        been a river before on that place. And <ref character="abraham">Abraham</ref> said unto his son <ref character="isaac">Isaac</ref>: <speech speaker="abraham">I ‎know this place well and there hath never been before neither a river nor any water, and it is ‎only the work 
            of <ref character="satan">Satan</ref>, who is doing these things in order to turn us this day from the ‎commandments of the <ref god="Lord">Lord</ref>.</speech> And <ref character="abraham">Abraham</ref> rebuked <ref character="satan">Satan</ref> saying unto him: <speech speaker="abraham">May the <ref god="Lord">Lord</ref> ‎rebuke thee, oh <ref character="satan">Satan</ref>, get 
                thee behind us for we are following the order of our <ref god="Lord">Lord</ref>.</speech> And ‎<ref character="satan">Satan</ref> became terrified at <ref character="abraham">Abraham</ref>'s voice and he departed from them,</p>
</midrashim>

    <verse>  
        <versenum>Genesis 22:1-19</versenum>
        <versetext>Some time afterward, God put Abraham to the test. He said to him, “Abraham,” and he answered, “Here I am.”
            And He said, “Take your son, your favored one, Isaac, whom you love, and go to the land of Moriah, and offer him there as a burnt offering on one of the heights that I will point out 
            to you.”
            So early next morning, Abraham saddled his ass and took with him two of his servants and his son Isaac. He split the wood for the burnt offering, and he set out for the place of which 
            God had told him.
            On the third day Abraham looked up and saw the place from afar.
            Then Abraham said to his servants, “You stay here with the ass. The boy and I will go up there; we will worship and we will return to you.”
            Abraham took the wood for the burnt offering and put it on his son Isaac. He himself took the firestone and the knife; and the two walked off together.
            Then Isaac said to his father Abraham, “Father!” And he answered, “Yes, my son.” And he said, “Here are the firestone and the wood; but where is the sheep for the burnt offering?”
            And Abraham said, “God will see to the sheep for His burnt offering, my son.” And the two of them walked on together.
            They arrived at the place of which God had told him. Abraham built an altar there; he laid out the wood; he bound his son Isaac; he laid him on the altar, on top of the wood.
            And Abraham picked up the knife to slay his son.
            Then an angel of the LORD called to him from heaven: “Abraham! Abraham!” And he answered, “Here I am.”
            And he said, “Do not raise your hand against the boy, or do anything to him. For now I know that you fear God, since you have not withheld your son, your favored one, from Me.”
            When Abraham looked up, his eye fell upon a ram, caught in the thicket by its horns. So Abraham went and took the ram and offered it up as a burnt offering in place of his son.
            And Abraham named that site Adonai-yireh, whence the present saying, “On the mount of the LORD there is vision.”
            The angel of the LORD called to Abraham a second time from heaven,
            and said, “By Myself I swear, the LORD declares: Because you have done this and have not withheld your son, your favored one,
            I will bestow My blessing upon you and make your descendants as numerous as the stars of heaven and the sands on the seashore; and your descendants shall seize the gates of their foes.
            All the nations of the earth shall bless themselves by your descendants, because you have obeyed My command.”
            Abraham then returned to his servants, and they departed together for Beer-sheba; and Abraham stayed in Beer-sheba.</versetext>
    </verse>
    <midrashim>
        <source>
            <midtext>Sefer HaYashar (midrash)</midtext> 
            <midpass>Book of Genesis, Vayera 21</midpass>
        </source>
        <p>And <ref character="abraham">Abraham</ref> slew the ram upon the altar for a burnt offering before the <ref god="Lord">Lord</ref> instead of his ‎son <ref character="isaac">Isaac</ref>; and <ref character="abraham">Abraham</ref> sprinkled of the blood of the ram upon the altar, and he 
            exclaimed, ‎saying: This is instead of my son, and may it be considered as the blood of my son before the ‎<ref god="Lord">Lord</ref>, even on this day; and whatsoever <ref character="abraham">Abraham</ref> performed upon that occasion he 
            always ‎accompanied it by these words: <speech speaker="abraham">This is in the place of my son, and may it be considered this ‎day before the <ref god="Lord">Lord</ref> in place of my son.</speech> And when <ref character="abraham">Abraham</ref> had completed the services at 
            the ‎altar, and the offering was accepted by the <ref god="Lord">Lord</ref>, it was actually considered as if it had been ‎<ref character="isaac">Isaac</ref> that was sacrificed. And the <ref god="Lord">Lord</ref> blessed <ref character="abraham">Abraham</ref> and his seed on that day. And 
            <ref character="Satan">Satan</ref> ‎hurried unto <ref character="sarah">Sarah</ref> and appeared unto her in the guise of a very humble and lowly old man, ‎while <ref character="abraham">Abraham</ref> was still performing his duties at the altar before the Lord. And Satan said 
            unto ‎<ref character="sarah">Sarah</ref>: <speech speaker="satan">Knowest thou not the work that <ref character="abraham">Abraham</ref> hath done with thine only son to-day? Verily, ‎he hath taken <ref character="isaac">Isaac</ref> and built an altar and killed him and brought him for a burnt 
                offering upon ‎the altar; and <ref character="isaac">Isaac</ref> was weeping and praying before his father, but he never heeded his cries ‎and he had no mercy upon him.‎‏</speech> ‏And after repeating his story, Satan departed 
            from <ref character="sarah">Sarah</ref>; and ‎<ref character="sarah">Sarah</ref> having heard these words of <ref character="satan">Satan</ref>, took him for one of the sons of man who had been ‎with her son and who had come to tell her these words.‎‏ ‏And <ref character="sarah">Sarah</ref> lifted up her 
            voice and she ‎wept and cried bitterly over the loss of her son; and she lay down upon the ground and she ‎scattered dust upon her head, and she exclaimed: <speech speaker="sarah">Oh, my son, <ref character="isaac">Isaac</ref> | oh, my son 
                would that I ‎had died to-day in thy place |</speech> And she continued weeping and crying: <speech speaker="sarah">It grieves me for thy ‎sake, oh, my son I Would that I had died to-day in thy place!</speech> And she kept on 
            lamenting, and ‎she said: <speech speaker="sarah">It grieves me for thy sake, now after I have raised thee and brought thee up, my joy ‎hath been turned into mourning for thee, I who was yearning for thee, I who 
                have been crying ‎and praying to the <ref god="Lord">Lord</ref> for thee until I bare thee at the age of ninety years, and now hast thou ‎been given up to-day to the knife and to the fire to be made a burnt 
                offering; yet I will take ‎comfort, my son, in the thought that all hath been caused by the word of the <ref god="Lord">Lord</ref>, as thou ‎hast performed the commandment of thy <ref god="God">God</ref>, and who can rebel 
                against the word of <ref god="God">God</ref> in ‎whose hand is the <ref item="soul">soul</ref> of every living creature? Thou art just, O <ref god="Lord_our_God">Lord our God</ref>, and all thy ‎works are justice and righteousness; and I am exceedingly glad at 
                the words of thy command, ‎and though mine eye weepeth, my heart rejoiceth within me.</speech>‎‏ ‏And <ref character="sarah">Sarah</ref> placed her head ‎upon the bosom of one of her maid servants and she became silent like a 
            rock. And soon after ‎she arose and went about to make inquiries until she reached Hebron. And she questioned ‎every passer-by that she met on the road, but no one could tell her 
            anything concerning the ‎fate of her son.‎</p>
    </midrashim>
    
</midrash>
