<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="Midrash/XML:Relax/midrashim_schema.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<midrash>

    <verse>
        <versenum>Psalm 24.1</versenum>
        <versetext>Of David. A psalm. The earth is the LORD’s and all that it holds, the world and
            its inhabitants.</versetext>
        <versenum>Psalm 24.2</versenum>
        <versetext>For He founded it upon the ocean, set it on the nether-streams.</versetext>
        <versenum>Psalm 24.3</versenum>
        <versetext>Who may ascend the mountain of the LORD? Who may stand in His holy
            place?—</versetext>
        <versenum>Psalm 24.4</versenum>
        <versetext>He who has clean hands and a pure heart, who has not taken a false oath by My
            life or sworn deceitfully.</versetext>
        <versenum>Psalm 24.5</versenum>
        <versetext>He shall carry away a blessing from the LORD, a just reward from God, his
            deliverer.</versetext>
        <versenum>Psalm 24.6</versenum>
        <versetext>Such is the circle of those who turn to Him, Jacob, who seek Your
            presence.Selah.</versetext>
        <versenum>Psalm 24.7</versenum>
        <versetext>O gates, lift up your heads! Up high, you everlasting doors, so the King of glory
            may come in!</versetext>
        <versenum>Psalm 24.8</versenum>
        <versetext>Who is the King of glory?— the LORD, mighty and valiant, the LORD, valiant in
            battle.</versetext>
        <versenum>Psalm 24.9</versenum>
        <versetext>O gates, lift up your heads! Lift them up, you everlasting doors, so the King of
            glory may come in!</versetext>
        <versenum>Psalm 24.10</versenum>
        <versetext>Who is the King of glory?— the LORD of hosts, He is the King of
            glory!Selah.</versetext>
    </verse>


    <midrashim>
        <source>
            <midtext>Midrash Ein Yaakov </midtext>
            <edition>Glick Edition</edition>
            <midpass>Rosh Hashanah 4:1</midpass>
        </source>
        <p><paren>Fol. 31</paren> We are taught in a Baraitha: <ref rabbi="Juda">R. Juda</ref> said,
            in the name of <ref rabbi="Akiba">R. Akiba</ref>: <quote speaker="Rabbi_Akiba">What
                <paren>song</paren> did <paren>the Levites</paren> chant on the first day of the week? <paren><ref
                        bibverse="Psalm24">Ps. 24</ref></paren>
                <quotation cite="Psalm24">The earth is the <ref god="Lord">Lord's</ref> and the
                    fulness thereof, because He <paren>the <ref god="Lord">Lord</ref>, in establishing the
                    world</paren> took possession and gave <paren>His creatures</paren> possession <paren>invested them
                        with life</paren>, and <paren>became</paren> the Sovereign of the world.</quotation> What
                did they sing on the second day? <paren><ref bibverse="Psalm48">Ib. 48</ref></paren>
                <quotation cite="Psalm48">Great is the <ref god="Lord">Lord</ref> and greatly to be
                    praised, because <paren>on that day</paren> He divided His works <paren>the heavens from the earth</paren>
                    and reigned over them.</quotation> On the third day they sang <paren><ref
                        bibverse="Psalm82">Ib. 82</ref></paren>
                <ref bibverse="Psalm82"><ref god="God">God</ref> standeth in the congregation of the
                    mighty, because <paren>on that day</paren> He, in His wisdom, caused the earth to be revealed
                    and the world to be prepared for its occupants.</ref> On the fourth day they
                sang <paren><ref bibverse="Psalm94">Ib. 94</ref></paren>
                <ref bibverse="Psalm94">O <ref god="Lord">Lord</ref>, to whom retribution belongeth,
                    because <paren>on that day</paren> He created the sun and moon, and in the future He will
                    punish those who would worship them.</ref> On the fifth day they sang
                        <paren><ref bibverse="Psalm81">Ib. 81</ref></paren>
                <ref bibverse="Psalm81">Sing aloud unto <ref god="God">God</ref>, our strength,
                    because <paren>on that day</paren> He created the birds and the fishes <paren>which bring</paren> praise
                    to His name.</ref> On the sixth day they sang, <paren><ref bibverse="Psalm93"
                        >Ib. 93</ref></paren>
                <ref bibverse="Psalm93">The <ref god="Lord">Lord</ref> reigneth. He is clothed in
                    majesty, because <paren>on that day</paren> He finished His works and became sovereign over
                    them.</ref> On the seventh day they sang <paren><ref bibverse="Psalm92">Ib.
                        92</ref></paren>
                <ref bibverse="Psalm92">A psalm, a song, for the <ref holyDay="Sabbath">Sabbath
                        day</ref>; i.e., for the day that is a perfect rest.</ref>"</quote>
            <ref rabbi="Nechemia">R. Nechemia</ref> said : <quote speaker="Rabbi_Nechemia">"What
                reason had <ref rabbi="Akiba">R. Akiba </ref>to make distinctions among these
                sections, <paren>for the last refers to a future event, while all the others refer to the
                past</paren> ? We must therefore say that they sang that psalm on the <ref
                    holyDay="Sabbath">Sabbath</ref> day, because He rested."</quote> This is
            contrary to the opinion of <ref rabbi="K'tina">R. K'tina</ref>, for <ref rabbi="K'tina"
                >R. K'tina</ref> said: <quote speaker="Rabbi_K'tina">"The world will last six
                thousand years, and one thousand years it will be waste; as it is said <paren><ref
                        bibverse="Isaiah2.11">Is. 2, 11</ref></paren>
                <ref bibverse="Isaiah2.11">And exalted shall be the <ref god="Lord">Lord</ref> alone
                    on that day</ref>"</quote>
            <quote speaker="Rabbi_Abaye">
                <ref rabbi="Abaye">Abaye</ref>, however, said: "Two thousand years it will waste; as
                it is said <paren><ref bibverse="Hosea6.2">Hos. 6, 2</ref></paren>
                <ref bibverse="Hosea6.2">He will revive us after two days.</ref>"</quote></p>
    </midrashim>

    <midrashim>
        <source>
            <midtext>Midrash Ein Yaakov </midtext>
            <edition>Glick Edition</edition>
            <midpass>Berakhot 6:2</midpass>
        </source>
        <p>Our Rabbis taught: "<quote speaker="Rabbis">It is prohibited to enjoy anything of this
                world without saving a benediction, and he who enjoys <paren>the least thing</paren> in this
                world without saving a benediction defrauds <ref god="Lord"><paren>the Lord</paren></ref>. What
                shall his remedy be? Let him go to a learned man."</quote> What can a learned man do
            for him when he already has transgressed the prohibition? <quote speaker="Raba"
                >"But,"</quote> said <ref rabbi="Raba">Raba</ref>, <quote speaker="Raba">"let him go
                unto a learned man first; study the laws of benedictions that he may avoid
                sacrilege."</quote>
            <ref rabbi="Juda">R. Juda</ref> said in the name of <ref character="Samuel">Samuel</ref>
            : <quote speaker="Rabbi_Juda_as_Samuel">"He who enjoys <paren>the least thing</paren> in this world
                without having said a benediction is considered as if he had enjoyed something of
                the things dedicated to Heaven, for it is said <paren><ref bibverse="Psalm24.1">Ps.
                        24, 1.</ref></paren> Unto the <ref god="Lord">Lord</ref> belongeth the earth
                and all that filleth it."</quote>
            <ref rabbi="Levi">R. Levi</ref> pointed out the following contradiction: <quote
                speaker="Rabbi_Levi">"It is written <paren><ref bibverse="Psalm24.1">Ib.
                    ib.</ref></paren>
                <ref bibverse="Psalm24.1">Unto the <ref god="Lord">Lord</ref> belongeth the earth
                    and all that filleth it</ref>, and it is also written <paren><ref
                        bibverse="Psalm115.16">Ib. 115, I6.</ref></paren>
                <ref bibverse="Psalm115.16">The Heavens are the Heavens of the <ref god="Lord"
                        >Lord</ref>; but the earth hath He given to the children of man.</ref> It is
                not difficult to reconcile <paren>these two verses</paren>. The former refers to the time before
                he pronounced the benediction <ref bibverse="Psalm115.16"><paren>it still belongs to
                    Heaven</paren></ref>, (Ib. b.) and the latter refers to the time after he pronounced
                the benediction <ref bibverse="Psalm115.16"><paren>then it belongs to man</paren></ref>."</quote>
            <ref rabbi="Chanina_b._Papa">R. Chanina b. Papa</ref> said: <quote
                speaker="Chanina_b._Papa">"He who enjoys <paren>anything</paren> in this world without saying a
                benediction is considered as if he has robbed the <ref god="Holy_One">Holy
                One</ref>, praised be He! and the Congregation of Israel, for it is said <paren><ref
                        bibverse="Proverbs28.24">Pr. 28, 24.</ref></paren>
                <ref bibverse="Proverbs28.24">Whoso robbeth his father or his mother and saith it is
                    no transgression, he is the companion of a destroyer.</ref> His father, refers
                to the <ref god="Holy_One">Holy One</ref>, praised be He! as it is said <paren><ref
                        bibverse="Deuteronomy32.6">Deu. 32, 6.</ref></paren>
                <ref bibverse="Deuteronomy32.6">Is He not thy father who hath bought thee</ref>; Or
                his mother, refers to nothing else but the Congregation of Israel., as it is said
                        <paren><ref bibverse="Proverbs1.8">Pr. 1, 8.</ref></paren>
                <ref bibverse="Proverbs1.8">Hear, my son, the instructions of your father and cast
                    not aside the teaching of your mother</ref>."</quote> What is meant by He is a
            companion of a destroyer? <ref rabbi="Chanina_b._Papa">R. Chanina b. Papa</ref> said:
                <quote speaker="Chanina_b._Papa"> "He is a companion of <ref character="Jeroboam"
                    >Jeroboam</ref>, the son of <ref character="Nebat">Nebat</ref>, who has
                corrupted Israel in their relation to their <ref god="Heavenly_Father">Heavenly
                    Father</ref>."</quote></p>
    </midrashim>
    <midrashim>
        <source>
            <midtext>Midrash Ein Yaakov </midtext>
            <edition>Glick Edition</edition>
            <midpass>Shabbat 16:12</midpass>
        </source>
        <p><function allegory="prosperity+piety"><ref character="Joseph">Joseph</ref>, who honored
                the <ref holyDay="Sabbath">Sabbath</ref>, had a very rich neighbor. This neighbor
                was told by the Chaldeans <paren><function definition="Chaldeans"
                        >soothsayers</function></paren> that all his wealth would eventually be
                eaten up by <ref character="Joseph">Joseph</ref>. The neighbor, therefore, sold his
                estate and with the proceeds bought a large diamond, which he fixed in his turban.
                One day, while crossing a bridge, a gust of wind blew his turban into the water and
                a fish swallowed it. This fish <paren>being caught</paren> was brought <paren>to the market</paren> on a
                Friday. <quote speaker="fishermen">"Who wants to buy fish to-day?"</quote> they
                inquired. They were told to go to <ref character="Joseph">Joseph</ref>, who honors
                the <ref holyDay="Sabbath">Sabbath</ref> and usually buys fish that day. So they
                brought the fish to him and he bought it. When the fish was cut up, the jewel was
                found and <ref character="Joseph">Joseph</ref> sold it for thirteen purses of gold
                denarim. When that old man met him, he said to <ref character="Joseph">Joseph</ref>:
                    <quote speaker="old_man">"He, who lends to the <ref holyDay="Sabbath"
                        >Sabbath</ref>
                    <paren>incurring additional expenses in its honor</paren> the Sabbath will
                    repay."</quote></function>
            <ref character="Rabbi">Rabbi</ref> asked <ref rabbi="Ishmael">R. Ishmael</ref>, the son
            of <ref rabbi="Jose">R. Jose</ref>, <quote speaker="Rabbi">"What merited the rich people
                of Palestine who become so wealthy?"</quote> He answered thus: <quote
                speaker="Ishmael">"Because they gave their tithes in due season, as it is said
                        <paren><ref bibverse="Deuteronomy14.22">Deu. 14, 22.</ref></paren> Thou
                shalt tithe the tithe, i.e., give tithes, in order that thou mayest become
                rich."</quote>
            <quote speaker="Rabbi">'What merited the rich of Babylon <paren>where people are exempt from
                tithes</paren> ?'</quote>
            <quote speaker="Ishmael">"Because,"</quote> said <ref rabbi="Ishmael">R. Ishmael</ref>,
                <quote speaker="Ishmael">"they honor the Torah."</quote>
            <quote speaker="Rabbi">"And what merited the rich of other countries that made them so
                wealthy ?"</quote>
            <quote speaker="Ishmael">"Because,"</quote> said he, <quote speaker="Ishmael">"they
                honored the <ref holyDay="Sabbath">Sabbath</ref> ; for <ref rabbi="Chiya_b._Abba">R.
                    Chiya b. Abba</ref> said : <function allegory="prosperity+piety"><quote
                        speaker="Chiya_b._Abba">'I sojourned once with a <ref
                            character="wealthy_man">wealthy man</ref> in Ludki. and I saw that they
                        brought before him a golden table carried by sixteen men, and having sixteen
                        silver links depending from it ; in these links were fixed bowls, cups,
                        pitchers and dishes, all filled with various kinds of victuals, and all
                        sorts of rare fruits and spices. When setting the table, they said: <ref
                            bibverse="Psalm24.1">Unto the <ref god="Lord">Lord</ref> belongs the
                            earth with what filleth it</ref>
                        <paren><ref bibverse="Psalm24.1">Ps. 24, 1</ref></paren>. And when they
                        removed the table, they said <ref bibverse="Psalm115.16">The heavens are the
                            heavens of the <ref god="Lord">Lord</ref>; but the earth hath he given
                            to the children of men</ref>
                        <paren><ref bibverse="Psalm115.16">Ib. 115, 16</ref></paren>. I said to him
                            <quote speaker="Chiya_b._Abba">'My son, how have you merited this
                            prosperity?'</quote> He said to me: <quote speaker="wealthy_man">'I was
                            formerly a butcher, and I always selected the finest cattle to be
                            slaughtered for the <ref holyDay="Sabbath">Sabbath</ref>.'</quote> I
                        then said to him : <quote speaker="Chiya_b._Abba">'Happy art thou for being
                            so merited and blessed be the <ref god="Lord">Lord</ref> who hath
                            rewarded thee with all this.'</quote></quote></function> "</quote></p>
    </midrashim>
    <midrashim>
        <source>
            <midtext>Midrash Ein Yaakov </midtext>
            <edition>Glick Edition</edition>
            <midpass>Bava Batra 5:23</midpass>
        </source>
        <p>When <ref rabbi="Dimi">R. Dimi</ref> came from Palestine, he said in the name of <ref
                rabbi="Jonathan">R. Jonathan</ref>, <quote speaker="Dimi_as_Jonathan">"what is the
                meaning of the passage <paren><ref bibverse="Psalm24.2">Ps. 24, 2</ref></paren><ref
                    bibverse="Psalm24.2"> For upon seas he hath founded it, and upon rivers he hath
                    established it?</ref> i.e. the seven seas and four rivers which surround the
                land of Israel <paren>Palestine</paren>, the seven seas are the seas of Tiberia,
                Sodom, Chirat, Chiltha, Sipchi, Aspamia, and the ocean; and the four rivers are
                Jordan, Jarmuch, Kirumyun, and Phiga."</quote> When <ref rabbi="Dimi">R. Dimi</ref>
            came, he said in the name of <ref rabbi="Jonathan">R. Jonathan</ref> : <quote
                speaker="Dimi_as_Jonathan">"In the future the angel <ref character="Gabriel"
                    >Gabriel</ref>
                <paren>Fol. 75</paren> will go hunting for the <ref character="leviathan"
                    >leviathan</ref>, as it is said <paren><ref bibverse="Job40.25">Job 40,
                    25</ref></paren>
                <ref bibverse="Job40.25">Canst thou draw out the <ref character="crocodile"
                        >crocodile</ref>
                    <paren><function definition="crocodile">leviathan</function></paren> with a
                    fishhook or cause his tongue to sink into the baited rope?</ref> And if not for
                the help of the <ref god="Holy_One">Holy One</ref>, praised be He ! he would not
                conquer him, as it is said <paren><ref bibverse="Job40.25">Ib.</ref></paren>
                <ref bibverse="Job40.25">He is the first in rank . . . he that hath made him can
                    alone bring his sword near to him</ref>."</quote> When <ref rabbi="Dimi">R.
                Dimi</ref> came, he said also in the name of <ref rabbi="Jochanan">R. Jochanan</ref>
            : <quote speaker="Dimi_as_Jochanan">"When the <ref character="leviathan">leviathan</ref>
                becomes hungry, he expels from his mouth a gas which makes all the waters in the
                deep boil, as it is said <paren><ref bibverse="Job41.23">Ib. 41, 23</ref></paren>
                <ref bibverse="Job41.23">He maketh the deep to boil like a pot. And should he put
                    his head in paradise, not one of the creatures could withstand the bad smell of
                    the gas</ref>, as it is said <paren><ref bibverse="Job41.23">Ib.</ref></paren>
                <ref bibverse="Job41.23">He maketh the sea like a seething mixture. And when he gets
                    thirsty, he makes the sea hollow like beds</ref>, as it is said: <ref
                    bibverse="Job41.23">Behind him he causeth his pathway to shine.</ref>"</quote>
            And <ref rabbi="Acha_b._Jacob">R. Acha b. Jacob</ref> said : <quote
                speaker="Acha_b._Jacob">"The deep does not come to its natural way before seventy
                years, as it is said <paren><ref bibverse="Job41.23">Ib.</ref></paren>
                <ref bibverse="Job41.23">Men esteem the deep to be hoary</ref> — and hoary is not
                less than seventy years."</quote></p>
    </midrashim>
    <midrashim>
        <source>
            <midtext>Midrash Ein Yaakov </midtext>
            <edition>Glick Edition</edition>
            <midpass>Moed Katan 1:4</midpass>
        </source>
        <p><paren><ref bibverse="Deuteronomy9">Ib. 9</ref></paren> But whence do we learn that one
            joy must not be mixed with another? Said <ref rabbi="Juda">R. Juda</ref> in the name of
                <ref character="Samuel">Samuel</ref> : <quote speaker="Juda_as_Samuel">"It is
                written <paren><ref bibverse="IKings8.65">I Kings 8, 65</ref></paren>
                <ref bibverse="IKings8.65">And <ref character="Solomon">Solomon</ref> held at the
                    time the feast, etc., seven days and seven days, even fourteen days</ref>. Now,
                if it be true that one joy may be mixed with another, why then did <ref
                    character="Solomon">Solomon</ref> not postpone his feast until the festival ;
                for then the seven days of the festival would have served for both?"</quote>
            <ref rabbi="Parnach">R. Parnach</ref>, in the name of <ref rabbi="Jochanan">R.
                Jochanan</ref>, said : <quote speaker="Parnach_as_Jochanan">"In that year the
                Israelites had not observed the <ref holyDay="Day_of_Atonement">Day of
                    Atonement</ref> and they were perturbed over the sin that might cause them
                destruction. Whereupon a heavenly voice came forth and said unto them: <quote
                    speaker="heavenly_voice">'All of you are destined for the future
                world'</quote>"</quote> And whence do we learn that they were pardoned for that sin?
                <ref rabbi="Tachlipha">R. Tachlipha</ref> was taught <paren>See Volume One, page
                118, line 9.</paren></p>
    </midrashim>
    <!-- Mark up this one later-->
    <midrashim>
        <source>
            <midtext>Midrash Ein Yaakov </midtext>
            <edition>Glick Edition</edition>
            <midpass>Shabat 2:10</midpass>
        </source>
        <p><paren>Fol. 30a</paren> The following question was asked of <ref rabbi="Tanchum_of_Noy"
                >R. Tanchum of Noy</ref>: <quote speaker="random_person">"Is it permissible to
                extinguish the <ref item="holy_light">light</ref> on the <ref holyDay="Sabbath"
                    >Sabbath</ref> for the sake of a sick person ?"</quote> He began his answer by
            saying: <quote speaker="Tanchum_of_Noy">"O thou <ref character="King_Solomon">King
                    Solomon</ref>! Where is thy wisdom and where is thy understanding ? Not only do
                the words contradict your father's words but <paren>they are at variance with</paren> thine own
                utterances also. Thy father <ref character="David">David</ref> said <paren><ref
                        bibverse="Psalm116.17">Ps. 116, 17.</ref></paren>
                <ref bibverse="Psalm116.17">Not the dead can praise the <ref god="Lord"
                    >Lord</ref></ref>, and thou sayest <paren><ref bibverse="Ecclesiastes4.2">Ecc.
                        4, 2.</ref></paren>
                <ref bibverse="Ecclesiastes4.2">Thereupon praise I the dead that are already
                    dead</ref>, and again thou sayest <paren><ref bibverse="Ecclesiastes9.4">Ib. 9.,
                        4.</ref></paren>
                <ref bibverse="Ecclesiastes9.4">For a living dog fareth better than a dead
                    lion</ref>. But this is not difficult to explain. When <ref character="David"
                    >David</ref> said. Not the dead can praise the <ref god="Lord">Lord</ref>, he
                meant thus: <quote speaker="David">'A man should always occupy himself with the
                    study of the <ref item="Torah">Torah</ref> and meritorious deeds before he dies;
                    for, as soon as he dies, he becomes free from the obligation of <paren>studying</paren> the
                        <ref item="Torah">Torah</ref> and <paren>fulfilling</paren> meritorious deeds and the
                        <ref god="Holy_One">Holy One</ref>, praised be He! accepts no praise of
                    him.'</quote> This is what <ref rabbi="Jochanan">R. Jochanan</ref> said : <quote
                    speaker="Jochanan">'What is meant by the passage <paren><ref
                            bibverse="Psalm88.61">Ps. 88, 61.</ref></paren> Free among the dead,
                    i.e., as soon as a man dies he is freed from the obligation of <paren>studying</paren> the
                        <ref item="Torah">Torah</ref> and <paren>fulfilling</paren> meritorious deeds, And when
                        <ref character="Solomon">Solomon</ref> says <paren><ref
                            bibverse="Ecclesiastes4.2">Ecc. 4. 2.</ref></paren> Thereupon praise I
                    the dead that are already dead, he refers to the time when Israel sinned in the
                    deserts. <ref character="Moses">Moses</ref> stood up before the <ref
                        god="Holy_One">Holy One</ref>, praised be He ! and offered many prayers and
                    supplications unto Him but was not answered. However, as soon as he said
                            <paren><ref bibverse="Exodus32.13">Ex 32, 13.</ref></paren> Remember
                        <ref character="Abraham">Abraham</ref>, <ref character="Isaac">Isaac</ref>
                    and <ref character="Israel">Israel</ref>, Thy servants, he was forthwith
                    answered. Now, did not <ref character="Solomon">Solomon</ref> say properly
                    Thereupon praise I the dead that are already dead.'</quote>"</quote> It may be
            explained in another way also. The usage of the world is that if a mortal prince issue a
            decree, it is doubtful whether it will be complied with or not; even if it be complied
            with while the prince lives it may not be complied with when he is dead. But <ref
                character="Moses">Moses</ref>, our teacher, has issued many decrees and established
            many ordinances and they endure forever and ever. Now did not <ref character="Solomon"
                >Solomon</ref> say properly <paren><ref bibverse="Ecclesiastes4.2">Ecc. 4,
                2.</ref></paren> Thereupon praise I the dead that are already dead! The passage,
            Thereupon praise I the dead, etc., may also be explained in another way, as <ref
                rabbi="Juda">R. Juda</ref> said in the name of <ref rabbi="Rab">Rab</ref> ; for <ref
                rabbi="Juda">R. Juda</ref> in the name of <ref rabbi="Rab">Rab</ref> said : <quote
                speaker="Juda_as_Rab">"What is meant by the passage <paren><ref
                        bibverse="Psalm86.17">Ps. 86, 17.</ref></paren>
                <speech speaker="David">Display on me a sign for good that those who hate me may see
                    it</speech>. Thus said <ref character="David">David</ref> before the <ref
                    god="Holy_One">Holy One</ref>, <speech speaker="writer">praised be He!</speech>
                <quote speaker="David">'<ref god="Sovereign_of_the_universe">Sovereign of the
                        universe</ref>, forgive me this sin <paren>of <ref character="Bath_Sheba">Bath
                        Sheba</ref></paren>.'</quote>
                <quote speaker="Lord">'Thou art forgiven.'</quote> answered the <ref god="Lord"
                    >Lord</ref>. <ref character="David">David</ref> then said to the <ref god="Lord"
                    >Lord</ref> : <quote speaker="David">'Show me a sign while I live.'</quote>
                Whereupon He answered, <quote speaker="Lord">'During thy life I shall not make it
                    known but during the life of <ref character="Solomon">Solomon</ref>, thy son, I
                    shall make it known.'</quote>
                <function allegory="importance_of_faith_in_God">When <ref character="Solomon"
                        >Solomon</ref> had built the Temple he desired to place the <ref item="ark"
                        >ark</ref> in the <ref item="holy_of_holies">holy of holies</ref>, but the
                    gates had become fastened to each other <paren>and they could not be opened</paren>. <ref
                        character="Solomon">Solomon</ref> then offered twenty-four prayer-songs but
                    was not answered. He then began the prayer <paren><ref bibverse="Psalm24.7">Ps.
                            24, 7.</ref></paren>
                    <ref bibverse="Psalm24">Raise your heads, O ye gates and be raised wide, ye
                        everlasting gates, and let the <ref god="king_of_glory">king of glory</ref>
                        enter. Thereupon the gates ran after him and opened their mouths and wanted
                        to swallow him up, saying: Who is the <ref god="King_of_glory">King of
                            glory</ref>?</ref>
                    <paren><ref bibverse="Psalm24.7">Ib.</ref></paren>
                    <ref character="Solomon">Solomon</ref> replied. <ref bibverse="Psalm24.7">The
                            <ref god="Lord">Lord</ref>, strong and mighty</ref>
                    <paren><ref bibverse="Psalm24.7">Ib.</ref></paren>. <ref bibverse="Psalm24">He
                        then repeated Raise your heads, O ye gates, and raise up, ye everlasting
                        doors, and let the <ref god="King_of_glory">King of glory</ref> enter. Who
                        is the <ref god="King_of_glory">King of glory</ref>, the <ref
                            god="Lord_of_Hosts">Lord of Hosts</ref>, He is the <ref
                            god="King_of_glory">King of glory</ref>, <hebrew>Selah</hebrew></ref>
                    <paren>
                        <ref bibverse="Psalm24.7">Ib.</ref></paren>. Still he was not answered ; but
                    as soon as he said <ref bibverse="Psalm24.7"><ref god="O_Lord_God">O Lord
                            God</ref> turn not away the face of thy anointed, remember the pious
                        deeds of <ref character="David">David</ref> thy servant,</ref>
                    <paren><ref bibverse="2Chronicles6.12">II Chr. 6, 12</ref></paren>, he was
                    immediately answered. <ref bibverse="2Chronicles6.12">At that moment the faces
                        of <ref character="David">David's</ref> enemies turned black like the bottom
                        of a pot and then it was known to all that the <ref god="Holy_One">Holy
                            One</ref>, praised be He! had forgiven <ref character="David"
                            >David</ref> that sin.</ref></function> Therefore, did not <ref
                    character="Solomon">Solomon</ref> properly say. <speech speaker="Solomon"
                    >Thereupon, praise I the dead, etc.</speech> This is meant by the passage
                        <paren><ref bibverse="IKings8.66">I Kings 8, 66.</ref></paren>
                <function allegory="faith+divineGlory">On the eighth day he dismissed the people;
                    they blessed the king and went unto their tents, glad of heart, because of all
                    the good that the <ref god="Lord">Lord</ref> had done for <ref character="David"
                        >David</ref> his servant and for Israel his people, i.e.. And they went unto
                    their tents, meaning they found their wives levitically pure. Joyful, because of
                    having enjoyed the <ref item="Divine_Glory">Divine Glory</ref>; glad of heart,
                    each man's wife had become pregnant with a male child; because of all the good
                    which <ref god="God">God</ref> had done unto <ref character="David">David</ref>
                    his servant, that he forgave him that sin; and Israel his people, for they were
                    forgiven their neglect of the observance of the <ref holyDay="day_of_Atonement"
                        >day of Atonement</ref>.</function> And when <ref character="Solomon"
                    >Solomon</ref> said <paren><ref bibverse="Ecclesiastes9.4">Ecc. 9,
                    4.</ref></paren></quote>
            <litdev metaphor="appreciate_that_you_are_alive"><ref bibverse="Ecclesiastes9.4">For a
                    living dog fareth better than a dead lion</ref></litdev>, he meant that which
                <ref rabbi="Juda">R. Juda</ref> said in the name of <ref rabbi="Rab">Rab</ref> ; for
                <ref rabbi="Juda">R. Juda</ref> in the name of <ref rabbi="Rab">Rab</ref>, said:
                <quote speaker="Juda_as_Rab">"What is meant by the passage <paren><ref
                        bibverse="Psalm39.5">Ps. 39, 5.</ref></paren>
                <ref bibverse="Psalm39.5">Let me know, O <ref god="Lord">Lord</ref>, my end, and
                    what the measure of my days is, I wish to know when I shall cease to be,</ref>
                i.e., thus said <ref character="David">David</ref> before the <ref god="Holy_One"
                    >Holy One</ref>, praised be He ! <quote speaker="David">'<ref
                        god="Sovereign_of_the_universe">Sovereign of the universe</ref> let me know
                    my end.'</quote> Whereupon the <ref god="Lord">Lord</ref> answered him : <quote
                    speaker="Lord">'It has been decreed by me that the time of the death of mortal
                    man shall not be known;'</quote>
                <quote speaker="David">'<ref bibverse="Psalm39.5">And the measures of my days what
                        are they</ref>'</quote>
                <paren><ref bibverse="Psalm39.5">Ib.</ref></paren>, <ref character="David"
                    >David</ref> again asked. <quote speaker="Lord">'It is decreed by me'</quote>
                answered the <ref god="Lord">Lord</ref>,<quote speaker="Lord">' that the measure of
                    the days of a man shall not be known.'</quote> Again <ref character="David"
                    >David</ref> asked: <quote speaker="David">'I wish to know when I shall cease to
                    be.'</quote> The <ref god="Lord">Lord</ref> then said to him : <quote
                    speaker="Lord">'Thou wilt die on the <ref holyDay="Sabbath"
                    >Sabbath</ref>.'</quote>
                <quote speaker="David">'Let me die rather on the first day of the week,'</quote>
                begged <ref character="David">David</ref>. <quote speaker="Lord">'The first day of
                    the week is the day on which thy son <ref character="Solomon">Solomon</ref>
                    shall be king, and one kingdom must not encroach on the other even by so much as
                    a hair's breath.'</quote>
                <quote speaker="David">'Let me then die on the <ref holyDay="Sabbath">Sabbath</ref>
                    eve,'</quote> pleaded <ref character="David">David</ref>. Whereupon the <ref
                    god="Lord">Lord</ref> said <ref bibverse="Psalm84.11">Far better is a day in thy
                    courts than a thousand</ref>
                <paren><ref bibverse="Psalm84.11">Ps. 84, 11</ref></paren>, i.e., <quote
                    speaker="Lord">'I like one day in which thou art studying the <ref item="Torah"
                        >Torah</ref> better than a thousand burnt offerings which <ref
                        character="Solomon">Solomon</ref>, thy son, will sacrifice before me upon
                    the altar.'</quote> (Ib. b) Each <ref holyDay="Sabbath">Sabbath</ref> day he
                would sit and study. On that <ref holyDay="Sabbath">Sabbath</ref> when he was to
                die, the <ref character="angle_of_death">angel of death</ref> came and stood before
                him, but was unable to do anything because <ref character="David">David</ref> never
                once ceased studying. <paren>Said the <ref character="angle_of_death">angel</ref> to
                himself</paren> <speech speaker="angle_of_death">What shall I do?</speech> There was an
                orchard in the back of <ref character="David">David's</ref> house; the <ref
                    character="angle_of_death">angel of death</ref> went there and shook the trees.
                    <ref character="David">David</ref> <paren>hearing the noise</paren> went out to see <paren>the
                cause of the noise</paren> ; as he ascended the ladder the <ref character="angle_of_death"
                    >angel</ref> caused it to break. <ref character="David">David</ref> fell down
                and consequently stopped studying; whereupon the <ref character="angle_of_death"
                    >angel of death</ref> took his life. It so happened that <ref
                    character="Solomon">Solomon</ref> sent to ask the following questions in the
                    <ref character="academy">academy</ref>: <quote speaker="Solomon">'My father died
                    and lies in sun; what shall I do? <paren>Am I allowed to remove him from the sun?</paren> And
                    the dogs of my father's house are hungry, what shall I do?'</quote> They
                answered him: <quote speaker="academy">'Cut up a carrion and place the pieces before
                    the dogs. As to thy father, place a loaf of bread or an infant upon his body and
                    then you may carry it away from the sun.'</quote> Did not <ref
                    character="Solomon">Solomon</ref>, therefore, say properly? <speech
                    speaker="Solomon">For a living dog fareth better than a dead lion.</speech> And
                as to the question, which I have been asked in your presence, I say this: <litdev
                    wordplay="lamp-Ner;soul-Ner">a <ref item="lamp">lamp</ref> is called
                        <hebrew>Ner</hebrew> and <ref item="soul">the soul</ref> is called
                        <hebrew>Ner</hebrew></litdev>; it is better that a human light
                        <paren><litdev metaphor="human_light">lamp</litdev></paren> be extinguished
                than that <ref god="God">God's</ref> light <paren><litdev metaphor="God's_light"
                        >life</litdev></paren> be extinguished."</quote></p>
    </midrashim>
    <midrashim>
        <source>
            <midtext>Midrash Ein Yaakov </midtext>
            <edition>Glick Edition</edition>
            <midpass>Menachot 4:3</midpass>
        </source>
        <p><ref rabbi="Eliezer_b._Jacob">R. Eliezer b. Jacob</ref> says: <quote
                speaker="Eliezer_b._Jacob">"Whoever wears <ref item="Phylacteries"
                    >Phylacteries</ref> upon his head, <ref item="Phylacteries">Phylacteries</ref>
                upon his hand, fringes on his cloak and has a <ref item="Mezuzh">Mezuzah</ref> on
                his door-post, these all will preserve him from sin, as it is said <paren><ref
                        bibverse="Ecclesiastes4.12">Ecc. 4, 12</ref></paren>
                <ref bibverse="Ecclesiastes4.12">And a <ref item="threefold_cord">threefold
                        cord</ref> is not quickly broken</ref>, and again there is another verse
                        <paren><ref bibverse="Psalm24.8">Ps. 24, 8</ref></paren>
                <ref bibverse="Psalm24.8">The <ref character="angle_of_the_Lord">angel of the <ref
                            god="Lord">Lord</ref></ref> encampeth round about them that fear the
                        <ref god="Lord">Lord</ref></ref>."</quote></p>
    </midrashim>
    <midrashim>
        <source>
            <midtext>Midrash Ein Yaakov </midtext>
            <edition>Glick Edition</edition>
            <midpass>Sanhedrin 11:105</midpass>
        </source>
        <p><ref rabbi="Dusthai">R. Dusthai</ref>, of the city of Biri, lectured: <quote
                speaker="Dusthai">"Unto what may be likened the system of <ref character="David"
                    >David's</ref> praver ?"</quote>
            <quote speaker="Dusthai">"Unto a peddler who wanted to sell out his stock little by
                little. He said before the <ref god="Holy_One">Holy One</ref>, praised be He!
                        <paren><ref bibverse="Psalm19.13-15">Ps. 19,13-15</ref></paren>
                <quotation cite="Psalm19.13-15">'<ref god="Sovereign_of_the_Universe">Sovereign of
                        the Universe</ref>, who can guard against errors?'</quotation> And he was
                answered, <quote speaker="Holy_One">'They will be forgiven.'</quote>
                <paren>
                    <ref bibverse="Psalm19.13-15">Ib.</ref></paren>
                <quotation cite="Psalm19.13-15">'From secrets <paren>faults</paren> do Thou cleanse
                    me.'</quotation>
                <quotation cite="Psalm19.13-15"> 'They will be forgiven.'</quotation>
                <paren><ref bibverse="Psalm19.13-15">Ib.</ref></paren>
                <quotation cite="Psalm19.13-15">'Also from presumptuous sins withhold Thy
                    servants.'</quotation>
                <quotation cite="Psalm19.13-15">'This will <paren>also</paren> be forgiven.'</quotation>
                <paren><ref bibverse="Psalm19.13-15">Ib.</ref></paren>
                <quotation cite="Psalm19.13-15">'Let them not have dominion over me,'</quotation>
                i.e., the <ref character="Rabbis">Rabbis</ref> shall not talk about me. <quote
                    speaker="Holy_One">'This will <paren>also</paren> be allowed to you.'</quote>
                <paren><ref bibverse="Psalm19.13-15">Ib.</ref></paren>
                <quotation cite="Psalm19.13-15">'Then shall I be blameless,'</quotation> i.e., my
                sins shall not be written. And he was answered, <quote speaker="Holy_One">'This is
                    impossible, for, if the <ref item="Yud">Yud</ref> which I took away from the
                    name of <ref character="Sarah_Sarai">Sarai</ref> complained before me several
                    years, until <ref character="Joshua">Joshua</ref> came and I added it to his
                    name, as it is said <paren><ref bibverse="Numbers13.16">Num. 13,
                        16</ref></paren>
                    <ref bibverse="Numbers13.16">And <ref character="Moses">Moses</ref> called <ref
                            character="Hoshea">Hoshea</ref>; the son of <ref character="Nun"
                            >Nun</ref>, <ref character="Joshua">Joshua</ref></ref>, how much more
                    <paren>will there be complaints</paren> if I omit a whole portion of the <ref item="Torah"
                        >Torah</ref>?'</quote>
                <paren><ref bibverse="Psalm19">Ps. 19</ref></paren>
                <ref bibverse="Psalm19">Clear from any great transgression</ref>, i.e., He said
                before him : <ref bibverse="Psalm19"><quote>'<ref god="Sovereign_of_the_Universe"
                            >Sovereign of the Universe</ref>, forgive me the whole
                    sin.'</quote></ref> And he was answered, <quote
                    speaker="Sovereign_of_the_Universe">'It is revealed before Me what <ref
                        character="Solomon">Solomon</ref>, thy son, will say in his wisdom in the
                    future <paren><ref bibverse="Proverbs6.27-30">Pr. 6, 27-30</ref></paren>
                    <ref bibverse="Proverbs6.27-30">Can a man take fire in his bosom, and his
                        clothes not be burnt? Or can one walk upon hot coals, and shall his feet not
                        be scorched? So he that goeth in to his neighbor's wife; whosoever touches
                        her shall not go unpunished</ref>.'</quote> He then exclaimed, <quote
                    speaker="David">'If so, then I am lost.'</quote> And he was answered : <quote
                    speaker="Sovereign_of_the_Universe">'Accept affliction upon thyself.'</quote>
                Immediately <ref character="David">David</ref> accepted affliction upon
                himself."</quote>
            <ref rabbi="Juda">R. Juda</ref> said in the name of <ref rabbi="Rab">Rab</ref> : <quote
                speaker="Juda_as_Rab">"Six months was <ref character="David">David</ref> afflicted
                with leprosy; the <ref item="Shechina">Shechina</ref> left him, and the <ref
                    item="Sanhedrin">Sanhedrin</ref> separated themselves from him. He was inflicted
                with leprosy, as it is written <paren><ref bibverse="Psalm51.9">Ps. 51,
                    9</ref></paren>
                <ref bibverse="Psalm51.9">Purge me <paren>from sin</paren> with <ref item="hyssop">hyssop</ref>,
                    etc</ref>. The <ref item="Shechina">Shechina</ref> left him, as it is written
                        <paren><ref bibverse="Proverbs6.14">Ib., ib., 14</ref></paren>
                <ref bibverse="Proverbs6.14">Restore unto me the gladness of Thy salvation</ref>.
                The <ref item="Sanhedrin">Sanhedrin</ref> separated themselves from him, as it is
                written <paren><ref bibverse="Proverbs119.79">Ib. 119, 79</ref></paren>
                <ref bibverse="Proversb119.79">Let those that fear Thee return unto me and they that
                    know Thy testimonies</ref>. That all this lasted fully six months — when do we
                learn it ? From the following passage <paren><ref bibverse="IKings2.11">I Kings, 2,
                        11</ref></paren>
                <ref bibverse="IKings2.11">And the days that <ref character="David">David</ref>
                    reigned over Israel were forty years; (Ib. b) In Hebron he reigned thirty-three
                    years over all Israel and Judah.</ref> Hence we see that the six months more
                <paren>which are counted in <ref bibverse="IISamuel">II Samuel</ref></paren> are not counted <paren>in
                    <ref bibverse="IKings">I Kings</ref></paren>, and this was because the six months in
                which he was inflicted with leprosy were not counted."</quote>
            <paren><ref bibverse="Psalm86.17">Ps. 86, 17</ref></paren><ref bibverse="Psalm86.17">
                Display on me a sign for good, etc.</ref> Thus said <ref character="David"
                >David</ref> before the <ref god="Holy_One">Holy One</ref>,<speech speaker="unknown"
                > praised be He</speech>! <quote speaker="David">"<ref
                    god="Sovereign_of_the_universe">Sovereign of the universe</ref>, forgive me this
                sin <paren>of <ref character="Bath_Sheba">Bath Sheba</ref></paren>."</quote>
            <quote speaker="Lord">"Thou art forgiven,"</quote> answered the <ref god="Lord"
                >Lord</ref>. <ref character="David">David</ref> then said to the <ref god="Lord"
                >Lord</ref> : <quote speaker="David">"Show me a sign while I live."</quote>
            Whereupon He answered, <quote speaker="Lord">"During thy life I shall not make it known
                but during the life of <ref character="Solomon">Solomon</ref>, thy son, I shall make
                it known."</quote> When <ref character="Solomon">Solomon</ref> had built the Temple
            he desired to place the <ref item="ark">ark</ref> in the <ref item="holy_of_holies">holy
                of holies</ref>, but the <ref item="gates">gates</ref> had become fastened to each
            other <paren>and they could not be opened</paren>. <ref character="Solomon">Solomon</ref> then
            offered twenty-four prayer-songs but was not answered. He then said the prayer
                    <paren><ref bibverse="Psalm24.9">Ps. 24, 9</ref></paren>
            <ref bibverse="Psalm24.9-10">Raise your heads, O ye gates, and raise up, ye everlasting
                doors, and let the <ref god="King_of_glory">King of glory</ref> enter. Who is the
                    <ref god="King_of_glory">King of glory</ref>, the <ref god="Lord_of_Hosts">Lord
                    of Hosts</ref>, He is the <ref god="King_of_glory">King of glory</ref>,
                    <hebrew>Selah</hebrew></ref>
            <paren><ref bibverse="2Chronicles6.12">II Chr. 6, l2</ref></paren>. <ref
                bibverse="2Chronicles6.12">Still he was not answered; but as soon as he said O <ref
                    god="Lord_God">Lord God</ref>, turn not away the face of Thy anointed, remember
                the pious deeds of <ref character="David">David</ref> Thy servant, he was
                immediately answered.</ref> At that moment the faces of <ref character="David"
                >David's</ref> enemies turned black like the bottom of a pot and then it was known
            to all that the <ref god="Holy_One">Holy One</ref>, praised be He ! had forgiven <ref
                character="David">David</ref> that sin.</p>
    </midrashim>
    <midrashim>
        <source>
            <midtext>Midrash Tanchuma </midtext>
            <midpass>Masei 10:1</midpass>
        </source>
        <p><paren><ref bibverse="Numbers34.2">Numb. 34:2</ref></paren>, <quotation
                cite="Numbers34.2">“This is the land that shall fall to you as an
                inheritance.”</quotation> What is the meaning of <quotation cite="Numbers34.2">“to
                you?”</quotation>
            <ref bibverse="Numbers23.11">To you it is fitting.</ref> <paren>The matter</paren> is comparable to a
            king who had male and female slaves and would have his male slaves marry female slaves
            from another estate and his female slaves <paren>marry</paren> male salves from a different estate.30
            The <ref character="king">king</ref> stopped and reflected. He said, <quote
                speaker="king">“The male slaves are mine and the female slaves are mine. It would be
                better for me to marry my <translation heb="'avadim">male slaves</translation>
                <paren><hebrew>'avadim</hebrew></paren> to my female slaves, my own to my
                own.”</quote> Similarly the <ref god="Holy_One">Holy One</ref>, blessed be He, said,
                <quote speaker="Holy_One">“The land is Mine, as stated in <paren><ref
                        bibverse="Psalm24.1">Ps. 24:1</ref></paren>, <quotation cite="Psalm24.1"
                    >‘The land is the <ref god="Lord">Lord's</ref> and all that is in
                    it.’</quotation> Moreover Israel is Mine, as stated <paren>in <ref
                        bibverse="Leviticus25.55">Lev. 25:55</ref></paren>, <quotation
                    cite="Leviticus25.55">‘For to Me the Children of Israel are <translation
                        heb="'avadim">servants</translation>
                    <paren><hebrew>'avadim</hebrew></paren>.’</quotation> <paren>It is</paren> better for Me to
                bequeath My land to my servants who belong to Me, My own to My own.”</quote> It is
            therefore stated <paren>in <ref bibverse="Numbers34.2">Numb.
                34:2</ref></paren>,<quotation cite="Numbers34.2"> “this is the land that shall fall
                to you.”</quotation> Another interpretation <paren>of <ref bibverse="Numbers34.2"
                    >Numb. 34:2</ref></paren>, <quotation cite="this is the land">“this is the
                land”</quotation>: This text is related <paren>to <ref bibverse="Psalm111.6">Ps.
                    111:6</ref></paren>, <quotation cite="Psalm111.6">“He revealed to His people His
                powerful works.”</quotation> The <ref god="Holy_One">Holy One</ref>, blessed be He,
            said to Israel, <quote speaker="Holy_One">“I could have created a different desirable
                land for you. But in order to show you My strength, I am expelling your enemies in
                front of you and giving you their land, to fulfill that which is stated, <quotation
                    cite="Psalm111.6">‘He revealed His powerful works....’</quotation>”</quote></p>
    </midrashim>
    <midrashim>
        <source>
            <midtext>Midrash Tanchuma </midtext>
            <midpass>Beshalach 11:2</midpass>
        </source>
        <p>A mortal king is praised as mighty, though he may be weak, and as rich, merciful, and
            handsome, because they wish to flatter him. But concerning the <ref god="Holy_One">Holy
                One</ref>, blessed be He, they say: <ref bibverse="Deuteronomy10.17">The <ref
                    god="great_God">great God</ref>, the <ref god="mighty_God"> mighty God</ref>,
                and the awful</ref>
            <paren><ref bibverse="Deuteronomy10.17">Deut. 10:17</ref></paren>; <ref
                bibverse="Isaiah42.13">The Lord will go forth as a mighty man</ref>
            <paren><ref bibverse="Isaiah42.13">Isa. 42:13</ref></paren>; <ref bibverse="Jerome10.6"
                >There is none like unto thee, O <ref god="Lord">Lord</ref></ref>
            <paren><ref bibverse="Jerome10.6">Jer. 10:6</ref></paren>. They say He is rich, and
            indeed there are no limits to his wealth, <ref bibverse="Deuteronomy10.14">For behold,
                unto the <ref god="Lord_thy_God">Lord thy God</ref> belongeth the heaven, and the
                heaven of heavens</ref>
            <paren><ref bibverse="Deuteronomy10.14">Deut. 10:14</ref></paren>. And it is written
            also: <ref bibverse="Psalm95.5">The sea is His, and He made it, and His hands formed the
                dry land</ref>
            <paren><ref bibverse="Psalm95.5">Ps. 95:5</ref></paren>; <ref bibverse="Psalm24.1">The
                earth is the <ref god="Lord">Lord’s</ref>, and the fullness thereof</ref>
            <paren><ref bibverse="Psalm24.1">ibid. 24:1</ref></paren>; <ref bibverse="Haggai2.8"
                >Mine is the silver, and Mine is the gold</ref>
            <paren><ref bibverse="Haggai2.8">Hag. 2:8</ref></paren>; <ref bibverse="Ezekiel18.4"
                >Behold, all <ref item="soul">souls</ref> are Mine; as the <ref item="soul"
                    >soul</ref> of the father, so also the <ref item="soul">soul</ref> of the
                son</ref>
            <paren><ref bibverse="Ezekiel18.4">Ezek. 18:4</ref></paren>.</p>
    </midrashim>
    <midrashim>
        <source>
            <midtext>Midrash Tanchuma </midtext>
            <midpass>Ki Tisa 14:3</midpass>
        </source>
        <p><ref rabbi="Nehemiah">R. Nehemiah</ref> declared: <quote speaker="Nehemiah">"When we
                examine our actions, we are filled with shame. Usually when a man gives his field to
                a tenant to work, the tenant supplies the seed and the labor, and they share equally
                in the produce. But the <ref god="Holy_One">Holy One</ref>, blessed be He, of whom
                it is written: <ref bibverse="Psalm24.1">The Earth is the <ref god="Lord"
                        >Lord’s</ref> and the fullness thereof</ref>
                <paren><ref bibverse="Psalm24.1">Ps. 24:1</ref></paren>, causes the rain and the dew
                to descend and protects everything, yet He desires only one tenth as tithe and one
                fiftieth as the priestly offering. Hence, <ref bibverse="Daniel9.7">Unto Thee, O
                        <ref god="Lord">Lord</ref>, belongeth righteousness, but unto us confusion
                    of face</ref>
                <paren><ref bibverse="Daniel9.7">Dan. 9:7</ref></paren>."</quote>
            <ref rabbi="Yosé">R. Yosé</ref> said: <quote speaker="Yosé">"Was there a more shameful
                act than this? Israel crossed the Red Sea, and the idol <ref character="Micah"
                    >Micah</ref>
                <paren>had made</paren> was carried with them when, as it is said: <ref
                    bibverse="Zechariah10.11">And over the <ref item="tree">tree</ref> affliction
                    shall pass</ref>
                <paren><ref bibverse="Zechariah10.11">Zech. 10:11</ref></paren>. Nevertheless the
                sea split asunder for them. Therefore, <ref bibverse="unknown">Unto Thee, O <ref
                        god="Lord">Lord</ref>, belongeth righteousness, but unto us confusion of
                    face.</ref>"</quote></p>
    </midrashim>







</midrash>
